<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<file xmlns="http://bibtexml.sf.net/">
    <entry id="sagan1967origin">
        <article>
            <author>Sagan, Lynn</author>
            <title>On the origin of mitosing cells</title>
            <journal>Journal of theoretical biology</journal>
            <year>1967</year>
            <volume>14</volume>
            <number>3</number>
            <pages>225--IN6</pages>
            <abstract>A theory of the origin of eukaryotic cells (“higher” cells which divide by classical mitosis) is presented. By hypothesis, three fundamental organelles the mitochondria, the photosynthetic plastids and the (9+2) basal bodies of flagella were themselves once free-living (prokaryotic) cells. The evolution of photosynthesis under the anaerobic conditions of the early atmosphere to form anaerobic bacteria, photosynthetic bacteria and eventually blue-green algae (and protoplastids) is described. The subsequent evolution of aerobic metabolism in prokaryotes to form aerobic bacteria (protoflagella and protomitochondria) presumably occurred during the transition to the oxidizing atmosphere. Classical mitosis evolved in protozoan-type cells millions of years after the evolution of photosynthesis. A plausible scheme for the origin of classical mitosis in primitive amoeboflagellates is presented. During the course of the evolution of mitosis, photosynthetic plastids (themselves derived from prokaryotes) were symbiotically acquired by some of these protozoans to form the eukaryotic algae and the green plants.

The cytological, biochemical and paleontological evidence for this theory is presented, along with suggestions for further possible experimental verification. The implications of this scheme for the systematics of the lower organisms is discussed</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1016/0022-5193(67)90079-3</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="bibliometrix">
        <article>
            <author>Massimo Aria and Corrado Cuccurullo</author>
            <title>bibliometrix: An R-tool for comprehensive science mapping analysis</title>
            <journal>Journal of Informetrics</journal>
            <year>2017</year>
            <volume>11</volume>
            <number>4</number>
            <pages>959-975</pages>
            <abstract>The use of bibliometrics is gradually extending to all disciplines. It is particularly suitable for science mapping at a time when the emphasis on empirical contributions is producing voluminous, fragmented, and controversial research streams. Science mapping is complex and unwieldly because it is multi-step and frequently requires numerous and diverse software tools, which are not all necessarily freeware. Although automated workflows that integrate these software tools into an organized data flow are emerging, in this paper we propose a unique open-source tool, designed by the authors, called bibliometrix, for performing comprehensive science mapping analysis. bibliometrix supports a recommended workflow to perform bibliometric analyses. As it is programmed in R, the proposed tool is flexible and can be rapidly upgraded and integrated with other statistical R-packages. It is therefore useful in a constantly changing science such as bibliometrics.</abstract>
            <url>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.joi.2017.08.007</url>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="ggplot2">
        <book>
            <author>Hadley Wickham</author>
            <title>ggplot2: Elegant Graphics for Data Analysis</title>
            <publisher>Springer-Verlag New York</publisher>
            <year>2016</year>
            <abstract>ggplot2 is a system for declaratively creating graphics, based on The Grammar of Graphics. You provide the data, tell ggplot2 how to map variables to aesthetics, what graphical primitives to use, and it takes care of the details.</abstract>
            <isbn>978-3-319-24277-4</isbn>
            <url>https://ggplot2.tidyverse.org</url>
        </book>
    </entry>
    <entry id="ggrepel">
        <manual>
            <author>Kamil Slowikowski</author>
            <title>ggrepel: Automatically Position Non-Overlapping Text Labels with 'ggplot2'</title>
            <year>2021</year>
            <note>R package version 0.9.1</note>
            <url>https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=ggrepel</url>
        </manual>
    </entry>
    <entry id="jenny1946arrangement">
        <article>
            <author>Jenny, Hans</author>
            <title>Arrangement of soil series and types according to functions of soil-forming factors</title>
            <journal>Soil Science</journal>
            <year>1946</year>
            <volume>61</volume>
            <number>5</number>
            <pages>375--392</pages>
            <abstract>In the United States, thousands of soil series and types have been mapped and described in great detail. The problem of classifying this huge array of soil units either on a state-wide or national basis is of concern to every soil surveyor and pedologist. The writer believes that a grouping of soil series and types in terms of functions of soil-forming factors has certain merits, for it emphasizes a logical interlacing of soil units and is amenable to geographic expression. The purpose of this paper is to present the theory of this approach and to give practical applications.</abstract>
            <url>https://journals.lww.com/soilsci/Citation/1946/05000/Arrangement_of_Soil_Series_and_Types_According_to.5.aspx</url>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="simonson1997early">
        <article>
            <author>Simonson, Roy W</author>
            <title>Early teaching in USA of Dokuchaiev factors of soil formation</title>
            <journal>Soil Science Society of America Journal</journal>
            <year>1997</year>
            <volume>61</volume>
            <number>1</number>
            <pages>11--16</pages>
            <abstract>Teaching of the factors of soil formation first recognized by Dokuchaiev began in the USA in the late 1920s and early 1930s. Reports on their functions had been available in English prior to and early in the 20th century, but Americans were not receptive to the Russian idea of five factors, still holding that soil formation consisted of rock weathering. Following the First International Congress of Soil Science and related activities in 1927, however, the Dokuchaiev factors were soon introduced in pedology courses, first by J.C. Russell in Nebraska and next by Charles E. Kellogg in North Dakota. Basically the same for the two men, the presentation of the five factors illustrated here is from the course taught by Kellogg in 1932. The presentation was chiefly a combination of lectures and reading assignments but included limited field study. Slightly less than half of the lectures in a three-hour course were about the factors of soil formation. Evident now, the lectures and reading assignments reflect the state of knowledge of their day, including both gaps and errors. At the same time, the coverage is impressive when considered against the limited study of soils in the world accomplished up to that time.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.2136/sssaj1997.03615995006100010002x</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="ibanez2005classical">
        <article>
            <author>Ibáñez, Juan Jose and Ramos, M Ruiz and Zinck, JA and Brú, A</author>
            <title>Classical pedology questioned and defended</title>
            <journal>EURASIAN SOIL SCIENCE C/C OF POCHVOVEDENIE</journal>
            <year>2005</year>
            <volume>38</volume>
            <pages>S75</pages>
            <abstract>Classical pedology is increasingly being questioned about its three main components: soil classification, soil mapping, and the concept of soil as a natural body on the landscape. We discuss some of the concerns most frequently put forth, in particular the pedometric approach with its focus on soil variability and its effect on making soil classes and map units. We analyze these issues in the light of the philosophy of science and by comparison with similar issues in the field of biological sciences. Situations where soil bodies can be delineated with sharp boundaries are probably as frequent in nature as situations with gradual variations of soil properties requiring a fuzzy mapping approach. Hierarchical taxonomies are, in general, appropriate to classify soils, as they reflect the tree model that the human mind chooses to classify natural objects. Soil classification results, expressed as pedotaxa, reveal mathematical structures similar to those of biotaxa, while pedodiversity, analyzed on the basis of pedotaxa richness, follows patterns similar to those of biodiversity. Universal classifications are better communication tools to compare soils within regions than single-property maps. Classical pedology needs to evolve towards a new soil paradigm and to promote synergy with the pedometric approach.</abstract>
            <url>https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Juan-Ibanez-5/publication/287331080_Classical_pedology_questioned_and_defended/links/56758ad808ae125516e72451/Classical-pedology-questioned-and-defended.pdf</url>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="ibanez2012archive">
        <article>
            <author>Ibáñez, Juan Jose and Krasilnikov, Pavel V and Saldana, Asuncion</author>
            <title>Archive and refugia of soil organisms: applying a pedodiversity framework for the conservation of biological and non-biological heritages</title>
            <journal>Journal of Applied Ecology</journal>
            <year>2012</year>
            <volume>49</volume>
            <number>6</number>
            <pages>1267--1277</pages>
            <abstract>The pedosphere is a part of our natural heritage. Soils should be considered both for their biological and for their geological resources. During the Anthropocene, human activities have dramatically changed the land surface and remodified soil cover, resulting in many natural pedotaxa being at risk of extinction. Recently, biogeographers and ecologists recognized that numerous biotaxa should be considered as edaphic endemisms, and as a consequence, in situ soil preservation is important relative to both its biological and geological value. This contribution discusses the similarity and differences between biodiversity and pedodiversity and proposes using pedodiversity as a surrogate measure of above-ground biodiversity and an indicator of below-ground biodiversity. Another objective is to explore the relevance of soil diversity to soil ecology by illustrating how the analysis of pedotaxa and their genetic soil horizons can be applied in conservation biology. To preserve biological and geological heritage inherent to the pedosphere, we propose to design a network of soil reserves. The proposed network could also be an efficient way to preserve soil characteristics and qualities of undisturbed soils that would become benchmarks for soil monitoring programs. Synthesis and applications. The coincidence between patterns of biodiversity and pedodiversity offers a new and unexplored direction for understanding the genesis of biological and non-biological assemblages and the spatial patterns of soils and living organisms. Pedodiversity can be used as a practical surrogate indicator of soil diversity. We provide a pedodiversity framework for the design of a network of soil reserves for the preservation and monitoring of soil biodiversity. This new framework could contribute toward the development of a unified theory of natural diversity and to understanding the role of the pedosphere in the provision of ecosystem services.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2664.2012.02213.x</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="usda1999">
        <book>
            <author>{Soil Survey Staff}</author>
            <title>Soil Taxonomy: A Basic System of Soil Classification for Making and Interpreting Soil Surveys.</title>
            <publisher>USDA-Natural Resources Conservation Service</publisher>
            <year>1999</year>
            <edition>2nd Edition</edition>
            <url>https://www.nrcs.usda.gov/wps/PA_NRCSConsumption/download?cid=stelprdb1252094&amp;ext=pdf</url>
        </book>
    </entry>
    <entry id="usda2014">
        <book>
            <author>{Soil Survey Staff}</author>
            <title>Keys to Soil Taxonomy</title>
            <publisher>USDA-Natural Resources Conservation Service</publisher>
            <year>2014</year>
            <edition>12th edition</edition>
            <url>https://www.nrcs.usda.gov/wps/PA_NRCSConsumption/download?cid=stelprdb1252094&amp;ext=pdf</url>
        </book>
    </entry>
    <entry id="bibliometicErrors">
        <article>
            <author>Zhang, Zhongheng and Van Poucke, Sven and Goyal, Hemant and Rowley, Daniel and Zhong, Ming and Liu, Nan</author>
            <title>The top 2,000 cited articles in critical care medicine: A bibliometric analysis</title>
            <journal>Journal of Thoracic Disease</journal>
            <year>2018</year>
            <volume>10</volume>
            <number>4</number>
            <pages>2437--2447</pages>
            <month>04</month>
            <abstract>Background: The bibliometric analysis has been performed on several topics in critical care medicine (CCM) focusing on top 100 cited articles, but the analysis on CCM literature as a whole is missing. The present study aimed to perform a complete bibliometric analysis in the field of CCM.

Methods: An electronic search of the Scopus database was performed on Feb 13, 2018. The search strategy involved core terms related to CCM. The top 2,000 most cited articles in the field of CCM were included in the analysis. Descriptive statistics on these top-cited articles, country distributions, and journals are reported. Individual author’s productivity was assessed with the Lotka’s law. Co-occurrence of keywords was visualized with the Fruchterman-Reingold layout. The Walktrap algorithm was employed for clustering analysis.

Results: A total of 2,000 documents were included in the analysis with median citations of 386 times [interquartile range (IQR): 308–562 times]. The most cited article was the original paper that described the Acute Physiology and Chronic Health Evaluation (APACHE) II score. The included articles were published in 411 journals. The median number of documents published in one journal was 1, and the mean number was 4.9, indicating a skewed distribution. The maximum number of publications was 217 in CCM. Author’s productivity profile was significantly different from the Lotka’s law (P=0.001), with n and C values of 2.8 and 0.52, respectively. Fruchterman-Reingold network plot showed that studies involving human subject were the most common literature type. Sepsis was a major research topic that co-occurred with keywords such as disease severity, nonhuman, risk assessment and practice guideline.

Conclusions: The study performed bibliometric analyses of 2,000 top-cited articles in CCM. The most cited article was the one which developed the APACHE II score. Author’s productivity was significantly different from the Lotka’s law.</abstract>
            <doi>10.21037/jtd.2018.03.178</doi>
            <keywords>Bibliometric; critical care; sepsis; Lotka’s law; Fruchterman-Reingold layout; top cited</keywords>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="chertov2018edaphology">
        <article>
            <author>Chertov, OG and Nadporozhskaya, MA and Palenova, MM and Priputina, IV and others</author>
            <title>Edaphology in the structure of soil science and ecosystem ecology.</title>
            <journal>Russian journal of ecosystem ecology</journal>
            <year>2018</year>
            <volume>3</volume>
            <number>3</number>
            <abstract>Edaphology (Edaphologia, from Greek - soil for planting) is a science of soil as a habitat for living beings. On the contrary, pedopogy (Pedologia from Greek - leg as a thing for walking) is a science of soil properties and formation, namely genetic soil science. Soil science is a relatively young discipline studying the complex "bio-abiogenic" systems. Even the history of soil science is not simple, as the main term was duplicated: pedology and edaphology. Later, Edaphology was driven out from soil science into agricultural chemistry to solve edaphic problems for agricultural plants only. The genetic soil science had been mainly developing that time. However the edaphic problems remained and they were solved both within basic soil science and adjoined sciences. The edaphic component is clearly seen in ecological soil science (soil ecology) that appeared in the middle of the 20th century, but without a return to the initial terminology. In forest soil science, the concept of humus forms is directly related to edaphology because humus forms represent a classification of topsoil organic and organo-mineral horizons that determine the vegetation productivity and they are developed under the impact of the biological cycle in forest ecosystems. The European and North American soil-landscape classifications of forest sites also belong to edaphology. The plant ordination according to the scales of soil moisture and "richness" in ecological botany (geobotany) and lower layers of landscape classifications are of clearly edaphic origin as well. The restoration of the edaphic branch in soil science is necessary for addressing theoretical and especially practical problems in sustainable forest and environmental management under the rapidly changing environment and developing economy.</abstract>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="vernadsky1998biosphere">
        <book>
            <author>Vernadsky, Vladimir I.</author>
            <title>The biosphere</title>
            <publisher>Springer Science \&amp; Business Media</publisher>
            <year>1998</year>
            <abstract>Long unknown in the West, The Biosphere established the field of biogeochemistry and is one of the classic founding documents of what later became known as Gaia theory. It is the first sustained expression of the idea that life is a geological force that can change Earth's landforms, its climate, and even the contents of its atmosphere. A complete, unabridged translation has never before been available in English. This edition - complete with extensive annotations, an introductory essay placing the work in its historical context and explaining its relevance to readers today, and a foreword cosigned by a stellar group of international experts - will be the definitive edition of this classic work. "What Darwin did for life through time, Vernadsky did for life through space on a geological scale".</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1007/978-1-4612-1750-3</doi>
        </book>
    </entry>
    <entry id="petela2008approach">
        <article>
            <author>Petela, Richard</author>
            <title>An approach to the exergy analysis of photosynthesis</title>
            <journal>Solar Energy</journal>
            <year>2008</year>
            <volume>82</volume>
            <number>4</number>
            <pages>311--328</pages>
            <abstract>The present paper contributes to the classic thermodynamic analysis of photosynthesis. Photosynthesis is a complex endothermic process involving two kinds of matter; substance and radiation. This threefold study consists of: (1) an energy analysis (the energy conservation equation is developed to estimate the energy effects of the process); (2) entropy analysis (the changes of entropy are used to estimate the irreversibility of the component processes); and (3) exergy analysis (developed for thermodynamic evaluation of both kinds of matter). A simplified mathematical diffusive model of photosynthesis (controlled by diffusion of gases) is used to analyze key aspects of the problem. The corresponding terms of energy and exergy equations are compared and discussed. Photosynthesis is a highly irreversible process. In the calculation example the irreversibility loss is 97.4%. This increases slightly together with increasing temperatures of leaf and environment. On the contrary, the energy equation does not show any loss due to irreversibility.

In the calculation example for the presented model, the exergy degree of perfection for photosynthesis is 2.61% and the energy degree of perfection is 35.4%. The rate of sugar production is 3.21 × 10−9 kmol m−2 s−1. Heat transferred to the environment by radiation and convection is respectively 6.4% and 65.3%. The exergies of the radiant and convective heat are 0.003% and zero, respectively. The impacts on several output parameters (e.g. leaf temperature, sugar rate, degrees of perfection, etc.) were determined: the effect of varying input conditions (e.g. environmental temperature and humidity, leaf absorptivity, intensity of solar radiation, coefficient of convective heat transfer, and CO2 concentration). Some possibilities for further developing the exergy analysis are discussed.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.solener.2007.09.002</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="smith2012chemosynthesis">
        <article>
            <author>Smith, C</author>
            <title>Chemosynthesis in the deep-sea: life without the sun</title>
            <journal>Biogeosciences Discussions</journal>
            <year>2012</year>
            <volume>9</volume>
            <number>12</number>
            <pages>17037--17052</pages>
            <abstract>Chemosynthetic communities in the deep-sea can be found at hydrothermal vents, cold seeps, whale falls and wood falls. While these communities have been suggested to exist in isolation from solar energy, much of the life associated with them relies either directly or indirectly on photosynthesis in the surface waters of the oceans. The sun indirectly provides oxygen, a byproduct of photosynthesis, which aerobic chemosynthetic microorganisms require to synthesize organic carbon from CO2. Planktonic life stages of many vent and cold seep invertebrates also directly feed on photosynthetically produced organic matter as they disperse to new vent and seep systems. While a large portion of the life at deep-sea chemosynthetic habitats can be linked to the sun and so could not survive without it, a small portion of anaerobically chemosynthetic microorganisms can persist in its absence. These small and exotic organisms have developed a way of life in the deep-sea which involves the use of resources originating in their entirety from terrestrial sources.</abstract>
            <doi>10.5194/bgd-9-17037-2012</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="SWEETON1970479">
        <article>
            <author>F.H Sweeton and C.F Baes</author>
            <title>The solubility of magnetite and hydrolysis of ferrous ion in aqueous solutions at elevated temperatures</title>
            <journal>The Journal of Chemical Thermodynamics</journal>
            <year>1970</year>
            <volume>2</volume>
            <number>4</number>
            <pages>479-500</pages>
            <abstract>The solubility of magnetite (Fe3O4) in dilute aqueous solutions saturated with H2 at 1 atm at 25 °C has been measured at temperatures between 50 and 300 °C. The solutions have ranged from KOH of molality 400 × 10−6 mol kg−1 to HCl of molality 100 × 10−6 mol kg−1. The measurements were made by the continuous flow of solution over a bed of specially prepared pure magnetite. It was found that, under these conditions of temperature and hydrogen activity, Fe3O4 does not transform to HFe5O8 or γ-Fe2O3. The results have been fitted with a scheme of soluble species consisting of Fe2+, FeOH+, Fe(OH)2, and Fe(OH)3−, and the equilibrium constants for the reactions (13Fe3O4 + (2−b)H+ + 13H2(g) = Fe(OH)(2−b)+b + 43H2O have been calculated. The temperature coefficients of the constants for Fe2+ and FeOH+ were found to be negative, and those of Fe(OH)2 and Fe(OH)3−, positive. The estimated values of ΔHo and ΔSo for these reactions are also given. The value of log10(K/mol kg−1) at 25 °C for the reaction Fe2+ + H2O = FeOH+ + H+, has been determined by extrapolation of the solubilities and has been found to be (−9.3 ± 0.5). The solubilities have been combined with other thermodynamic data to calculate ΔGo, ΔHo, and ΔSo for the formation of Fe2+ and FeOH+ by the reaction: Fe + bH2O + (2−b) H+ = Fe(OH)(2−b)+b + H2(g). The extrapolated value of ΔGo for the formation of Fe2+ at 25 °C by this reaction gives an Eo of (0.475 ± 0.010) V.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1016/0021-9614(70)90098-4</doi>
            <issn>0021-9614</issn>
            <url>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/0021961470900984</url>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="schrodinger1948que">
        <book>
            <author>Schrödinger, Erwin</author>
            <title>¿Qué es la vida?</title>
            <publisher>Espasa-Calpe</publisher>
            <year>1948</year>
            <url>https://d1wqtxts1xzle7.cloudfront.net/35910770/QEV-with-cover-page-v2.pdf?Expires=1669298571&amp;Signature=NknyJSUU~~LV9mg35~czbSl4ZyEJUrCsTlkUsh1-3Vg6xjnJi5Q4q-OcDmNDBCYiviwhK3DWspw6FZ~o6Pf6lvDroZVRrPyD5Y~YY~vXc-3EDsU7cgvcDy64kzaQYeGKBhg3bMuYPDtoX7s8-hfWKszhUib56mNJccvPtlh17XCB5Jpc15TeViYzF9s66Q~9gE80xktqscIi98Y0-o2T-B7OtDzbBdr~fCMYGYX40CxKytsuVFSDxs6MJLe1QNgr5Yjnw50PTzWeQuK1QUedJemb8Cy8XGXFP~ld4h7XO~87iaDUDXubkEolnH9SwnfBBCmLmQjAXXItpfkGB505Hw__&amp;Key-Pair-Id=APKAJLOHF5GGSLRBV4ZA</url>
        </book>
    </entry>
    <entry id="schwarz1909probability">
        <article>
            <author>Schwarz, EHL</author>
            <title>The probability of large meteorites having fallen upon the Earth</title>
            <journal>The Journal of Geology</journal>
            <year>1909</year>
            <volume>17</volume>
            <number>2</number>
            <pages>124--135</pages>
            <abstract>From time to time the accumulation of new facts in any one science renders it necessary to examine into the cause for the existence of certain features, and to see whether some small points which rendered the earlier explanations not altogether satisfactory, may not be
entirely accounted for in the light of the new experience. In many cases this proceeding has resulted in the entire recasting of our ideas concerning certain phenomena, especially in the physical sciences where laboratory demonstration can prove the truth of the new law; in geology, the unwieldy nature of the subject-matter, and the different aspects which the same country or mountain may present to different observers, renders this method somewhat unsatisfactory. It must, however, be done, if the science is to progress, although in the end a categorical statement that the new explanation is a true one, and the old one a false one, cannot be made. It is the purpose of this paper to pick out certain facts in connection with the amygdaloidal lavas of Prieska, Cape Colony, which cannot readily be explained on any of the theories of igneous extrusion, and to see whether they cannot be accounted for on some other theory; I shall summarise what is known of the fall of large meteorites and point out in what way the phenomena connected with these show certain significant resemblances to those exhibited by the amygdaloids of Prieska, tentatively suggesting that in the past huge bolides fell on the earth, melted the rocks in the neighborhood of the fall and produced these great fields of lava.</abstract>
            <url>https://www.journals.uchicago.edu/doi/pdf/10.1086/621595</url>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="crutzen2006anthropocene">
        <incollection>
            <author>Crutzen, Paul J</author>
            <title>The “anthropocene”</title>
            <booktitle>Earth system science in the anthropocene</booktitle>
            <publisher>Springer</publisher>
            <year>2021</year>
            <pages>13--18</pages>
            <abstract>Human activities are exerting increasing impacts on the environment on all scales, in many ways outcompeting natural processes. This includes the manufacturing of hazardous chemical compounds which are not produced by nature, such as for instance
the chlorofluorocarbon gases which are responsible for the “ozone hole”. Because human activities have also grown to become significant geological forces, for instance through land use changes, deforestation and fossil fuel burning, it is justified to assign the term “anthropocene” to the current geological epoch. This epoch may be defined to have started about two centuries ago, coinciding with James Watt’s design of the steam engine in 1784.</abstract>
            <url>http://ndl.ethernet.edu.et/bitstream/123456789/74935/1/Eckart%20Ehlers.pdf</url>
        </incollection>
    </entry>
    <entry id="bonneuil2015geological">
        <incollection>
            <author>Bonneuil, Christophe</author>
            <title>The geological turn: narratives of the Anthropocene</title>
            <booktitle>The Anthropocene and the global environmental crisis</booktitle>
            <publisher>Routledge</publisher>
            <year>2015</year>
            <pages>17--31</pages>
            <url>https://library.oapen.org/bitstream/handle/20.500.12657/62310/9781317589099.pdf?sequence=1#page=30</url>
        </incollection>
    </entry>
    <entry id="latour">
        <book>
            <author>Bruno Latour and Steve Woolgar</author>
            <editor>Alianza Editorial</editor>
            <title>La vida en el laboratorio, La construcción de los hechos científicos</title>
            <publisher>Alianza Universal</publisher>
            <year>1995</year>
            <isbn>84-206-2813-1</isbn>
        </book>
    </entry>
    <entry id="Marcuse1993">
        <book>
            <author>Marcuse, Herbert</author>
            <title>El hombre unidimensional</title>
            <publisher>Plantea-Agostini</publisher>
            <year>1993</year>
            <address>Barcelona, Spain</address>
        </book>
    </entry>
    <entry id="Popper1993">
        <inbook>
            <chapter>La Falsabilidad como criterio de demarcación</chapter>
            <pages>39-42</pages>
            <month>#nov#</month>
            <year>1993</year>
            <author>Popper, Karl</author>
            <bibtexkey>Popper1993</bibtexkey>
            <publisher>Tecnos</publisher>
            <language>en</language>
            <title>Logica de la investigacion</title>
        </inbook>
    </entry>
    <entry id="wood2008daisyworld">
        <article>
            <author>Wood, Andrew J and Ackland, Graeme J and Dyke, James G and Williams, Hywel TP and Lenton, Timothy M</author>
            <title>Daisyworld: A review</title>
            <journal>Reviews of Geophysics</journal>
            <year>2008</year>
            <volume>46</volume>
            <number>1</number>
            <month>jan</month>
            <abstract>Daisyworld is a simple planetary model designed to show the long-term effects of coupling between life and its environment. Its original form was introduced by James Lovelock as a defense against criticism that his Gaia theory of the Earth as a self-regulating homeostatic system requires teleological control rather than being an emergent property. The central premise, that living organisms can have major effects on the climate system, is no longer controversial. The Daisyworld model has attracted considerable interest from the scientific community and has now established itself as a model independent of, but still related to, the Gaia theory. Used widely as both a teaching tool and as a basis for more complex studies of feedback systems, it has also become an important paradigm for the understanding of the role of biotic components when modeling the Earth system. This paper collects the accumulated knowledge from the study of Daisyworld and provides the reader with a concise account of its important properties. We emphasize the increasing amount of exact analytic work on Daisyworld and are able to bring together and summarize these results from different systems for the first time. We conclude by suggesting what a more general model of life-environment interaction should be based on.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1029/2006RG000217</doi>
            <keywords>Daisyworld; Gaia; Homeostasis</keywords>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="costanza1992ecological">
        <book>
            <author>Costanza, Robert</author>
            <title>Ecological economics: the science and management of sustainability</title>
            <publisher>Columbia University Press</publisher>
            <year>1992</year>
        </book>
    </entry>
    <entry id="malthus">
        <book>
            <author>Malthus, Thomas Robert</author>
            <editor>Ediciones Akal S.A</editor>
            <title>Ensayo sobre el principio de la población</title>
            <year>1990</year>
            <isbn>84-7600-534-2</isbn>
        </book>
    </entry>
    <entry id="darwinMalthus"/>
    <entry id="costanza2020valuing">
        <article>
            <author>Costanza, Robert</author>
            <title>Valuing natural capital and ecosystem services toward the goals of efficiency, fairness, and sustainability</title>
            <journal>Ecosystem Services</journal>
            <year>2020</year>
            <volume>43</volume>
            <pages>101096</pages>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ecoser.2020.101096</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="captandoGenomas">
        <book>
            <author>Margulis, Lynn and Sagan, Dorion</author>
            <title>Captando genomas</title>
            <publisher>Editorial Kairos</publisher>
            <year>2003</year>
            <isbn>9788472455511</isbn>
            <url>http://www.librosmaravillosos.com/captandogenomas/pdf/Captando%20genomas%20-%20Lynn%20Margulis%20y%20Dorion%20Sagan.pdf</url>
        </book>
    </entry>
    <entry id="kutschera2022origin">
        <article>
            <author>Kutschera, Ulrich and Khanna, Rajnish</author>
            <title>The origin of chloroplasts: Constantin S. Merezhkowsky (1855--1921) and symbiogenesis</title>
            <journal>Journal of Plant Biochemistry and Biotechnology</journal>
            <year>2022</year>
            <volume>31</volume>
            <number>1</number>
            <pages>178--184</pages>
            <abstract>One century ago (Jan. 9, 1921), the Russian biologist Constantin S. Merezhkowsky, who proposed the endosymbiotic origin of plastids, committed suicide at the age of 66 years. Here, we provide Merezhkowsky’s original observations on chloroplast development in seedlings and recount the career and achievements of the “founding father” of this Anti-Darwinian symbiogenesis-theory of cell evolution via cooperation and functional integration. In his phylogenetic tree published in 1910, Merezhkowsky distinguished between organisms that belong to all five Kingdoms of Life (Monera, Protoctista, Fungi, Animalia and Plantae), proposed a hypothesis concerning the origin of life, and argued that chloroplasts are descendants of once free-living cyanobacteria. A few years later, the American biologist Ivan E. Wallin (1883–1969) proposed that mitochondria evolved from ancient bacteria. The Merezhkowsky-Wallin-principle of organelle origin is summarized, and its current status critically evaluated. In addition, the contributions of Lynn Margulis (1938–2011), who died ten years ago, are outlined and evaluated in the light of Merezhkowsky’s pioneering work that led to the establishment of “evolutionary cell biology” as an independent research agenda.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1007/s13562-021-00717-6</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="Merrill1897">
        <book>
            <author>Merrill, George Perkins</author>
            <title>A treatise on rocks, rock-weathering and soils</title>
            <publisher>Macmillan</publisher>
            <year>1897</year>
            <url>https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/c/c7/A_treatise_on_rocks%2C_rock-weathering_and_soils_%28IA_treatirocks00merrrich%29.pdf</url>
        </book>
    </entry>
    <entry id="Dokutchaev1893">
        <book>
            <author>Dokutchaev, Vasily Vasilyevich</author>
            <title>The Russian Steppes: Study of the soil in Russia, its past and present</title>
            <publisher>Department of Agriculture, Ministry of Crown Domains</publisher>
            <year>1893</year>
        </book>
    </entry>
    <entry id="Lovelock1993">
        <book>
            <author>Lovelock, James</author>
            <title>Edades de Gaia</title>
            <publisher>Tusquets Barcelona</publisher>
            <year>1995</year>
            <edition>2</edition>
            <isbn>84-7223-646-3</isbn>
        </book>
    </entry>
    <entry id="Margulis1998">
        <book>
            <author>Margulis, Lynn</author>
            <title>Symbiotic Planet</title>
            <publisher>Basic Books</publisher>
            <year>1998</year>
            <address>London, England</address>
            <month>#nov#</month>
        </book>
    </entry>
    <entry id="maslin2019climate">
        <article>
            <author>Maslin, MA</author>
            <title>Climate Change: essential knowledge for developing holistic solutions to our climate crisis</title>
            <journal>Emerging Topics in Life Sciences</journal>
            <year>2019</year>
            <volume>3</volume>
            <number>2</number>
            <pages>245--256</pages>
            <abstract>Understanding anthropogenic climate change is essential for anyone working in the life sciences. Firstly because climate change has already started to impact the Earth biosphere and human health and these changes need to be documented and acknowledged. Secondly, many of the solutions to climate change, both mitigation and adaptation, will be through the life sciences, everything from massive reforestation and sustainable agriculture to preventing the spread of disease and protecting individual human health. Anthropogenic climate change is, therefore, one of the defining challenges of the 21st century, along with poverty alleviation, environmental degradation and global security. Climate change is no longer just a scientific concern but encompasses economics, sociology, geopolitics, national and local politics, law and health to name a few. Hence, to understand climate change fully then not only does one have to review the science but also the politics and geopolitics, which have created the issue and can provide the solutions. Climate change ultimately makes us examine the whole basis of modern society and ultimately asks questions about humanity's relationship with the rest of the planet.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1042/ETLS20180116</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="maxwell2018data">
        <article>
            <author>Maxwell, Dan and Norton, Hannah and Wu, Joe</author>
            <title>The data science opportunity: crafting a holistic strategy</title>
            <journal>Journal of Library Administration</journal>
            <year>2018</year>
            <volume>58</volume>
            <number>2</number>
            <pages>111--127</pages>
            <abstract>The rise of data-driven research and discovery may be one of the greatest strategic opportunities to confront academic libraries in a generation. The argument advanced in this article is that the data science opportunity is about data curation AND data analysis. Thus the development of a holistic data science strategy ought to include both elements. Up until now, academic libraries have largely responded to the data science opportunity from a curatorial and archiving perspective. However, this is beginning to change. The case for crafting a holistic data science strategy is presented in six parts in this article. In part one, a broad overview of the data science opportunity is presented, followed by a definition of data analysis and data curation in part two. The traditional academic library response (curation) and a reframing of it to include data analysis are then presented in two separate parts. And finally, part five reports findings from a recent survey conducted at the University of Florida (UF) which indicates robust demand for training in analytical tools and technologies. The article concludes with some thoughts on the challenges of offering data analysis services, using the UF experience to highlight key issues.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1080/01930826.2017.1412704</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="rickards2015metaphor">
        <article>
            <author>Rickards, Lauren A</author>
            <title>Metaphor and the Anthropocene: Presenting humans as a geological force</title>
            <journal>Geographical research</journal>
            <year>2015</year>
            <volume>53</volume>
            <number>3</number>
            <pages>280--287</pages>
            <abstract>Intellectually as well as materially, the Anthropocene is a deeply cultural phenomenon. This includes its communicative form, which is a contested trope-rich narrative, even within the sciences. In this essay I focus on the role of metaphor in Anthropocene thought and in particular, on the provocative, ambiguous, and potentially far-reaching idea of humans as a geological force. By considering the different interpretations and meaning this metaphor encourages – including differences in what is meant by geological and force, both within and beyond stratigraphy and Earth System Science – we gain a stronger sense of the deeply allegorical and theological character of the Anthropocene story and the way it promises to reposition humans in the world.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1111/1745-5871.12128</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="Feyerabend1991">
        <book>
            <author>Feyerabend, Paul K.</author>
            <title>Limites de la Ciencia</title>
            <publisher>Ediciones Paidos Iberica</publisher>
            <year>1991</year>
        </book>
    </entry>
    <entry id="kuhn1979metaphor">
        <inbook>
            <pages>533--542</pages>
            <year>1993</year>
            <author>Kuhn, Thomas S.</author>
            <bibtexkey>kuhn1979metaphor</bibtexkey>
            <edition>2</edition>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <place>Cambridge</place>
            <title>Metaphor in science</title>
            <url>https://d1wqtxts1xzle7.cloudfront.net/61516192/Andrew_Ortony_-_Metaphor_and_Thought-Cambridge_University_Press_199320191214-31564-1cv3p9k.pdf?1576379223=&amp;response-content-disposition=inline%3B+filename%3DMETAPHO_R_THOUGHT.pdf&amp;Expires=1666185865&amp;Signature=JVcmV2mdpAXZs63IPv9J6vRQGnqyDusQVyXdJ1T9PIftumJOh~36-bAZcXf2-rfNhfuIrzGjQOpy24pvGimW15TvrJ3j-ccqVWUYRxxasQgOT4av3LsBSr2M-Mn5493fqyhfEQp0RwTzlwIVbhtMr6pmsdFA3PGAuHF3AP48dVL-Av1ZEW2XRNtJuQR6aqbV3WTH5LmMJoLiJYBIN4oKfLiGiiWLgM9pd6fZT80J1Th5clsdOGVg-UU9b4eUIPw1NJx5RaO6oFKH8PuA9C54APDpw8vWe6z3bxUthSZb8eGHpZ2ZvpjGt8AzNGh6YJp3VfGRLpUahPnMrp344H8~lA__&amp;Key-Pair-Id=APKAJLOHF5GGSLRBV4ZA#page=541</url>
            <doi>10.1017/CBO9781139173865</doi>
        </inbook>
    </entry>
    <entry id="bhuiyan2018impact">
        <article>
            <author>Bhuiyan, Miraj Ahmed and Jabeen, Musarrat and Zaman, Khalid and Khan, Aqeel and Ahmad, Jamilah and Hishan, Sanil S</author>
            <title>The impact of climate change and energy resources on biodiversity loss: Evidence from a panel of selected Asian countries</title>
            <journal>Renewable energy</journal>
            <year>2018</year>
            <volume>117</volume>
            <pages>324--340</pages>
            <abstract>This study examined the relationships between climate change, energy resources, growth specific factors and their resulting impact on biodiversity loss in a panel of 18 selected Asian countries during the period of 2000–2014. The study employed panel fixed effect regression and panel quantile regression to assess the influence of different factors on biodiversity loss at low, medium, and high levels quantile distribution. The results show that climatic factors increase aquaculture production, whereas energy sources and growth specific factors affected the production of aquaculture in a panel of selected countries. Potential habitat area is affected by high population growth and renewable energy consumption whereas Global Environment Facility (GEF) biodiversity index is affected by average precipitation, foreign direct investment (FDI) inflows, and per capita income. Climatic factors and renewable energy both supported the total fisheries production, whereas nitrous oxide emissions, renewable internal freshwater resources, FDI inflows, per capita income, and population growth affected the production of total fisheries at different quantile distributions.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.renene.2017.10.054</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="van2018effects">
        <article>
            <author>Van Oijen, Marcel and Bellocchi, Gianni and H{\"o}glind, Mats</author>
            <title>Effects of climate change on grassland biodiversity and productivity: the need for a diversity of models</title>
            <journal>Agronomy</journal>
            <year>2018</year>
            <volume>8</volume>
            <number>2</number>
            <pages>14</pages>
            <abstract>There is increasing evidence that the impact of climate change on the productivity of grasslands will at least partly depend on their biodiversity. A high level of biodiversity may confer stability to grassland ecosystems against environmental change, but there are also direct effects of biodiversity on the quantity and quality of grassland productivity. To explain the manifold interactions, and to predict future climatic responses, models may be used. However, models designed for studying the interaction between biodiversity and productivity tend to be structurally different from models for studying the effects of climatic impacts. Here we review the literature on the impacts of climate change on biodiversity and productivity of grasslands. We first discuss the availability of data for model development. Then we analyse strengths and weaknesses of three types of model: ecological, process-based and integrated. We discuss the merits of this model diversity and the scope for merging different model types.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.3390/agronomy8020014</doi>
            <keywords>data needs; empirical models; integrated models; process-based models; review</keywords>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="shaw2015metaphor">
        <article>
            <author>Shaw, Christopher and Nerlich, Brigitte</author>
            <title>Metaphor as a mechanism of global climate change governance: A study of international policies, 1992--2012</title>
            <journal>Ecological Economics</journal>
            <year>2015</year>
            <volume>109</volume>
            <pages>34--40</pages>
            <abstract>This paper explores the emergence of a global climate change mitigation regime through an analysis of the language employed in international science-policy reports. We assume that a global climate regime can only operate effectively on the basis of a shared understanding of climate change which is itself based on a shared language of governance. We therefore carried out an in-depth thematic and metaphor analysis of 63 policy documents published between 1992 and 2012. Results show that global climate science-policy discourses universalise the myriad impacts of a changing climate into a single dichotomous impacted/not-impacted scenario and aim to govern this world according to economic principles of cost–benefit analysis. These discourses use metaphors that draw on narrative structures prevalent in the wider culture to produce and legitimate a reductionist representation of climate change. This representation undermines public understanding of and engagement with climate change by marginalising subordinate policy framings which do not align with the prevailing dichotomous framing. The types of documents we analyse in this paper represent important sources for journalists reporting on climate change. We therefore suggest that any attempt to improve public communication of climate change should include revisions to these organisational discourses.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ecolecon.2014.11.001</doi>
            <keywords>Metaphor; Global climate regime; Climate change communication; Science-policy interface; Cost–benefit analysis</keywords>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="vernadsky2014">
        <incollection>
            <author>Vernadsky, Vladimir</author>
            <title>Some words about the Noösphere</title>
            <booktitle>150 Years of Vernadsky: The Noösphere</booktitle>
            <publisher>CreateSpace</publisher>
            <year>2014</year>
            <editor>Rss, Jason and Freeman, Marsha</editor>
            <volume>2</volume>
            <pages>79--84</pages>
            <isbn>9781500605391</isbn>
        </incollection>
    </entry>
    <entry id="vernadsky2014transition">
        <incollection>
            <author>Vernadsky, Vladimir</author>
            <title>The Transition From the Biosphere To the Noösphere</title>
            <booktitle>150 Years of Vernadsky: The Noösphere</booktitle>
            <publisher>CreateSpace</publisher>
            <year>2014</year>
            <editor>Rss, Jason and Freeman, Marsha</editor>
            <volume>2</volume>
            <pages>11--26</pages>
            <isbn>9781500605391</isbn>
        </incollection>
    </entry>
    <entry id="stevenson1983nature">
        <article>
            <author>Stevenson, David J</author>
            <title>The nature of the earth prior to the oldest known rock record-The Hadean earth</title>
            <journal>IN: Earth's earliest biosphere: Its origin and evolution (A84-43051 21-51). Princeton</journal>
            <year>1983</year>
            <pages>32--40</pages>
            <abstract>Statements about the Earth's history prior to 3.8 Ga ago, the age of the oldest rock sequence now known on Earth, are based on indirect evidence (such as that derived from meteorites and lunar samples) and on plausibility arguments, the persuasiveness of which often depend more on the eloquence of their advocates than on the weight of relevant data. Such statements, however, are of profound importance as they relate to one of the central issues of this volume - the origin of biologic systems (see Chapter 4) - an event that may well have occurred during the pre-3.8-Ga-old "Hadean" segment of Earth history. Yet understanding of the Hadean Earth is far from complete; in particular. and because of the paucity of directly relevant data, theorists dealing with the problem are obliged to work with "models," constructs that can be no better than the input assumptions. New data or interpretations can cause these models to be discarded or recast. The discussion presented in this chapter should be seen in this light: basic physical principles need to be understood, but for the present, detailed scenarios or predictions based upon them are best regarded as "convenient fictions," worthy of discussion but not enshrinement.</abstract>
            <keywords>Earth Planetary Structure; Planetary Evolution; Precambrian Period; Protoplanets; Accretion Disks; Catastrophe Theory; Earth Core; Earth Mantle; Geotemperature; Outgassing; Primitive Earth Atmosphere; Solar System; Geophysics</keywords>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="harrison2020plan">
        <inproceedings>
            <author>Harrison, Mark and Bell, Elizabeth A</author>
            <title>A Plan For Detecting Evidence of Hadean Life</title>
            <booktitle>AGU Fall Meeting Abstracts</booktitle>
            <year>2020</year>
            <volume>2020</volume>
            <pages>P030--03</pages>
            <abstract>The paucity of an early (&gt;3.8 Ga) Earth rock record and the intense metamorphism of what little is left makes challenging the definitive detection of Hadean signs of life and thus an empirical test of molecular clock predictions that the last universal common ancestor (LUCA) of Eubacteria and Archaebacteria emerged between 4.2 and 4.4 Ga (Betts et al., 2018, Nature ecol. &amp; evol. 2, 1556). Evidence that pushes back the established minimum age of life's origin is typically met with asymmetric criticism and argues for guidelines from which to judge the merit of a claim. The Ladder of Life Detection (Neveu et al., 2018, Astrobiology 18, 1375) is a set of criteria meant to guide design of robotic space missions to detect signs of life elsewhere, but this system also has application to studies of early Earth. Seven criteria build toward an increasingly robust interpretation of life detection: Sensitivity, Contaminant-free signal, Repeatability, Context, Detectability, Preservation, Compatibility, and Definitiveness. An 8th criterion, the Last Resort Hypothesis, is the ultimate hurdle: does the signal "compellingly preclude an abiotic origin". Evaluation of those cases in which light C isotopes were measured in situ on graphitic inclusions within an armoring mineral shell in &gt;3.8 Ga samples (i.e., Akilia, Jack Hills) meet the first 6 criteria. While exotic abiotic mechanisms capable of creating light C isotope signals might appear to preclude Definitiveness and the Last Resort Hypothesis, the failure of those mechanisms to globally mimic the sign and magnitude of the vital effect of photosynthesis on C isotopes (Schidlowski, 2001, Precamb. Res. 106, 117) supports the view that these 3.8-4.1 Ga materials meet those tests as well. The path forward is acquisition of a large global database of C isotopes in carbonaceous inclusions (along with geochemical clues as to the origin of their hosts) from the 15 localities known to host &gt;4 Ga zircons. We describe a field and analytical protocol that should permit clear selection between their biogenic vs. abiogenic origin and thus provide an observational test of molecular clock predictions of when LUCA arose.</abstract>
        </inproceedings>
    </entry>
    <entry id="dalla2022integrated">
        <article>
            <author>Dalla Costa, Lorenza and Vinciguerra, Daniela and Giacomelli, Lisa and Salvagnin, Umberto and Piazza, Stefano and Spinella, Katia and Malnoy, Mickael and Moser, Claudio and Marchesi, Ugo</author>
            <title>Integrated approach for the molecular characterization of edited plants obtained via \textit{Agrobacterium tumefaciens}-mediated gene transfer</title>
            <journal>European Food Research and Technology</journal>
            <year>2022</year>
            <volume>248</volume>
            <number>1</number>
            <pages>289--299</pages>
            <abstract>Agrobacterium tumefaciens-mediated gene transfer—actually the most used method to engineer plants—may lead to integration of multiple copies of T-DNA in the plant genome, as well as to chimeric tissues composed of modified cells and wild type cells. A molecular characterization of the transformed lines is thus a good practice to select the best ones for further investigation. Nowadays, several quantitative and semi-quantitative techniques are available to estimate the copy number (CN) of the T-DNA in genetically modified plants. In this study, we compared three methods based on (1) real-time polymerase chain reaction (qPCR), (2) droplet digital PCR (ddPCR), and (3) next generation sequencing (NGS), to carry out a molecular characterization of grapevine edited lines. These lines contain a knock-out mutation, obtained via CRISPR/Cas9 technology, in genes involved in plant susceptibility to two important mildew diseases of grapevine. According to our results, qPCR and ddPCR outputs are largely in agreement in terms of accuracy, especially for low CN values, while ddPCR resulted more precise than qPCR. With regard to the NGS analysis, the CNs detected with this method were often not consistent with those calculated by qPCR and ddPCR, and NGS was not able to discriminate the integration points in three out of ten lines. Nevertheless, the NGS method can positively identify T-DNA truncations or the presence of tandem/inverted repeats, providing distinct and relevant information about the transgene integration asset. Moreover, the expression analysis of Cas9 and single guide RNA (sgRNA), and the sequencing of the target site added new information to be related to CN data. This work, by reporting a practical case-study on grapevine edited lines, explores pros and cons of the most advanced diagnostic techniques available for the precocious selection of the proper transgenic material. The results may be of interest both to scientists developing new transgenic lines, and to laboratories in charge of GMO control.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1007/s00217-021-03881-0</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="johnson1967hierarchical">
        <article>
            <author>Johnson, Stephen C</author>
            <title>Hierarchical clustering schemes</title>
            <journal>Psychometrika</journal>
            <year>1967</year>
            <volume>32</volume>
            <number>3</number>
            <pages>241--254</pages>
            <abstract>Techniques for partitioning objects into optimally homogeneous groups on the basis of empirical measures of similarity among those objects have received increasing attention in several different fields. This paper develops a useful correspondence between any hierarchical system of such clusters, and a particular type of distance measure. The correspondence gives rise to two methods of clustering that are computationally rapid and invariant under monotonic transformations of the data. In an explicitly defined sense, one method forms clusters that are optimally "connected," while the other forms clusters that are optimally "compact.</abstract>
            <url>http://cda.psych.uiuc.edu/psychometrika_highly_cited_articles/johnson_1967.pdf</url>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="margulis2009genome">
        <article>
            <author>Margulis, Lynn</author>
            <title>Genome acquisition in horizontal gene transfer: symbiogenesis and macromolecular sequence analysis</title>
            <journal>Horizontal Gene Transfer</journal>
            <year>2009</year>
            <pages>181--191</pages>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1007/978-1-60327-853-9_10</doi>
            <keywords>Elysia; karyomastigont; symbiogenesis; replicons; parasexuality; fallacy of misplaced concreteness; microbial communities as units of selection</keywords>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="gould1972punctuated">
        <article>
            <author>Gould, Stephen Jay and Eldredge, Niles</author>
            <title>Punctuated equilibria: an alternative to phyletic gradualism</title>
            <journal>Models in paleobiology</journal>
            <year>1972</year>
            <volume>1972</volume>
            <pages>82--115</pages>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="gould1977punctuated">
        <article>
            <author>Gould, Stephen Jay and Eldredge, Niles</author>
            <title>Punctuated equilibria: the tempo and mode of evolution reconsidered</title>
            <journal>Paleobiology</journal>
            <year>1977</year>
            <volume>3</volume>
            <number>2</number>
            <pages>115--151</pages>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1017/S0094837300005224</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="casanova2020developmental">
        <article>
            <author>Casanova, Emily L and Konkel, Miriam K</author>
            <title>The developmental gene hypothesis for punctuated equilibrium: combined roles of developmental regulatory genes and transposable elements</title>
            <journal>Bioessays</journal>
            <year>2020</year>
            <volume>42</volume>
            <number>2</number>
            <pages>1900173</pages>
            <abstract>Theories of the genetics underlying punctuated equilibrium (PE) have been vague to date. Here the developmental gene hypothesis is proposed, which states that: 1) developmental regulatory (DevReg) genes are responsible for the orchestration of metazoan morphogenesis and their extreme conservation and mutation intolerance generates the equilibrium or stasis present throughout much of the fossil record and 2) the accumulation of regulatory elements and recombination within these same genes—often derived from transposable elements—drives punctuated bursts of morphological divergence and speciation across metazoa. This two-part hypothesis helps to explain the features that characterize PE, providing a theoretical genetic basis for the once-controversial theory. Also see the video abstract here https://youtu.be/C-fu-ks5yDs</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1002/bies.201900173</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="reconstruccionRacionalCiencia">
        <book>
            <author>Lakatos, Irme and Feigl, Herbert and Hall, Richard J. and Koertge Noretta and Kuhn, Thomas S.</author>
            <title>Historia de la Ciencia y sus reconstrucciones racionales</title>
            <publisher>Tecnos</publisher>
            <year>2018</year>
            <edition>4</edition>
            <isbn>978-84309-5158-1</isbn>
        </book>
    </entry>
    <entry id="Kuhn1971">
        <book>
            <author>Kuhn, Thomas S.</author>
            <title>La estructura de las revoluciones científicas</title>
            <publisher>FCE México</publisher>
            <year>1971</year>
            <month>nov</month>
            <isbn>9786071608253</isbn>
            <url>https://materiainvestigacion.files.wordpress.com/2016/05/kuhn1971.pdf</url>
        </book>
    </entry>
    <entry id="FeyerabendMetodo">
        <book>
            <author>Feyerabend, Paul K.</author>
            <title>Tratado Contra El Metodo/ Against Method: Esquema De Una Teoria Anarquista Del Conocimiento / Outline of an anarchistic theory of knowledge (Filosofia ... / Philosophy and Essay) (Spanish Edition)</title>
            <publisher>Tecnos Editorial S A</publisher>
            <year>1986</year>
            <address>Madrid</address>
            <isbn>84-309-0887-0</isbn>
            <url>https://monoskop.org/images/3/3f/Feyerabend_Paul_Tratado_contra_el_metodo.pdf</url>
        </book>
    </entry>
    <entry id="notasKuhn">
        <inbook>
            <chapter>Notas sobre Lakatos</chapter>
            <editor>Tecnos (Grupo Anaya S.A)</editor>
            <pages>81--95</pages>
            <year>2018</year>
            <author>Kuhn, Thomas S.</author>
            <isbn>978-84309-5158-1</isbn>
            <bibtexkey>notasKuhn</bibtexkey>
            <publisher>Tecnos</publisher>
            <edition>4º Edición (reimpresión)</edition>
            <title>Historia de la Ciencia y sus reconstrucciones racionales</title>
        </inbook>
    </entry>
    <entry id="kaplaner2022we">
        <article>
            <author>Kaplaner, Constantin and Steinebach, Yves</author>
            <title>Why we should use the gini coefficient to assess punctuated equilibrium theory</title>
            <journal>Political Analysis</journal>
            <year>2022</year>
            <volume>30</volume>
            <number>3</number>
            <pages>450--455</pages>
            <abstract>Punctuated Equilibrium Theory posits that policy-making is generally characterized by long periods of stability that are interrupted by short periods of fundamental policy change. The literature converged on the measure of kurtosis and L-kurtosis to assess these change patterns. In this letter, we critically discuss these measures and propose the Gini coefficient as a (1) comparable, but (2) more intuitive, and (3) more precise measure of “punctuated” change patterns.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1017/pan.2021.25</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="morgan2021narrative">
        <article>
            <author>Morgan, Mary S</author>
            <title>Narrative Inference with and without Statistics: Making Sense of Economic Cycles with Malthus and Kondratiev</title>
            <journal>History of Political Economy</journal>
            <year>2021</year>
            <volume>53</volume>
            <pages>113--138</pages>
            <abstract>An integrated view on the possible effects of global climate change is provided while taking into account that not only the rising average temperature is likely to impact natural populations but also that increased variation around the mean and higher frequency of extreme events will be important. We propose that complex genetic effects in concert with demographic patterns may affect how focal populations react to the environmental challenge in an adaptive way (if they can). In order to aim for an inclusive picture of the ongoing environmental change we argue for a synthesis of knowledge from a range of ‘classical’ disciplines such as quantitative genetics, conservation genetics and population ecology. A hereto little exposed concern is the importance of the increase in amplitude of environmental fluctuations and how the corresponding evolutionary and ecological reactions are expected to occur. Due to the complex interactions between the ecological and genetic mechanisms in the response to climate-induced impacts interdisciplinary approaches are the most promising path in seeking knowledge about the present and future changes in the biosphere.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jtherbio.2007.01.011</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="fet2021lynn">
        <article>
            <author>Fet, Victor</author>
            <title>Lynn Margulis and Boris Kozo-Polyansky: How the Symbiogenesis was translated from Russian</title>
            <journal>Biosystems</journal>
            <year>2021</year>
            <volume>199</volume>
            <pages>104316</pages>
            <abstract>This contribution details the complex history of the early work by Boris Kozo-Polyansky (1924) that became available in English translation 86 years after it was published in Russian. The great American naturalist Lynn Margulis—whose serial endosymbiosis theory was presciently predated by Kozo-Polyansky by four decades—was instrumental in organizing this resurrection and ‘horizontal transfer’ of knowledge, forgotten by that time even in Russia.</abstract>
            <doi>This contribution details the complex history of the early work by Boris Kozo-Polyansky (1924) that became available in English translation 86 years after it was published in Russian. The great American naturalist Lynn Margulis—whose serial endosymbiosis theory was presciently predated by Kozo-Polyansky by four decades—was instrumental in organizing this resurrection and ‘horizontal transfer’ of knowledge, forgotten by that time even in Russia.</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="dobzhansky1982genetics">
        <book>
            <author>Dobzhansky, Theodosius</author>
            <title>Genetics and the Origin of Species</title>
            <publisher>Columbia university press</publisher>
            <year>1982</year>
            <number>11</number>
            <url>https://collopy.net/teaching/2017/evolution/readings/Genetics%20and%20the%20Origin%20of%20Species.pdf</url>
        </book>
    </entry>
    <entry id="mallet2006does">
        <article>
            <author>Mallet, James</author>
            <title>What does Drosophila genetics tell us about speciation?</title>
            <journal>Trends in ecology \&amp; evolution</journal>
            <year>2006</year>
            <volume>21</volume>
            <number>7</number>
            <pages>386--393</pages>
            <abstract>Studies of hybrid inviability, sterility and speciation genes in Drosophila have given insight into the genetic changes that result in reproductive isolation. Here, I survey some extraordinary and important advances in Drosophila speciation research. However, ‘reproductive isolation’ is not the same as ‘speciation’, and this Drosophila work has resulted in a lopsided view of speciation. In particular, Drosophila are not always well-suited to investigating ecological and other selection-driven primary causes of speciation in nature. Recent advances have made use of far less tractable, but more charismatic organisms, such as flowering plants, vertebrates and larger insects. Work with these organisms has complemented Drosophila studies of hybrid unfitness to provide a more complete understanding of speciation.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tree.2006.05.004</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="guilhot2019environmental">
        <article>
            <author>Guilhot, Robin and Rombaut, Antoine and Xu{\'e}reb, Anne and Howell, Kate and Fellous, Simon</author>
            <title>Environmental specificity and evolution in Drosophila-bacteria symbiosis</title>
            <journal>bioRxiv</journal>
            <year>2019</year>
            <pages>546838</pages>
            <abstract>Environmentally acquired microbial symbionts could contribute to host adaptation to local adaptation like vertically transmitted symbionts do. This scenario necessitates symbionts to have different effects in different environments. In Drosophila melanogaster, communities of extracellular bacterial symbionts vary largely among environments, which could be due to variable effects on phenotype. We investigated this idea with four bacterial strains isolated from the feces of a D. melanogaster lab strain, and tested their effects in two environments: the environment of origin (i.e. the laboratory medium) and a new one (i.e. fresh fruit with live yeast). All bacterial effects on larval and adult traits differed among environments, ranging from very beneficial to marginally deleterious. The joint analysis of larval development speed and adult size further suggests bacteria would affect developmental plasticity more than resource acquisition in males. The context-dependent effects of bacteria we observed, and its underlying mechanisms, sheds light on how environmentally acquired symbionts may contribute to host evolution.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1101/546838</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="genEgoista">
        <book>
            <author>Richard Dawkins</author>
            <editor>Grupo editorial Bruño S.L.</editor>
            <title>El Gen Egoísta Extendido</title>
            <publisher>Salvat</publisher>
            <year>2017</year>
            <edition>4º Edición</edition>
            <isbn>978-84-696-2043-4</isbn>
        </book>
    </entry>
    <entry id="hancock2021neo">
        <article>
            <author>Hancock, Zachary B and Lehmberg, Emma S and Bradburd, Gideon S</author>
            <title>Neo-darwinism still haunts evolutionary theory: A modern perspective on Charlesworth, Lande, and Slatkin (1982)</title>
            <journal>Evolution</journal>
            <year>2021</year>
            <volume>75</volume>
            <number>6</number>
            <pages>1244--1255</pages>
            <abstract>The Modern Synthesis (or “Neo-Darwinism”), which arose out of the reconciliation of Darwin's theory of natural selection and Mendel's research on genetics, remains the foundation of evolutionary theory. However, since its inception, it has been a lightning rod for criticism, which has ranged from minor quibbles to complete dismissal. Among the most famous of the critics was Stephen Jay Gould, who, in 1980, proclaimed that the Modern Synthesis was “effectively dead.” Gould and others claimed that the action of natural selection on random mutations was insufficient on its own to explain patterns of macroevolutionary diversity and divergence, and that new processes were required to explain findings from the fossil record. In 1982, Charlesworth, Lande, and Slatkin published a response to this critique in Evolution, in which they argued that Neo-Darwinism was indeed sufficient to explain macroevolutionary patterns. In this Perspective for the 75th Anniversary of the Society for the Study of Evolution, we review Charlesworth et al. in its historical context and provide modern support for their arguments. We emphasize the importance of microevolutionary processes in the study of macroevolutionary patterns. Ultimately, we conclude that punctuated equilibrium did not represent a major revolution in evolutionary biology – although debate on this point stimulated significant research and furthered the field – and that Neo-Darwinism is alive and well.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1111/evo.14268</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="knapp2019placing">
        <article>
            <author>Knapp, Corrine Nöel and Reid, Robin S and Fernández-Giménez, María E and Klein, Julia A and Galvin, Kathleen A</author>
            <title>Placing transdisciplinarity in context: A review of approaches to connect scholars, society and action</title>
            <journal>Sustainability</journal>
            <year>2019</year>
            <volume>11</volume>
            <number>18</number>
            <pages>4899</pages>
            <abstract>Complex sustainability problems (e.g., climate change) are challenging to understand and manage, leading to an increase in approaches that connect scholars to society and research to action (collaborative approaches). The transdisciplinary approach (TDA) represents one such approach. While TDA is new to many, there are several prior collaborative approaches including collaborative adaptive management, knowledge integration, participatory action research, and indigenous/local knowledge. Other contemporary and parallel approaches include citizen science, translational science, evidence-based practice, and knowledge with action. The varied disciplinary roots and problem areas contribute to a lack of interaction among these parallel but distinct approaches, and among the scholars and stakeholders who practice them. In this paper, we consider the connections, complementarities and contradictions among these distinct but related collaborative approaches. This review offers insights into the interaction between science and practice, including the importance of social processes and recognition of different ways of knowing, as well as how to conduct collaborative approaches on a variety of scales and think about how to generalize findings. The review suggests a need to rethink roles and relationships in the process of knowledge co-creation, both extending the roles of researchers and practitioners, creating new hybrid roles for “pracademics”, and placing greater awareness on issues of power.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.3390/su11184899</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="autopoiesis">
        <book>
            <author>Humberto Maturana and Francisco Varela</author>
            <editor>Editorial Universitaria S.A</editor>
            <title>De Máquinas y Seres Vivos. Autopoiesis: La organización de lo vivo</title>
            <year>1994</year>
            <isbn>987-00-0386-9</isbn>
        </book>
    </entry>
    <entry id="gordin2012lysenkoism">
        <article>
            <author>Gordin, Michael D.</author>
            <title>How lysenkoism became pseudoscience: dobzhansky to velikovsky</title>
            <journal>Journal of the History of Biology</journal>
            <year>2011</year>
            <volume>45</volume>
            <number>3</number>
            <pages>443--468</pages>
            <month>jun</month>
            <abstract>At some point in America in the 1940s, T. D. Lysenko’s neo-Lamarckian hereditary theories transformed from a set of disputed doctrines into a prime exemplar of “pseudoscience.” This paper explores the context in which this theory acquired this pejorative status by examining American efforts to refute Lysenkoism both before and after the famous August 1948 endorsement of Lysenko’s doctrines by the Stalinist state, with particular attention to the translation efforts of Theodosius Dobzhansky. After enumerating numerous tactics for combating perceived pseudoscience, the Lysenko case is then juxtaposed with another American case of alleged pseudoscience: the notorious 1950 scandal surrounding Immanuel Velikovsky’s Worlds in Collision (1950, Worlds in Collision. New York: Macmillan). On several levels, the characterization of Lysenkoism as pseudoscientific served as a template for casting other rejected theories, including Velikovsky’s, in the same light.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1007/s10739-011-9287-3</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="Velikovsky2009-ci">
        <book>
            <author>Velikovsky, Immanuel</author>
            <title>Worlds in Collision</title>
            <publisher>Paradigma</publisher>
            <year>2009</year>
            <address>London, England</address>
            <month>#oct#</month>
            <url>http://www.oplysning.org/uploads/9/1/4/3/9143605/velikovsky_immanuel_-_worlds_in_collision.pdf</url>
        </book>
    </entry>
    <entry id="cowie2022sixth">
        <article>
            <author>Cowie, Robert H and Bouchet, Philippe and Fontaine, Benoît</author>
            <title>The Sixth Mass Extinction: fact, fiction or speculation?</title>
            <journal>Biological Reviews</journal>
            <year>2022</year>
            <abstract>There have been five Mass Extinction events in the history of Earth's biodiversity, all caused by dramatic but natural phenomena. It has been claimed that the Sixth Mass Extinction may be underway, this time caused entirely by humans. Although considerable evidence indicates that there is a biodiversity crisis of increasing extinctions and plummeting abundances, some do not accept that this amounts to a Sixth Mass Extinction. Often, they use the IUCN Red List to support their stance, arguing that the rate of species loss does not differ from the background rate. However, the Red List is heavily biased: almost all birds and mammals but only a minute fraction of invertebrates have been evaluated against conservation criteria. Incorporating estimates of the true number of invertebrate extinctions leads to the conclusion that the rate vastly exceeds the background rate and that we may indeed be witnessing the start of the Sixth Mass Extinction. As an example, we focus on molluscs, the second largest phylum in numbers of known species, and, extrapolating boldly, estimate that, since around AD 1500, possibly as many as 7.5–13% (150,000–260,000) of all ~2 million known species have already gone extinct, orders of magnitude greater than the 882 (0.04%) on the Red List. We review differences in extinction rates according to realms: marine species face significant threats but, although previous mass extinctions were largely defined by marine invertebrates, there is no evidence that the marine biota has reached the same crisis as the non-marine biota. Island species have suffered far greater rates than continental ones. Plants face similar conservation biases as do invertebrates, although there are hints they may have suffered lower extinction rates. There are also those who do not deny an extinction crisis but accept it as a new trajectory of evolution, because humans are part of the natural world; some even embrace it, with a desire to manipulate it for human benefit. We take issue with these stances. Humans are the only species able to manipulate the Earth on a grand scale, and they have allowed the current crisis to happen. Despite multiple conservation initiatives at various levels, most are not species oriented (certain charismatic vertebrates excepted) and specific actions to protect every living species individually are simply unfeasible because of the tyranny of numbers. As systematic biologists, we encourage the nurturing of the innate human appreciation of biodiversity, but we reaffirm the message that the biodiversity that makes our world so fascinating, beautiful and functional is vanishing unnoticed at an unprecedented rate. In the face of a mounting crisis, scientists must adopt the practices of preventive archaeology, and collect and document as many species as possible before they disappear. All this depends on reviving the venerable study of natural history and taxonomy. Denying the crisis, simply accepting it and doing nothing, or even embracing it for the ostensible benefit of humanity, are not appropriate options and pave the way for the Earth to continue on its sad trajectory towards a Sixth Mass Extinction.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1111/brv.12816</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="rolshausen2022lichen">
        <article>
            <author>Rolshausen, Gregor and Dal Grande, Francesco and Otte, Jürgen and Schmitt, Imke</author>
            <title>Lichen holobionts show compositional structure along elevation</title>
            <journal>Molecular Ecology</journal>
            <year>2022</year>
            <abstract>Holobionts are dynamic ecosystems that may respond to abiotic drivers with compositional changes. Uncovering elevational diversity patterns within these microecosystems can further our understanding of community-environment interactions. Here, we assess how the major components of lichen holobionts—fungal hosts, green algal symbionts, and the bacterial community—collectively respond to an elevational gradient. We analyse populations of two lichen symbioses, Umbilicaria pustulata and U. hispanica, along an elevational gradient spanning 2100 altitudinal metres and covering three major biomes. Our study shows (i) discontinuous genomic variation in fungal hosts with one abrupt genomic differentiation within each of the two host species, (ii) altitudinally structured bacterial communities with pronounced turnover within and between hosts, and (iii) altitude-specific presence of algal symbionts. Alpha diversity of bacterial communities decreased with increasing elevation. A marked turnover in holobiont diversity occurred across two altitudinal belts: at 11°C–13°C average annual temperature (here: 800–1200 m a.s.l.), and at 7°C–9°C average annual temperature (here: 1500–1800 m a.s.l.). The two observed zones mark a clustering of distribution limits and community shifts. The three ensuing altitudinal classes, that is, the most frequent combinations of species in holobionts, approximately correspond to the Mediterranean, cool-temperate, and alpine climate zones. We conclude that multitrophic microecosystems, such as lichen holobionts, respond with concerted compositional changes to climatic factors that also structure communities of macroorganisms, for example, vascular plants.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1111/mec.16471</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="suarez2019metaphysical">
        <article>
            <author>Suárez, Javier and Triviño, Vanessa</author>
            <title>A metaphysical approach to holobiont individuality: Holobionts as emergent individuals</title>
            <journal>Quaderns de filosofia</journal>
            <year>2019</year>
            <volume>6</volume>
            <number>1</number>
            <abstract>Holobionts are symbiotic assemblages composed by a host plus its microbiome. The status of holobionts as individuals has recently been a subject of continuous controversy, which has given rise to two main positions: on the one hand, holobiont advocates argue that holobionts are biological individuals; on the other, holobiont detractors argue that they are just mere chimeras or ecological communities, but not individuals. Both parties in the dispute develop their argu-ments from the framework of the philosophy of biology, in terms of what it takes for a “conglomerate” to be considered an interesting individual from a biological point of view. However, the debates about holobiont individuality have important ontological implications that have remained vaguely explored from a metaphysical framework. The purpose of this paper is to cover that gap by presenting a meta-physical approach to holobionts individuality. Drawing upon a conception of natu-ral selection that puts the focus on the transgenerational recurrence of the traits and that supports the thesis that holobionts are units of selection, we argue that holobionts bear emergent traits and exert downward powers over the entities that compose them. In this vein, we argue, a reasonable argument can be made for conceiving holobionts as emergent biological individuals.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.7203/qfia.6.1.14825</doi>
            <keywords>emergence; holobiont; symbiosis; microbiome; biological individuality; trait-recurrence</keywords>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="sagan2021empedocles">
        <article>
            <author>Sagan, Dorion</author>
            <title>From Empedocles to Symbiogenetics: Lynn Margulis's revolutionary influence on evolutionary biology</title>
            <journal>Biosystems</journal>
            <year>2021</year>
            <volume>204</volume>
            <pages>104386</pages>
            <abstract>As a primary expositor of the work of Lynn Margulis collaborating with her over thirty years on over thirty books and forty articles, scientific and popular, I attempt here to summarize her unique and lasting influence on evolutionary biology. Describing life on Earth as the multi-billion-year evolution of microbial communities, from prokaryotes maintaining Earth's atmosphere away from thermodynamic equilibrium to all eukaryotes as polygenomic beings, Margulis's interdisciplinary work has deeply influenced multiple fields including systematics, theories of the evolution of metabolism, paleobiology, and biogeochemistry. Overturning the neo-Darwinist narrative that speciation almost always occurs by the gradual accumulation of random mutations, Margulis's work revives a discarded philosophical speculation of the pre-Socratic Empedocles, who suggested that Earth's early beings both merged and differentially reproduced (were naturally selected); a speculation that was rejected by Aristotle probably because it smacked of mythological chimeras that had no place in observational biology, and later by Charles Darwin, who mentioned Aristotle's rejection of Empedocles to show that he knew of but did not accept natural selection, thus helping lay his own claim to its own proper scientific presentation in a Victorian culture whose thinking of origins was dominated not by Greek mythology but Christian special creation. Margulis's curiosity-driven science, collaborative work ethic, status as a woman, embrace of novelty, philosophical stance, current status of her theories, and the proposal for a new science of symbiogenetics are among the topics examined.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.biosystems.2021.104386</doi>
            <keywords>Lynn Margulis; Symbiogenetics; Thermodynamics; Prototaxis; History of Science; Biophenomenology</keywords>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="whitehouse1949multiple">
        <article>
            <author>Whitehouse, H. L. K.</author>
            <title>Multiple-allelomorph heterothallism in the fungi</title>
            <journal>The New Phytologist</journal>
            <year>1949</year>
            <volume>48</volume>
            <number>2</number>
            <pages>212--244</pages>
            <month>jun</month>
            <abstract>Heterothallism in the Hymenomycetes was first reported by Mile. Bensaude (1917) to the Academie des Sciences of Paris, and published fully the following year (Bensaude,1918). Bensaude discovered that in Coprinus fimetarius the clamp-connexions are associated with the simultaneous or 'conjugate' division of a pair of nuclei. She found that single-spore cultures, unlike cultures derived from many spores, did not produce clamp-connexions or fruit-bodies. Furthermore, she obtained two cultures, each originating from a single spore, which separately remained in the primary condition indeflnitely, but when placed together they gave rise to hyphae with clamp-connexions, followed by the formation of fruit-bodies. Bensaude regarded the two strains as analogous to the plus and minus strains of the heterothallic species of the Mucorales.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1469-8137.1949.tb05120.x</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="wilson2021genetic">
        <article>
            <author>Wilson, Andi M and Wilken, P Markus and Wingfield, Michael J and Wingfield, Brenda D</author>
            <title>Genetic networks that govern sexual reproduction in the Pezizomycotina</title>
            <journal>Microbiology and Molecular Biology Reviews</journal>
            <year>2021</year>
            <volume>85</volume>
            <number>4</number>
            <pages>e00020--21</pages>
            <month>dec</month>
            <abstract>Sexual development in filamentous fungi is a complex process that relies on the precise control of and interaction between a variety of genetic networks and pathways. The mating-type (MAT) genes are the master regulators of this process and typically act as transcription factors, which control the expression of genes involved at all stages of the sexual cycle. In many fungi, the sexual cycle typically begins when the mating pheromones of one mating type are recognized by a compatible partner, followed by physical interaction and fertilization. Subsequently, highly specialized sexual structures are formed, within which the sexual spores develop after rounds of meiosis and mitosis. These spores are then released and germinate, forming new individuals that initiate new cycles of growth. This review provides an overview of the known genetic networks and pathways that are involved in each major stage of the sexual cycle in filamentous ascomycete fungi.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1128/MMBR.00020-21</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="mela2020syncytia">
        <article>
            <author>Mela, Alexander P and Rico-Ramírez, Adriana M and Glass, N Louise</author>
            <title>Syncytia in fungi</title>
            <journal>Cells</journal>
            <year>2020</year>
            <volume>9</volume>
            <number>10</number>
            <pages>2255</pages>
            <abstract>Filamentous fungi typically grow as interconnected multinucleate syncytia that can be microscopic to many hectares in size. Mechanistic details and rules that govern the formation and function of these multinucleate syncytia are largely unexplored, including details on syncytial morphology and the regulatory controls of cellular and molecular processes. Recent discoveries have revealed various adaptations that enable fungal syncytia to accomplish coordinated behaviors, including cell growth, nuclear division, secretion, communication, and adaptation of the hyphal network for mixing nuclear and cytoplasmic organelles. In this review, we highlight recent studies using advanced technologies to define rules that govern organizing principles of hyphal and colony differentiation, including various aspects of nuclear and mitochondrial cooperation versus competition. We place these findings into context with previous foundational literature and present still unanswered questions on mechanistic aspects, function, and morphological diversity of fungal syncytia across the fungal kingdom.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.3390/cells9102255</doi>
            <keywords>syncytia; filamentous fungi; heterokaryon; nucleus; morphology</keywords>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="rosenberg2021evolution">
        <article>
            <author>Rosenberg, Eugene</author>
            <title>Evolution of holobionts: the hologenome concept</title>
            <journal>Microbiome</journal>
            <year>2021</year>
            <pages>317--352</pages>
            <abstract>The holobiont (host with its endocellular and extracellular microbiome) can function as a distinct biological entity, an additional organismal level to the ones previously considered, on which natural selection operates. The holobiont can function as a whole: anatomically, metabolically, immunologically, developmentally, and during evolution. Consideration of the holobiont with its hologenome as an independent level of selection in evolution has led to a better understanding of underappreciated modes of genetic variation and evolution. The hologenome is comprised of two complimentary parts: host and microbiome genomes. Changes in either genome can result in variations that can be selected for or against. The host genome is highly conserved, and genetic changes within it occur slowly, whereas the microbiome genome is dynamic and can change rapidly in response to the environment by increasing or reducing particular microbes, by acquisition of novel microbes, by horizontal gene transfer, and by mutation. Recent experiments showing that microbiota can play an initial role in speciation have been suggested as an additional mode of enhancing evolution. Some of the genetic variations can be transferred to offspring by a variety of mechanisms. Strain-specific DNA analysis has shown that at least some of the microbiota can be maintained across hundreds of thousands of host generations, implying the existence of a microbial core. We argue that rapid changes in the microbiome genome could allow holobionts to adapt and survive under changing environmental conditions thus providing the time necessary for the host genome to adapt and evolve. As Darwin wrote, “It is not the strongest of the species that survives but the most adaptable”.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1186/s40168-018-0457-9</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="steensels2021interspecific">
        <article>
            <author>Steensels, Jan and Gallone, Brigida and Verstrepen, Kevin J.</author>
            <title>Interspecific hybridization as a driver of fungal evolution and adaptation</title>
            <journal>Nature Reviews Microbiology</journal>
            <year>2021</year>
            <volume>19</volume>
            <number>8</number>
            <pages>485--500</pages>
            <abstract>Cross-species gene transfer is often associated with bacteria, which have evolved several mechanisms that facilitate horizontal DNA exchange. However, the increased availability of whole-genome sequences has revealed that fungal species also exchange DNA, leading to intertwined lineages, blurred species boundaries or even novel species. In contrast to prokaryotes, fungal DNA exchange originates from interspecific hybridization, where two genomes are merged into a single, often highly unstable, polyploid genome that evolves rapidly into stabler derivatives. The resulting hybrids can display novel combinations of genetic and phenotypic variation that enhance fitness and allow colonization of new niches. Interspecific hybridization led to the emergence of important pathogens of humans and plants (for example, various Candida and ‘powdery mildew’ species, respectively) and industrially important yeasts, such as Saccharomyces hybrids that are important in the production of cold-fermented lagers or cold-cellared Belgian ales. In this Review, we discuss the genetic processes and evolutionary implications of fungal interspecific hybridization and highlight some of the best-studied examples. In addition, we explain how hybrids can be used to study molecular mechanisms underlying evolution, adaptation and speciation, and serve as a route towards development of new variants for industrial applications.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41579-021-00537-4</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="giordano2018mitonuclear">
        <article>
            <author>Giordano, Luana and Sillo, Fabiano and Garbelotto, Matteo and Gonthier, Paolo</author>
            <title>Mitonuclear interactions may contribute to fitness of fungal hybrids</title>
            <journal>Scientific Reports</journal>
            <year>2018</year>
            <volume>8</volume>
            <number>1</number>
            <pages>1--7</pages>
            <abstract>Hybridization between species is being recognized as a major force in the rapid adaptive evolution of fungal plant pathogens. The first stages of interspecific hybridization necessarily involve nuclear-mitochondrial chimeras. In their 2001 publication, Olson and Stenlid reported that mitochondria control the virulence of first generation hybrids between the North American fungal pathogen Heterobasidion irregulare and its congeneric H. occidentale. By assessing saprobic ability and gene expression of H. irregulare × H. annosum sensu stricto hybrids and of their parental genotypes, we demonstrate that mitochondria also influence saprobic growth of hybrids. Moreover, gene expression data suggest that fungal fitness is modulated by an intimate interplay between nuclear genes and mitochondrial type, and is dependent on the specific mitonuclear combination.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-018-19922-w</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="fan2019effects">
        <article>
            <author>Fan, ZiTeng and Wu, YuLing and Wang, XinJu and Li, TaiQiang and Gao, JiangYun and others</author>
            <title>Effects of symbiotic fungi on seed germination of interspecific hybrid progenies in Orchidaceae.</title>
            <journal>Chinese Journal of Plant Ecology</journal>
            <year>2019</year>
            <volume>43</volume>
            <number>4</number>
            <pages>374--382</pages>
            <abstract>AimsPrevious studies have shown that Dendrobium plants form a specific symbiotic relationship with fungi at differentiation stages during natural seed germination. In order to explore the evolution and adaptation of this symbiotic relationship in interspecific hybrid progenies, this study was to understand whether the strong specificity with symbiotic fungi during seedling formation and differentiation was also an important factor limiting the formation of hybrid progenies in Dendrobium, and the relationship between hybrid progenies of orchids and symbiotic fungi during seed germination stage.
MethodsThe effects of fungi on germination of interspecific hybrid seeds of D. officinale and D. tortile were studied using the highly specific fungi strains Tulasnella SSCDO-5 and Epulorhiza FDd1, which can effectively promote seed germination and seedling formation in D. officinale and D. devonianum, respectively.
Important findings The results showed that both SSCDO-5 and FDd1 strains could effectively promote the protocorm and seedling formation of hybrid seeds after 68 days incubation with no significant difference. The SSCDO-5 strain from D. officinale did not show any advantages, and the seedling formation rate of hybrid was lower than that of FDd1 strain from D. devonianum. The seedling formation rate incubation with SSCDO-5 strain was (22.13 ± 6.62)% while with FDd1 strain was (29.53 ± 5.51)%. The specificity of SSCDO-5 strain with D. officinale at seedling formation and development stage was not inherited or expressed in hybrid progenies, indicating that hybridization broke the symbiotic relationship of this specificity, which enabled hybrid progenies to establish new symbiotic relationship with different fungi. Our results do not support the hypothesis that the specificity of symbiotic fungi is an important limiting factor for the formation of hybrid progenies in Dendrobium. We speculate that the symbiotic relationship between Dendrobium plants and fungi during seedling differentiation and development is formed and established in the process of adapting to specific ecological environment.</abstract>
            <url>https://www.plant-ecology.com/EN/10.17521/cjpe.2019.0048</url>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="strullu2007mycorrhization">
        <article>
            <author>Strullu-Derrien, Christine and Strullu, D{\'e}sir{\'e}-Georges</author>
            <title>Mycorrhization of fossil and living plants</title>
            <journal>Comptes Rendus Palevol</journal>
            <year>2007</year>
            <volume>6</volume>
            <pages>483--494</pages>
            <abstract>The widespread mycorrhization together with the fossil record indicate that plants and fungi have evolved in mycorrhizal relationship since the colonization of land by early plants. In living plants most mycorrhizal symbioses are mutualistic associations in which fungus and plant exchange metabolites and nutrients required for their growth and survival. They concern either the gametophyte and/or the sporophyte of most embryophytes. A new nomenclature is suggested to define two types of mycorrhizae: (1) paramycorrhizae for the colonization of thalli and shoot systems: (2) eumycorrhizae for the colonization of root systems. The aim of this paper is to show the mycorrhizal status in relation with the various clades of embryophytes by considering both fossil and living plants and to develop the implications of mycorrhizal symbiosis in the colonization of land by early plants and in the evolution of plants.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.crpv.2007.09.006</doi>
            <keywords>Mycorrhizae; Nomenclature; Embryophytes; Colonization of land</keywords>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="wu2012spatial">
        <article>
            <author>Wu, Qiang-Sheng and He, Xin-Hua and Zou, Ying-Ning and He, Kai-Ping and Sun, Ya-Hong and Cao, Ming-Qin</author>
            <title>Spatial distribution of glomalin-related soil protein and its relationships with root mycorrhization, soil aggregates, carbohydrates, activity of protease and $\upbeta$-glucosidase in the rhizosphere of Citrus unshiu</title>
            <journal>Soil Biology and Biochemistry</journal>
            <year>2012</year>
            <volume>45</volume>
            <pages>181--183</pages>
            <month>feb</month>
            <abstract>Relationships between the spatial distributions of glomalin-related soil protein (GRSP) and soil aggregates, carbohydrates or relevant enzymes are poorly studied. We found that two categories of GRSP, the easily extractable Bradford-reactive soil protein (EE-BRSP) and total BRSP (T-BRSP), respectively ranged between 0.3–0.6 and 0.5–0.8 mg/g DW soil, and these two BRSPs decreased with the increase of soil depth (0–40 cm) in the rhizosphere of a 22-year-old Citrus unshiu orchard. Both EE-BRSP and T-BRSP were significantly positively correlated with mycorrhization, 0.25–0.50 mm soil water-stable aggregates, water-extractable or hydrolyzable carbohydrates, and β-glucosidase, but significantly negatively correlated with protease. Our results demonstrate that the spatial distribution of GRSP is significantly affected by mycorrhization, soil carbohydrate, β-glucosidase and protease.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.soilbio.2011.10.002</doi>
            <keywords>β-glucosidase;Citrus; Glomalin; Glomalin-related soil protein; Mycorrhization; Protease</keywords>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="shi2021variations">
        <article>
            <author>Shi, Songmei and Wen, Miao and Dong, Xingshui and Sharifi, Sharifullah and Xie, Deti and He, Xinhua</author>
            <title>Variations in glomalin-related soil protein in Vicia faba rhizosphere depending upon interactions among mycorrhization, daytime and/or nighttime elevated CO2 levels</title>
            <journal>Geoderma</journal>
            <year>2021</year>
            <volume>404</volume>
            <pages>115283</pages>
            <abstract>Relationships between glomalin-related soil protein (GRSP) and soil organic carbon, total nitrogen or enzyme activity are unknown under the combined effects of varying daytime/nighttime elevated CO2 (eCO2) levels and arbuscular mycorrhizal fungi (AMF). We demonstrated that daytime, nighttime, and dual daytime/nighttime eCO2 levels could significantly increase AMF mycorrhization, soil organic carbon, total nitrogen, easily extractable, difficultly extractable and total GRSP in AMF soil. Under daytime eCO2, soil total nitrogen was significantly decreased in non-AMF soil, while mycorrhization alleviated soil nitrogen limitation. Nighttime and dual daytime/nighttime eCO2 significantly increased β-glucosidase and protease activities in AMF and non-AMF soils. With greater eCO2 effects in AMF than in non-AMF soils, GRSPs positively related to mycorrhization, soil organic carbon, total nitrogen, and β-glucosidase activity. Under the circumstance of global CO2 rising, besides mycorrhization, the combined effects of varying, non-steady-state daytime and nighttime eCO2, play important roles in soil carbon and nitrogen cycles.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.geoderma.2021.115283</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="vlavcic2021evolving">
        <article>
            <author>Vlačić, Božidar and Corbo, Leonardo and e Silva, Susana Costa and Dabić, Marina</author>
            <title>The evolving role of artificial intelligence in marketing: A review and research agenda</title>
            <journal>Journal of Business Research</journal>
            <year>2021</year>
            <volume>128</volume>
            <pages>187--203</pages>
            <month>may</month>
            <abstract>An increasing amount of research on Intelligent Systems/Artificial Intelligence (AI) in marketing has shown that AI is capable of mimicking humans and performing activities in an ‘intelligent’ manner. Considering the growing interest in AI among marketing researchers and practitioners, this review seeks to provide an overview of the trajectory of marketing and AI research fields. Building upon the review of 164 articles published in Web of Science and Scopus indexed journals, this article develops a context-specific research agenda. Our study of selected articles by means of Multiple Correspondence Analysis (MCA) procedure outlines several research avenues related to the adoption, use, and acceptance of AI technology in marketing, the role of data protection and ethics, the role of institutional support for marketing AI, as well as the revolution of the labor market and marketers’ competencies.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jbusres.2021.01.055</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="furrer2020twenty">
        <article>
            <author>Furrer, Olivier and Kerguignas, Jie Yu and Delcourt, C{\'e}cile and Gremler, Dwayne D</author>
            <title>Twenty-seven years of service research: a literature review and research agenda</title>
            <journal>Journal of Services Marketing</journal>
            <year>2020</year>
            <volume>34</volume>
            <number>3</number>
            <pages>299--316</pages>
            <abstract>The growing service sector has experienced several revolutions that have transformed the way services are created and delivered. In parallel, services increasingly pique the interest of scholars, resulting in an expanding body of knowledge. Accordingly, it is time to reflect on extant service research, assess its boundaries, and think about its future. This paper aims to consider three research questions: How has service research evolved over the past 27 years? Which articles have most influenced the evolution of service research in the past 27 years? What are the most promising research themes for the future?

To answer these questions, the authors analyze the contents of 3,177 service research articles published in ten major academic journals between 1993 and August 2019. Multiple correspondence analysis reveals the evolution of key service research themes and their underlying relationships.

The research themes are organized in a growth–share matrix with four quadrants (stars, question marks, cash cows and pets) and also combine into four research clusters (human resource management, organizational behavior and strategy, technology, and operations and customer behavior and marketing). Together with a specified list of influential articles that have shaped the evolution of service research, these insights suggest an agenda for research.

Acknowledging the vast growth of service research, this study presents an up-to-date picture of the discipline and an agenda to stimulate continued research.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1108/JSM-02-2019-0078</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="network2011happens">
        <article>
            <author>Network, Global Footprint</author>
            <title>What happens when infinite-growth economy runs into a finite planet</title>
            <journal>Global Footprint Network 2011 annual report. Oakland, California</journal>
            <year>2011</year>
            <pages>94607--3510</pages>
            <abstract>The Philippines builds momentum: Last year, the government began exploring ways to incorporate the Ecological Footprint into its proposed National Land Use Act for 2012. The legislation, a comprehensive national land-use policy, will protect areas from haphazard development and plan for the country's use and management of its physical resources. The government will continue to work with Global Footprint Network in 2012 to make the Philippines the first country in Southeast Asia to adopt the Footprint at the national level.</abstract>
            <url>https://www.footprintnetwork.org/content/images/article_uploads/Annual_Report_2011.pdf</url>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="henry2006aristotle">
        <article>
            <author>Henry, Devin</author>
            <title>Aristotle on the Mechanism of Inheritance</title>
            <journal>Journal of the History of Biology</journal>
            <year>2006</year>
            <volume>39</volume>
            <number>3</number>
            <pages>425--455</pages>
            <abstract>In this paper I address an important question in Aristotle’s biology, What are the causal mechanisms behind the transmission of biological form? Aristotle’s answer to this question, I argue, is found in Generation of Animals Book 4 in connection with his investigation into the phenomenon of inheritance. There we are told that an organism’s reproductive material contains a set of “movements'' which are derived from the various “potentials'' of its nature (the internal principle of change that initiates and controls development). These “movements,'' I suggest, function as specialized vehicles for communicating the parts of the parent’s heritable form during the act of reproduction. After exploring the details of this mechanism, I then take up Aristotle’s theory of inheritance proper. At the heart of the theory are three general principles (or ‘laws’) that govern the interactions between the maternal and paternal movements, the outcome of which determines the pattern of inheritance for the offspring. Although this paper is primarily aimed at providing a detailed analysis of Aristotle’s account of inheritance, the results of that analysis have implications for other areas of Aristotle’s biology. One of the most interesting of these is the question of whether Aristotle’s biology is anti-evolutionary (as traditionally assumed) or whether (as I argue) it leaves room for a theory of evolution by natural selection, even if Aristotle himself never took that step.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1007/s10739-005-3058-y</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="mueller2017archean">
        <article>
            <author>Mueller, Paul A and Nutman, Allen P</author>
            <title>The Archean-Hadean Earth: modern paradigms and ancient processes</title>
            <journal>The Web of Geological Sciences Advances Impacts and Interactions II</journal>
            <year>2017</year>
            <volume>523</volume>
            <pages>175--237</pages>
            <abstract>his contribution attempts to recount our collective progress in understanding the Archean–Hadean Earth system over the past 50 yr. Many realms of the geological sciences (geochemistry, petrology, geophysics, structural geology, geobiology, planetary science, and more) have made substantive contributions to this effort. These contributions have changed our understanding of the Archean–Hadean Earth in five major areas: (1) the expanse of Archean–Hadean time; (2) tectonics and lithospheric evolution, particularly possible analogs for the sites of modern, primary crust production and mantle differentiation (e.g., magmatic arcs, ocean ridges, and large igneous provinces); (3) evolution of the atmosphere-hydrosphere system, and its impact...</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1130/2017.2523(03)</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="perkins2009earth">
        <article>
            <author>Perkins, Sid</author>
            <title>Earth: Plate tectonics may have had an early start: Ancient zircon crystals imply activity during Hadean eon</title>
            <journal>Science News</journal>
            <year>2009</year>
            <volume>175</volume>
            <number>1</number>
            <pages>10--10</pages>
            <abstract>The chemical composition of ancient crystals bolsters the notion that tectonic plates may have jostled across Earth’s surface more than 4 billion years ago.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1002/scin.2009.5591750108</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="ermakov2018living">
        <article>
            <author>Ermakov, VV and Kovalsky, Yu V</author>
            <title>Living matter of the biosphere: mass and chemical elemental composition</title>
            <journal>Geochemistry International</journal>
            <year>2018</year>
            <volume>56</volume>
            <number>10</number>
            <pages>969--981</pages>
            <abstract>The paper discusses V.I. Vernadsky’s concept of living matter of the biosphere. Living matter in the sense of all organisms of the biosphere considered collectively is heterogeneous, plastic, integral, organized, and facilitates the continuous movement of atoms of chemical elements, transforms energy, and forms and preserves corresponding environments. Living matter is characterized by a certain chemical elemental composition and mass and performs certain functions. Living matter is mosaic and ubiquitous. It is characterized by homeostasis due to biological diversity, multiple relations between individual organisms, and the unique ability of adaptation. The paper reports data on the mass of living matter, its differentiation, and chemical composition.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1134/S0016702918100063</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="oparin">
        <book>
            <author>Alexander Ivánovich Oparin</author>
            <title>El origen de la vida</title>
            <publisher>Akal</publisher>
            <year>2015</year>
            <isbn>978-84-460-4172-6</isbn>
        </book>
    </entry>
    <entry id="genova2016scientometric">
        <article>
            <author>Génova, Gonzalo and Astudillo, Hernán and Fraga, Anabel</author>
            <title>The scientometric bubble considered harmful</title>
            <journal>Science and Engineering Ethics</journal>
            <year>2016</year>
            <volume>22</volume>
            <number>1</number>
            <pages>227--235</pages>
            <abstract>This article deals with a modern disease of academic science that consists of an enormous increase in the number of scientific publications without a corresponding advance of knowledge. Findings are sliced as thin as salami and submitted to different journals to produce more papers. If we consider academic papers as a kind of scientific ‘currency’ that is backed by gold bullion in the central bank of ‘true’ science, then we are witnessing an article-inflation phenomenon, a scientometric bubble that is most harmful for science and promotes an unethical and antiscientific culture among researchers. The main problem behind the scenes is that the impact factor is used as a proxy for quality. Therefore, not only for convenience, but also based on ethical principles of scientific research, we adhere to the San Francisco Declaration on Research Assessment when it emphasizes “the need to eliminate the use of journal-based metrics in funding, appointment and promotion considerations; and the need to assess research on its own merits rather on the journal in which the research is published”. Our message is mainly addressed to the funding agencies and universities that award tenures or grants and manage research programmes, especially in developing countries. The message is also addressed to well-established scientists who have the power to change things when they participate in committees for grants and jobs.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1007/s11948-015-9632-6</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="turiel2020petrocalipsis">
        <book>
            <author>Turiel, Antonio</author>
            <title>Petrocalipsis: Crisis energética global y cómo (no) la vamos a solucionar</title>
            <publisher>Editorial Alfabeto</publisher>
            <year>2020</year>
            <abstract>Petrocalypse is a raw and clear analysis of the possible alternatives to our current energy system. In contrast to the triumphalism that often appears in the news about the future use of new energy sources, the book concisely explains why each of the false solutions that have been discussed over the last two decades do not and will not work. There are no simple solutions or shortcuts to the dilemma posed by the energy transition, which is doubly necessary not only because of the environmental impact of fossil fuels, but also because of an often ignored factor: their upcoming scarcity. In contrast to the blind faith in technology that political and economic decision-makers seem to profess, the author explains that nothing can prevent us from following a path of energy decline in the coming decades that nobody wants to talk about. Reading this book makes it clear that if we want to avoid the worst case scenario, the "petrocalypse", we must stop deluding ourselves, understand our real situation and act accordingly as soon as possible.</abstract>
            <isbn>978-84-17951-11-5</isbn>
        </book>
    </entry>
    <entry id="fischer2007mind">
        <article>
            <author>Fischer, Joern and Manning, Adrian D and Steffen, Will and Rose, Deborah B and Daniell, Katherine and Felton, Adam and Garnett, Stephen and Gilna, Ben and Heinsohn, Rob and Lindenmayer, David B and others</author>
            <title>Mind the sustainability gap</title>
            <journal>Trends in ecology \&amp; evolution</journal>
            <year>2007</year>
            <volume>22</volume>
            <number>12</number>
            <pages>621--624</pages>
            <abstract>Despite increasing efforts to reach sustainability, key global biophysical indicators such as climate change and biodiversity loss continue to deteriorate rather than improve. Ongoing failure to move towards sustainability calls into question the focus of current research and policy. We recommend two strategies for progress. First, sustainability must be conceptualized as a hierarchy of considerations, with the biophysical limits of the Earth setting the ultimate boundaries within which social and economic goals must be achieved. Second, transdisciplinary research programs must confront key normative questions facing modern consumer societies. The humanities should have a key role in such programs. Assisted by these strategies, ambitious targets that realistically reflect the biophysical limits of the life-support system of the Earth must be set and relentlessly worked towards.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tree.2007.08.016</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="cousins2022outside">
        <article>
            <author>Cousins, Ian T and Johansson, Jana H and Salter, Matthew E and Sha, Bo and Scheringer, Martin</author>
            <title>Outside the Safe Operating Space of a New Planetary Boundary for Per-and Polyfluoroalkyl Substances (PFAS)</title>
            <journal>Environmental Science \&amp; Technology</journal>
            <year>2022</year>
            <abstract>It is hypothesized that environmental contamination by per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances (PFAS) defines a separate planetary boundary and that this boundary has been exceeded. This hypothesis is tested by comparing the levels of four selected perfluoroalkyl acids (PFAAs) (i.e., perfluorooctanesulfonic acid (PFOS), perfluorooctanoic acid (PFOA), perfluorohexanesulfonic acid (PFHxS), and perfluorononanoic acid (PFNA)) in various global environmental media (i.e., rainwater, soils, and surface waters) with recently proposed guideline levels. On the basis of the four PFAAs considered, it is concluded that (1) levels of PFOA and PFOS in rainwater often greatly exceed US Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) Lifetime Drinking Water Health Advisory levels and the sum of the aforementioned four PFAAs (Σ4 PFAS) in rainwater is often above Danish drinking water limit values also based on Σ4 PFAS; (2) levels of PFOS in rainwater are often above Environmental Quality Standard for Inland European Union Surface Water; and (3) atmospheric deposition also leads to global soils being ubiquitously contaminated and to be often above proposed Dutch guideline values. It is, therefore, concluded that the global spread of these four PFAAs in the atmosphere has led to the planetary boundary for chemical pollution being exceeded. Levels of PFAAs in atmospheric deposition are especially poorly reversible because of the high persistence of PFAAs and their ability to continuously cycle in the hydrosphere, including on sea spray aerosols emitted from the oceans. Because of the poor reversibility of environmental exposure to PFAS and their associated effects, it is vitally important that PFAS uses and emissions are rapidly restricted.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.est.2c02765</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="kosoy2012pillars">
        <article>
            <author>Kosoy, Nicolas and Brown, Peter G and Bosselmann, Klaus and Duraiappah, Anantha and Mackey, Brendan and Martinez-Alier, Joan and Rogers, Deborah and Thomson, Robert</author>
            <title>Pillars for a flourishing Earth: planetary boundaries, economic growth delusion and green economy</title>
            <journal>Current Opinion in Environmental Sustainability</journal>
            <year>2012</year>
            <volume>4</volume>
            <number>1</number>
            <pages>74--79</pages>
            <abstract>In the hue and cry about the ‘green economy’ leading up to Rio + 20 a number of simple points have been neglected. First, the purposes of the economy have been too narrowly conceived. Second, the role of demand management is vastly underplayed. Third, the assumptions about the nature of reality are inconsistent with contemporary science. Fourth, it is mired in a complex discourse about measurement, which fails to even recognize that all economies are dependent on living within Earth's biogeochemical constraints. Fifth, it uses a conceptual framework laid down in the 18th century and tries to apply it to the Anthropocene. The simple, but to many unthinkable, fact is that you cannot get to a flourishing or even sustainable Earth if you start with the assumptions of neo-classical economics. This is not to say that some of the neo-classical tools are not useful, but that they must be deployed in a framework that it does not and cannot supply.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cosust.2012.02.002</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="hanavcek2020ecological">
        <article>
            <author>Hanaček, Ksenija and Roy, Brototi and Avila, Sofia and Kallis, Giorgos</author>
            <title>Ecological economics and degrowth: Proposing a future research agenda from the margins</title>
            <journal>Ecological Economics</journal>
            <year>2020</year>
            <volume>169</volume>
            <pages>106495</pages>
            <abstract>Research by ecological economists on degrowth is a flourishing field. Existing research has focused on limits to (green) growth and on economic alternatives for prospering without growth. Future research, we argue here, should pay more attention to, and be written, from the “margins” – that is from the point of view of those marginalized in the growth economy. We conduct a comprehensive systematic review of the prevalent themes in the existing literature on the ecological economics of degrowth, and its engagements with North-South relations and gender issues. The analysis identifies seven research areas where ecological economics can better integrate these matters, namely: the study of post-growth policies for the Global South; the unequal exchanges that sustain an imperial mode of living; the deconstruction of ecological economic concepts that reproduce problematic Western or gendered assumptions; the study of the clash of metabolisms in peripheries of the Global South; the metabolism of care-work in growth economies; the leading role of women in ecological distribution conflicts, and the reproduction of gender inequalities in alternative post-growth spaces. We propose that ecological economics should welcome more contributions from critical feminist scholarship and scholars from the Global South.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ecolecon.2019.106495</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="grimes2018modelling">
        <article>
            <author>Grimes, David Robert and Bauch, Chris T and Ioannidis, John PA</author>
            <title>Modelling science trustworthiness under publish or perish pressure</title>
            <journal>Royal Society open science</journal>
            <year>2018</year>
            <volume>5</volume>
            <number>1</number>
            <pages>171511</pages>
            <abstract>Scientific publication is immensely important to the scientific endeavour. There is, however, concern that rewarding scientists chiefly on publication creates a perverse incentive, allowing careless and fraudulent conduct to thrive, compounded by the predisposition of top-tier journals towards novel, positive findings rather than investigations confirming null hypothesis. This potentially compounds a reproducibility crisis in several fields, and risks undermining science and public trust in scientific findings. To date, there has been comparatively little modelling on factors that influence science trustworthiness, despite the importance of quantifying the problem. We present a simple phenomenological model with cohorts of diligent, careless and unethical scientists, with funding allocated by published outputs. This analysis suggests that trustworthiness of published science in a given field is influenced by false positive rate, and pressures for positive results. We find decreasing available funding has negative consequences for resulting trustworthiness, and examine strategies to combat propagation of irreproducible science.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1098/rsos.171511</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="yang2020greenwashing">
        <article>
            <author>Yang, Zhi and Nguyen, Thi Thu Huong and Nguyen, Hoang Nam and Nguyen, Thi Thuy Nga and Cao, Thi Thanh</author>
            <title>Greenwashing behaviours: causes, taxonomy and consequences based on a systematic literature review</title>
            <journal>Journal of Business Economics and Management</journal>
            <year>2020</year>
            <volume>21</volume>
            <number>5</number>
            <pages>1486--1507</pages>
            <month>sep</month>
            <abstract>This study used the systematic review methodology to examine peer-reviewed journal articles published in the Web of Science, ScienceDirect, Springer and Emerald Insight during the 2000–2020 period to analyse greenwashing. In an open market, the behaviours of state-owned enterprises (SOEs), private firms and multinational corporations (MNCs) pose an implicit greenwashing threat. Our focal point is to analyse corporate greenwashing in MNCs in host emerging markets, particularly in Asia, for two reasons. First, reports of greenwashing have increased around the world since Volkswagen was revealed to have falsified automobile emissions data. Second, MNCs play an important role in expanding market size and their behaviour is increasingly unpredictable. The analysis shows that MNCs tend to engage in greenwashing immediately after doing business in host emerging markets characterised by restricted regulations, clear market opportunities and low competitive pressure. When greenwashing occurs, it will harm the interests of not only consumers, but also society as a whole, despite offering significant benefits to existing stakeholders. In this case, the authorities should implement regulations to confront MNCs before attracting them, which should be enforced in practice.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.3846/jbem.2020.13225</doi>
            <keywords>green marketing; greenwashing behaviour; environmental performance; corporate communication; corporate social responsibility; business ethics; sustainability</keywords>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="schroder2019degrowth">
        <article>
            <author>Schröder, Patrick and Bengtsson, Magnus and Cohen, Maurie and Dewick, Paul and Hofstetter, Joerg and Sarkis, Joseph</author>
            <title>Degrowth within--Aligning circular economy and strong sustainability narratives</title>
            <journal>Resources, Conservation and Recycling</journal>
            <year>2019</year>
            <volume>146</volume>
            <pages>190--191</pages>
            <abstract>This perspective calls for building greater understanding of overlapping and conflicting considerations between the sustainability principles that inform current conceptions of circular economy and degrowth. We contend that scholars and practitioners need to be pragmatic and to recognize evident ideological differences, but simultaneously to acknowledge beneficial similarities and complements. The common aim of both frameworks – to change business-as-usual and to enable human society to operate within ecological planetary boundaries – will likely engender opportunities to formulate new solutions. Management of the inherent tensions, such as the scale and scope of rebound effects, will continue to pose challenges. However, with thoughtful dialogue, commitment to respectful discourse, and more refined articulation we are confident that progress will be made. By building on synergies and seeking holistic strategies, the academic community, along with its transdisciplinary partners, can advance strong global sustainability efforts.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.resconrec.2019.03.038</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="kallis2018research">
        <article>
            <author>Kallis, Giorgos and Kostakis, Vasilis and Lange, Steffen and Muraca, Barbara and Paulson, Susan and Schmelzer, Matthias</author>
            <title>Research on degrowth</title>
            <journal>Annual Review of Environment and Resources</journal>
            <year>2018</year>
            <volume>43</volume>
            <number>1</number>
            <pages>291--316</pages>
            <abstract>Scholars and activists mobilize increasingly the term degrowth when producing knowledge critical of the ideology and costs of growth-based development. Degrowth signals a radical political and economic reorganization leading to reduced resource and energy use. The degrowth hypothesis posits that such a trajectory of social transformation is necessary, desirable, and possible; the conditions of its realization require additional study. Research on degrowth has reinvigorated the limits to growth debate with critical examination of the historical, cultural, social, and political forces that have made economic growth a dominant objective. Here we review studies of economic stability in the absence of growth and of societies that have managed well without growth. We reflect on forms of technology and democracy com-patible with degrowth and discuss plausible openings for a degrowth transition. This dynamic and productive research agenda asks inconvenient questions that sustainability sciences can no longer afford to ignore.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev-environ-102017-025941</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="fitzhugh2016phylogenetic">
        <article>
            <author>Fitzhugh, Kirk</author>
            <title>Phylogenetic hypotheses: neither testable nor falsifiable</title>
            <journal>Evolutionary Biology</journal>
            <year>2016</year>
            <volume>43</volume>
            <number>2</number>
            <pages>257--266</pages>
            <abstract>Crother and Murray (Cladistics 31: 573–574, 2015) criticize the statement by Assis (Cladistics 30: 240–242, 2014) that phylogenetic hypotheses are amenable to testing but not falsification. The claims by both sets of authors are based on long-standing misconceptions about testing developed within systematics. Testing phylogenetic hypotheses confuses the inferences of those hypotheses by way of abductive reasoning with their being tested via induction. Cladograms lack the causal details of the different hypotheses implied by those diagrams to make testing feasible, and falsification has been shown to be problematic for historical sciences.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1007/s11692-016-9381-8</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="martin2016physiology">
        <article>
            <author>Martin, William F and Weiss, Madeline C and Neukirchen, Sinje and Nelson-Sathi, Shijulal and Sousa, Filipa L</author>
            <title>Physiology, phylogeny, and LUCA</title>
            <journal>Microbial Cell</journal>
            <year>2016</year>
            <volume>3</volume>
            <number>12</number>
            <pages>582</pages>
            <abstract>Genomes record their own history. But if we want to look all the way back to life's beginnings some 4 billion years ago, the record of microbial evolution that is preserved in prokaryotic genomes is not easy to read. Microbiology has a lot in common with geology in that regard. Geologists know that plate tectonics and erosion have erased much of the geological record, with ancient rocks being truly rare. The same is true of microbes. Lateral gene transfer (LGT) and sequence divergence have erased much of the evolutionary record that was once written in genomes, and it is not obvious which genes among sequenced genomes are genuinely ancient. Which genes trace to the last universal ancestor, LUCA? The classical approach has been to look for genes that are universally distributed. Another approach is to make all trees for all genes, and sift out the trees where signals have been overwritten by LGT. What is left ought to be ancient. If we do that, what do we find?</abstract>
            <doi>10.15698/mic2016.12.545</doi>
            <keywords>early evolution, autotrophy, geochemistry, acetogens, methanogens</keywords>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="ellegaard2015bibliometric">
        <article>
            <author>Ellegaard, Ole and Wallin, Johan A</author>
            <title>The bibliometric analysis of scholarly production: How great is the impact?</title>
            <journal>Scientometrics</journal>
            <year>2015</year>
            <volume>105</volume>
            <number>3</number>
            <pages>1809--1831</pages>
            <abstract>Bibliometric methods or “analysis” are now firmly established as scientific specialties and are an integral part of research evaluation methodology especially within the scientific and applied fields. The methods are used increasingly when studying various aspects of science and also in the way institutions and universities are ranked worldwide. A sufficient number of studies have been completed, and with the resulting literature, it is now possible to analyse the bibliometric method by using its own methodology. The bibliometric literature in this study, which was extracted from Web of Science, is divided into two parts using a method comparable to the method of Jonkers et al. (Characteristics of bibliometrics articles in library and information sciences (LIS) and other journals, pp. 449–551, 2012: The publications either lie within the Information and Library Science (ILS) category or within the non-ILS category which includes more applied, “subject” based studies. The impact in the different groupings is judged by means of citation analysis using normalized data and an almost linear increase can be observed from 1994 onwards in the non-ILS category. The implication for the dissemination and use of the bibliometric methods in the different contexts is discussed. A keyword analysis identifies the most popular subjects covered by bibliometric analysis, and multidisciplinary articles are shown to have the highest impact. A noticeable shift is observed in those countries which contribute to the pool of bibliometric analysis, as well as a self-perpetuating effect in giving and taking references.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1007/s11192-015-1645-z</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="roberston1998darwinian">
        <article>
            <author>Roberston, David and Robinson, Jennifer</author>
            <title>Darwinian daisyworld</title>
            <journal>Journal of theoretical biology</journal>
            <year>1998</year>
            <volume>195</volume>
            <number>1</number>
            <pages>129--134</pages>
            <abstract>The Daisyworld model was developed to show that organisms can collectively regulate the global environment without assuming conscious or altruistic behaviour, i.e. that Gaia is feasible. We studied the effects of adaptive evolution of Daisyworld by allowing daisies to shift their optimal growth temperatures toward the prevailing temperature. This estimates Daisyworld's homeostatic ability, suggesting a trade-off between the ability of organisms to collectively regulate the environment and the abilities of evolving genotypes to adapt to it.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1006/jtbi.1998.0799</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="kleidon2009nonequilibrium">
        <article>
            <author>Kleidon, Axel</author>
            <title>Nonequilibrium thermodynamics and maximum entropy production in the Earth system</title>
            <journal>Naturwissenschaften</journal>
            <year>2009</year>
            <volume>96</volume>
            <number>6</number>
            <pages>1--25</pages>
            <abstract>The Earth system is maintained in a unique state far from thermodynamic equilibrium, as, for instance, reflected in the high concentration of reactive oxygen in the atmosphere. The myriad of processes that transform energy, that result in the motion of mass in the atmosphere, in oceans, and on land, processes that drive the global water, carbon, and other biogeochemical cycles, all have in common that they are irreversible in their nature. Entropy production is a general consequence of these processes and measures their degree of irreversibility. The proposed principle of maximum entropy production (MEP) states that systems are driven to steady states in which they produce entropy at the maximum possible rate given the prevailing constraints. In this review, the basics of nonequilibrium thermodynamics are described, as well as how these apply to Earth system processes. Applications of the MEP principle are discussed, ranging from the strength of the atmospheric circulation, the hydrological cycle, and biogeochemical cycles to the role that life plays in these processes. Nonequilibrium thermodynamics and the MEP principle have potentially wide-ranging implications for our understanding of Earth system functioning, how it has evolved in the past, and why it is habitable. Entropy production allows us to quantify an objective direction of Earth system change (closer to vs further away from thermodynamic equilibrium, or, equivalently, towards a state of MEP). When a maximum in entropy production is reached, MEP implies that the Earth system reacts to perturbations primarily with negative feedbacks. In conclusion, this nonequilibrium thermodynamic view of the Earth system shows great promise to establish a holistic description of the Earth as one system. This perspective is likely to allow us to better understand and predict its function as one entity, how it has evolved in the past, and how it is modified by human activities in the future.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1007/s00114-009-0509-x</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="lynch2001rhizosphere">
        <article>
            <author>Lynch, James M and Brimecombe, Melissa J and De Leij, Frans AAM</author>
            <title>Rhizosphere</title>
            <journal>e LS</journal>
            <year>2001</year>
            <abstract>The rhizosphere is that part of the soil ecosystem where plant roots, soil and the soil biota interact with each other. These interactions are often of benefit to plants, improve soil fertility and enhance the degradation of toxic chemicals. Rhizodeposition from plants is the key energy supply for the rhizosphere biota. Mineral nutrients are supplied by the soil matrix, organic residues and biological nitrogen fixation. The interactive biotic community includes microorganisms, protozoa and soil fauna. Some organisms are beneficial whereas others are harmful. Some deleterious organisms can be suppressed in a variety of biological control strategies. The key physical factors governing rhizosphere activity are temperature, water availability, oxygen, pH and soil structure. The rhizosphere has strong influences on agriculture, and the bioremediation of contaminated and degraded land.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1002/9780470015902.a0000403.pub2</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="lal2015carbon">
        <article>
            <author>Lal, Rattan and Negassa, Wakene and Lorenz, Klaus</author>
            <title>Carbon sequestration in soil</title>
            <journal>Current Opinion in Environmental Sustainability</journal>
            <year>2015</year>
            <volume>15</volume>
            <pages>79--86</pages>
            <abstract>Soil carbon (C) sequestration implies transferring of atmospheric CO2 into soil of a land unit through its plants. Co-benefits of soil C sequestration include: advancing food and nutritional security, increasing renewability and quality of water, improving biodiversity, and strengthening elemental recycling. Threshold level of soil organic C (SOC) in the root zone is 1.5–2.0%. SOC is influenced by land use, soil management and farming systems. To 1-m depth, more than 50% total C pool is contained between 0.3 and 1 m depth. Soils of agroecosystems are strongly depleted of their SOC stock and are degraded. Restoring soil quality necessitates increasing SOC concentration by adopting best management practices (i.e., conservation agriculture) which create a positive C budget. French Government is proposing to COP-21 of UNFCCC in December 2015 that SOC concentration be increased globally at 4 per 1000 per year to mitigate climate change and advance food security.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cosust.2015.09.002</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="liang2020novel">
        <article>
            <author>Liang, Jie-Liang and Liu, Jun and Jia, Pu and Yang, Tao-tao and Zeng, Qing-wei and Zhang, Sheng-chang and Liao, Bin and Shu, Wen-sheng and Li, Jin-tian</author>
            <title>Novel phosphate-solubilizing bacteria enhance soil phosphorus cycling following ecological restoration of land degraded by mining</title>
            <journal>The ISME journal</journal>
            <year>2020</year>
            <volume>14</volume>
            <number>6</number>
            <pages>1600--1613</pages>
            <abstract>Little is known about the changes in soil microbial phosphorus (P) cycling potential during terrestrial ecosystem management and restoration, although much research aims to enhance soil P cycling. Here, we used metagenomic sequencing to analyse 18 soil microbial communities at a P-deficient degraded mine site in southern China where ecological restoration was implemented using two soil ameliorants and eight plant species. Our results show that the relative abundances of key genes governing soil microbial P-cycling potential were higher at the restored site than at the unrestored site, indicating enhancement of soil P cycling following restoration. The gcd gene, encoding an enzyme that mediates inorganic P solubilization, was predominant across soil samples and was a major determinant of bioavailable soil P. We reconstructed 39 near-complete bacterial genomes harboring gcd, which represented diverse novel phosphate-solubilizing microbial taxa. Strong correlations were found between the relative abundance of these genomes and bioavailable soil P, suggesting their contributions to the enhancement of soil P cycling. Moreover, 84 mobile genetic elements were detected in the scaffolds containing gcd in the 39 genomes, providing evidence for the role of phage-related horizontal gene transfer in assisting soil microbes to acquire new metabolic potential related to P cycling.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41396-020-0632-4</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="filippelli2002global">
        <article>
            <author>Filippelli, Gabriel M</author>
            <title>The global phosphorus cycle</title>
            <journal>Reviews in mineralogy and geochemistry</journal>
            <year>2002</year>
            <volume>48</volume>
            <number>1</number>
            <pages>391--425</pages>
            <abstract>Phosphorus (P) is a limiting nutrient for terrestrial biological productivity that
commonly plays a key role in net carbon uptake in terrestrial ecosystems (Tiessen et al.
1984, Roberts et al. 1985, Lajtha and Schlesinger 1988). Unlike nitrogen (another
limiting nutrient but one with an abundant atmospheric pool), the availability of “new” P
in ecosystems is restricted by the rate of release of this element during soil weathering.
Because of the limitations of P availability, P is generally recycled to various extents in
ecosystems depending on climate, soil type, and ecosystem level. The release of P from
apatite dissolution is a key control on ecosystem productivity (Cole et al. 1977, Tiessen et
al. 1984, Roberts et al. 1985, Crews et al. 1995, Vitousek et al. 1997, Schlesinger et al.
1998), which in turn is critical to terrestrial carbon balances (e.g., Kump and Alley 1994,
Adams 1995). Furthermore, the weathering of P from the terrestrial system and transport
by rivers is the only appreciable source of P to the oceans. On longer time scales, this
supply of P also limits the total amount of primary production in the ocean (Holland
1978, Broecker 1982, Smith 1984, Filippelli and Delaney 1994). Thus, understanding the
controls on P weathering from land and transport to the ocean is important for models of
global change. In this paper, I will present an overview of the natural (pre-human) and
modern (syn-human) global P mass balances, followed by in-depth examinations of
several current areas of research in P cycling, including climatic controls on ecosystem
dynamics and soil development, the control of oxygen on coupled P and Carbon (C)
cycling in continental margins, and the role that P plays in controlling ocean productivity
on Cenozoic timescales</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.2138/rmg.2002.48.10</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="wang2021effects">
        <article>
            <author>Wang, Qiang and Zhang, Fuyu</author>
            <title>The effects of trade openness on decoupling carbon emissions from economic growth--evidence from 182 countries</title>
            <journal>Journal of cleaner production</journal>
            <year>2021</year>
            <volume>279</volume>
            <pages>123838</pages>
            <month>jan</month>
            <abstract>The current rise of protectionism has become the main uncertainty associated with global energy, economy, and the environment. Furthermore, the decoupling carbon emissions from economic growth is crucial for implementing Intended Nationally Determined Contributions (INDCs). These INDCs would be discounted if decreasing carbon emissions would require sacrificing economic growth. This study explored the effect of protectionism (by measuring trade openness based on available data) on the decoupling carbon emissions from economic growth. For this, the heterogenous effects of trade openness on carbon emissions were investigated using in data of 182 countries from 1990 to 2015. The results show that trade openness decreased carbon emissions in high-income and upper-middle-income countries, while having no significant impact on carbon emissions of lower-middle-income countries; even worse, for low-income countries, trade openness increased carbon emissions. The heterogeneous effects of trade openness on carbon emissions indicate that trade openness positively impacts the decoupling economic growth from carbon emission in rich countries, but negatively impacts poor countries. In addition, increasing individual incomes and population distort the decoupling economic growth from carbon emissions. Renewable energy and high oil prices contributed to the decoupling economic growth from carbon emissions. These effects are similar in all countries. Targeted policy implications are presented that enable the decoupling economic growth from carbon emissions for countries with different income levels.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jclepro.2020.123838</doi>
            <keywords>Decoupling; Trade openness; Oil price; Income level; Renewable energy; Carbon emissions</keywords>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="gray1999mitochondrial">
        <article>
            <author>Gray, Michael W and Burger, Gertraud and Lang, B Franz</author>
            <title>Mitochondrial evolution</title>
            <journal>Science</journal>
            <year>1999</year>
            <volume>283</volume>
            <number>5407</number>
            <pages>1476--1481</pages>
            <abstract>The serial endosymbiosis theory is a favored model for explaining the origin of mitochondria, a defining event in the evolution of eukaryotic cells. As usually described, this theory posits that mitochondria are the direct descendants of a bacterial endosymbiont that became established at an early stage in a nucleus-containing (but amitochondriate) host cell. Gene sequence data strongly support a monophyletic origin of the mitochondrion from a eubacterial ancestor shared with a subgroup of the α-Proteobacteria. However, recent studies of unicellular eukaryotes (protists), some of them little known, have provided insights that challenge the traditional serial endosymbiosis–based view of how the eukaryotic cell and its mitochondrion came to be. These data indicate that the mitochondrion arose in a common ancestor of all extant eukaryotes and raise the possibility that this organelle originated at essentially the same time as the nuclear component of the eukaryotic cell rather than in a separate, subsequent event.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1126/science.283.5407.1476</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="saether1986myth">
        <article>
            <author>Saether, Ole A</author>
            <title>The myth of objectivity—post-Hennigian deviations</title>
            <journal>Cladistics</journal>
            <year>1986</year>
            <volume>2</volume>
            <number>1</number>
            <pages>1--13</pages>
            <abstract>The punctuated equilibrium speciation mode is an implied consequence of the deviation rule and the differences between cladograms and phylogenetic trees implicitly were recognized by Hennig. Neocladism and transformed cladism, however, both are contradictory to the view of Hennig. Neither of them will be consistent when parallel changes exceed informative unparallel changes, which in the real world there are many indications to believe they do. In three tables cladogenetic trends used in erecting three schemes of argumentation, on the specific, generic, and subfamily levels respectively, are analyzed and divided into: “objective” synapomorphies not allowing for outside parallelism or secondary change, subjective synapomorphies, and underlying synapomorphies. Evaluations based on the strictest criteria for asserting synapomorphy are possible only when comparing higher taxa of subfamily level and up. On the generic level trends showing outside parallelism can be rejected if all other possibly synapomorphic trends are included. On the specific level it is necessary to take all kinds of synapomorphies into consideration, including those showing outside parallelism. There may often be a preponderance of trends caused by parallel selection in taxa with specialized sexual and/or feeding behaviors, as exemplified by some chironomid male imagines and larvae. It is necessary to have knowledge of the nature of the different possible natural processes and try to explain these before undertaking estimations of patterns of kinship. The persistent intuitive and subjective element in phylogenetics was stressed by Hennig. Objectivity is a myth.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1096-0031.1986.tb00438.x</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="Fitzhugh2016">
        <article>
            <author>Fitzhugh, Kirk</author>
            <title>Phylogenetic hypotheses: neither testable nor falsifiable</title>
            <journal>Evolutionary Biology</journal>
            <year>2016</year>
            <volume>43</volume>
            <number>2</number>
            <pages>257--266</pages>
            <abstract>Crother and Murray (Cladistics 31: 573–574, 2015) criticize the statement by Assis (Cladistics 30: 240–242, 2014) that phylogenetic hypotheses are amenable to testing but not falsification. The claims by both sets of authors are based on long-standing misconceptions about testing developed within systematics. Testing phylogenetic hypotheses confuses the inferences of those hypotheses by way of abductive reasoning with their being tested via induction. Cladograms lack the causal details of the different hypotheses implied by those diagrams to make testing feasible, and falsification has been shown to be problematic for historical sciences.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1007/s11692-016-9381-8</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="base">
        <manual>
            <author>{R Core Team}</author>
            <title>R: A Language and Environment for Statistical Computing</title>
            <organization>R Foundation for Statistical Computing</organization>
            <address>Vienna, Austria</address>
            <year>2022</year>
            <abstract>R is a free software environment for statistical computing and graphics. It compiles and runs on a wide variety of UNIX platforms, Windows and MacOS. To download R, please choose your preferred CRAN mirror.</abstract>
            <url>https://www.R-project.org/</url>
        </manual>
    </entry>
    <entry id="berkner1964history">
        <inproceedings>
            <author>Berkner, LV and Marshall, LC</author>
            <title>The history of growth of oxygen in the earth's atmosphere</title>
            <booktitle>The origin and evolution of atmospheres and oceans</booktitle>
            <year>1964</year>
            <pages>102</pages>
        </inproceedings>
    </entry>
    <entry id="thauer2008methanogenic">
        <article>
            <author>Thauer, Rudolf K and Kaster, Anne-Kristin and Seedorf, Henning and Buckel, Wolfgang and Hedderich, Reiner</author>
            <title>Methanogenic archaea: ecologically relevant differences in energy conservation</title>
            <journal>Nature Reviews Microbiology</journal>
            <year>2008</year>
            <volume>6</volume>
            <number>8</number>
            <pages>579--591</pages>
            <abstract>Most methanogenic archaea can reduce CO2 with H2 to methane, and it is generally assumed that the reactions and mechanisms of energy conservation that are involved are largely the same in all methanogens. However, this does not take into account the fact that methanogens with cytochromes have considerably higher growth yields and threshold concentrations for H2 than methanogens without cytochromes. These and other differences can be explained by the proposal outlined in this Review that in methanogens with cytochromes, the first and last steps in methanogenesis from CO2 are coupled chemiosmotically, whereas in methanogens without cytochromes, these steps are energetically coupled by a cytoplasmic enzyme complex that mediates flavin-based electron bifurcation.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1038/nrmicro1931</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="goldblatt2006bistability">
        <article>
            <author>Goldblatt, Colin and Lenton, Timothy M and Watson, Andrew J</author>
            <title>Bistability of atmospheric oxygen and the Great Oxidation</title>
            <journal>Nature</journal>
            <year>2006</year>
            <volume>443</volume>
            <number>7112</number>
            <pages>683--686</pages>
            <abstract>The history of the Earth has been characterized by a series of major transitions separated by long periods of relative stability1. The largest chemical transition was the ‘Great Oxidation’, approximately 2.4 billion years ago, when atmospheric oxygen concentrations rose from less than 10-5 of the present atmospheric level (PAL) to more than 0.01 PAL, and possibly2 to more than 0.1 PAL. This transition took place long after oxygenic photosynthesis is thought to have evolved3,4,5, but the causes of this delay and of the Great Oxidation itself remain uncertain6,7,8,9,10,11. Here we show that the origin of oxygenic photosynthesis gave rise to two simultaneously stable steady states for atmospheric oxygen. The existence of a low-oxygen (less than 10-5 PAL) steady state explains how a reducing atmosphere persisted for at least 300 million years after the onset of oxygenic photosynthesis. The Great Oxidation can be understood as a switch to the high-oxygen (more than 5 × 10-3 PAL) steady state. The bistability arises because ultraviolet shielding of the troposphere by ozone becomes effective once oxygen levels exceed 10-5 PAL, causing a nonlinear increase in the lifetime of atmospheric oxygen. Our results indicate that the existence of oxygenic photosynthesis is not a sufficient condition for either an oxygen-rich atmosphere or the presence of an ozone layer, which has implications for detecting life on other planets using atmospheric analysis12,13 and for the evolution of multicellular life.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1038/nature05169</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="shaw2017feyerabend">
        <article>
            <author>Shaw, Jamie</author>
            <title>Was Feyerabend an anarchist? The structure (s) of ‘anything goes’</title>
            <journal>Studies in History and Philosophy of Science part A</journal>
            <year>2017</year>
            <volume>64</volume>
            <pages>11--21</pages>
            <abstract>The near consensus in the secondary literature on Feyerabend is that his epistemological anarchism, characterized by the slogan ‘anything goes’, was not a positive proposal but the conclusion of a reductio argument against his opponents (Lloyd 1997; Staley 1999; Munévar 2000; Farrell 2003; Tsou 2003; Oberheim 2006; Roe 2009). This makes anarchism a mere criticism rather than a substantive position in its own right. In this paper, I argue that Feyerabend held anarchism as a positive thesis. Specifically, I present two possible interpretations of anarchism: one where anarchism is entailed by Feyerabend’s radical view of pluralism and another where scientists must be ‘methodological opportunists’, which Feyerabend held simultaneously from at least 1970. I then consider how these positions fare against the more influential criticisms of anarchism (Nagel 1977; Worrall 1978; Godfrey-Smith 2003). I conclude by suggesting two avenues to constraining a literal interpretation of ‘anything goes’ on Feyerabendian grounds.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.shpsa.2017.06.002</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="nietzsche1998ocaso">
        <book>
            <author>Nietzsche, Friedrich Wilhelm</author>
            <title>El Ocaso de los Ídolos</title>
            <publisher>Tusquets</publisher>
            <year>1998</year>
            <url>https://www.academia.edu/download/56874771/El_crepusculo_de_los_idolos_F.Nietzsche.pdf</url>
        </book>
    </entry>
    <entry id="knowles2001lingua">
        <article>
            <author>Knowles, Lori P</author>
            <title>The lingua franca of human rights and the rise of a global bioethic</title>
            <journal>Cambridge Quarterly of Healthcare Ethics</journal>
            <year>2001</year>
            <volume>10</volume>
            <number>3</number>
            <pages>253--263</pages>
            <abstract>Globalization is often discussed as if it were a recent phenomenon relating primarily to the development of world financial markets and improvements in information and travel technologies. But globalization is an ancient process, beginning with mercantile and cultural exchanges and facilitated by advances in transportation. In the twentieth century, the results of globalization can be seen in the rise of global capitalism and in the construction of a global economy. Most recently, the process of globalization has moved beyond the world of finance, however, into areas still traditionally thought of as national concerns, such as culture and healthcare. It is no surprise, therefore, that increasingly the challenges the United States is confronting in healthcare, biotechnology, and the environment are simultaneously faced by the international community as a whole. In the wake of the HIV pandemic, growing environmental consciousness, and a series of sensational advances in biotechnology, there is a dawning realization that problems such as improving public health, regulating advances in biotechnology, and achieving sustainable environmental development transcend national borders. In other words, bioethics concerns are global in nature.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1017/S096318010100305X</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="jackson2020ending">
        <article>
            <author>Jackson, Bethany and Sparks, Jessica L Decker</author>
            <title>Ending slavery by decarbonisation? Exploring the nexus of modern slavery, deforestation, and climate change action via REDD+</title>
            <journal>Energy Research \&amp; Social Science</journal>
            <year>2020</year>
            <volume>69</volume>
            <pages>101610</pages>
            <abstract>Activities involving the deforestation are high-risk for modern slavery, and is an issue which has global consequences for forest environments and communities. Despite this, little work is being done to eradicate modern slavery from these sectors. Antislavery interventions have often been separate from the work of development providers despite sharing many congruent objectives. Here we outline one sector that could see the integration of antislavery and development interventions to support both at risk environments and highly vulnerable communities. It is proposed that antislavery interventions are incorporated into the national strategies of the Reducing Emissions from Deforestation and Forest Degradation (REDD+) programme which targets vulnerable communities to prevent deforestation and forest degradation. It is within these communities that vulnerability factors to modern slavery persist and lead to the degradation of the forest. It is posited that the incorporation of antislavery interventions
with REDD+ would improve efficiencies, target more vulnerable populations, protect the environment and support the Sustainable Development Goals (SDGs). By combining these efforts we can combat the effects of the modern slavery-environmental degradation nexus within an ecosystem that has been shown to be vital in the fight against anthropogenic climate change. With the renewal of REDD+ due, now is the time to integrate these measures.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.erss.2020.101610</doi>
            <keywords>Forest Degradation, Antislavery Interventions, Tree Loss, Modern Slavery- Environmental Degradation Nexus, Climate Change Mitigation and Adaptation</keywords>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="wollenweber2005need">
        <article>
            <author>Wollenweber, Bernd and Porter, John R and L{\"u}bberstedt, Thomas</author>
            <title>Need for multidisciplinary research towards a second green revolution</title>
            <journal>Current opinion in plant biology</journal>
            <year>2005</year>
            <volume>8</volume>
            <number>3</number>
            <pages>337--341</pages>
            <abstract>Despite recent achievements in conventional plant breeding and genomics, the rate of increase of crop yields is declining and thus there is a need for a second green revolution. Advances within single disciplines, alone, cannot solve the challenges of increasing yield. As scientific disciplines have become increasingly diversified, a more complete understanding of the mechanisms by which genetic and environmental variation modify grain yield and composition is needed, so that specific quantitative and quality targets can be identified. To achieve this aim, the expertise of plant genomics, physiology and agronomy, as well as recently developed plant modelling techniques, must be combined. There has been recent progress in these individual disciplines, but multidisciplinary approaches must be implemented to tackle drought stress and salinity as major constraints to achieving sufficient grain yield in the future.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.pbi.2005.03.001</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="d2013global">
        <article>
            <author>D’Odorico, Paolo and Bhattachan, Abinash and Davis, Kyle F. and Ravi, Sujith and Runyan, Christiane W.</author>
            <title>Global desertification: drivers and feedbacks</title>
            <journal>Advances in water resources</journal>
            <year>2013</year>
            <volume>51</volume>
            <pages>326--344</pages>
            <abstract>Desertification is a change in soil properties, vegetation or climate, which results in a persistent loss of ecosystem services that are fundamental to sustaining life. Desertification affects large dryland areas around the world and is a major cause of stress in human societies. Here we review recent research on the drivers, feedbacks, and impacts of desertification. A multidisciplinary approach to understanding the drivers and feedbacks of global desertification is motivated by our increasing need to improve global food production and to sustainably manage ecosystems in the context of climate change. Classic desertification theories look at this process as a transition between stable states in bistable ecosystem dynamics. Climate change (i.e., aridification) and land use dynamics are the major drivers of an ecosystem shift to a “desertified” (or “degraded”) state. This shift is typically sustained by positive feedbacks, which stabilize the system in the new state. Desertification feedbacks may involve land degradation processes (e.g., nutrient loss or salinization), changes in rainfall regime resulting from land-atmosphere interactions (e.g., precipitation recycling, dust emissions), or changes in plant community composition (e.g., shrub encroachment, decrease in vegetation cover). We analyze each of these feedback mechanisms and discuss their possible enhancement by interactions with socio-economic drivers. Large scale effects of desertification include the emigration of “environmental refugees” displaced from degraded areas, climatic changes, and the alteration of global biogeochemical cycles resulting from the emission and long-range transport of fine mineral dust. Recent research has identified some possible early warning signs of desertification, which can be used as indicators of resilience loss and imminent shift to desert-like conditions. We conclude with a brief discussion on some desertification control strategies implemented in different regions around the world.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.advwatres.2012.01.013</doi>
            <keywords>Desertification Land degradation Ecohydrology Feedbacks Overgrazing Soil salinity</keywords>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="pertoldi2007evolutionary">
        <article>
            <author>Pertoldi, C and Bach, LA</author>
            <title>Evolutionary aspects of climate-induced changes and the need for multidisciplinarity</title>
            <journal>Journal of Thermal Biology</journal>
            <year>2007</year>
            <volume>32</volume>
            <number>3</number>
            <pages>118--124</pages>
            <abstract>An integrated view on the possible effects of global climate change is provided while taking into account that not only the rising average temperature is likely to impact natural populations but also that increased variation around the mean and higher frequency of extreme events will be important. We propose that complex genetic effects in concert with demographic patterns may affect how focal populations react to the environmental challenge in an adaptive way (if they can). In order to aim for an inclusive picture of the ongoing environmental change we argue for a synthesis of knowledge from a range of ‘classical’ disciplines such as quantitative genetics, conservation genetics and population ecology. A hereto little exposed concern is the importance of the increase in amplitude of environmental fluctuations and how the corresponding evolutionary and ecological reactions are expected to occur. Due to the complex interactions between the ecological and genetic mechanisms in the response to climate-induced impacts interdisciplinary approaches are the most promising path in seeking knowledge about the present and future changes in the biosphere.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jtherbio.2007.01.011</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="manning2013challenges">
        <incollection>
            <author>Manning, Patrick</author>
            <title>Challenges of Big Data in History</title>
            <booktitle>Big Data in History</booktitle>
            <publisher>Springer</publisher>
            <year>2013</year>
            <pages>1--13</pages>
            <abstract>This book makes the case for expanding the worldwide historical archive now under development through the Collaborative for Historical Information and Analysis (CHIA). The opening chapter emphasizes that the time has come for using available technology to create a coherent record of human social change in recent centuries, so as to link patterns of past change to the great policy decisions our society faces. The chapter underscores the fundamentally collaborative nature of CHIA’s expanding worldwide project, comparing it to existing projects in climate modeling and genetic databases. It describes the five major levels of the archive — tied together by the three missions for developing them — and the global analysis that will emerge from the fifth level. It introduces the succeeding chapters on the construction of the global historical archive and its intended use by researchers and the general public.</abstract>
            <doi>10.1057/9781137378972_1</doi>
        </incollection>
    </entry>
    <entry id="gokturk2005paradigm">
        <article>
            <author>Göktürk, Erek</author>
            <title>What is “paradigm”</title>
            <journal>Department of Informatics, University of Oslo</journal>
            <year>2005</year>
            <abstract>Today, the word “paradigm” is being used with a vague definition. In this paper, an attempt at clarifying the meaning of the word “paradigm” is made, with reference to its philosophical roots and how it came to its proliferation of use.</abstract>
            <url>https://citeseerx.ist.psu.edu/document?repid=rep1&amp;type=pdf&amp;doi=53158c78b2c7caec7ffe728f1d286b7df36dd7a2</url>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="worrall2003paradigms">
        <inbook>
            <pages>65--71</pages>
            <year>2003</year>
            <author>Worrall, John</author>
            <bibtexkey>worrall2003paradigms</bibtexkey>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <abstract>One sixties' summer, shortly before the ‘Summer of Love’, probably the two most widely influential philosophers of science of the twentieth century – Karl Popper and Thomas Kuhn – met at a conference in ‘swinging London’ to compare and contrast their views on the nature of theory change in science.

The debate was recorded (and extended) in an influential book called Criticism and the Growth of Knowledge Although Kuhn was at pains to begin his paper (1970) by stressing similarities between his own views of scientific development and those of ‘Sir Karl’, and although Kuhn's official line was that the differences between Popper and himself were ‘comparatively secondary’, it soon became clear that those differences were in fact sharp and apparently rather deep. Kuhn claimed, for example, that ‘Sir Karl has characterized the entire scientific enterprise in terms that apply only to its occasional revolutionary parts’ (p. 6). And he suggested that to accept his own account of science was, in effect, ‘to turn Sir Karl's view on its head’ by accepting that ‘it is precisely the abandonment of critical discourse that marks the transition to a science’ (ibid.). Popper responded by, amongst other things, admitting that Kuhn's ‘normal science’ is a real phenomenon and that he had indeed hitherto failed fully to recognise it – but he did so reluctantly in the way that a starstruck lover might be brought to admit that he had hitherto been blind to an imperfection in his inamorata.</abstract>
            <title>Paradigms and Progress: Kuhn'versus''Popper and Lakatos</title>
            <url>http://polanco.jesuits-africa.education:8080/jspui/bitstream/123456789/74/1/Thomas%20Kuhn%20%28Contemporary%20Philosophy%20in%20Focus%29.pdf#page=79</url>
        </inbook>
    </entry>
    <entry id="wilson1997consilience">
        <book>
            <author>Wilson, Edward O</author>
            <title>Consilience</title>
            <publisher>Random House</publisher>
            <year>1999</year>
            <edition>1</edition>
            <month>#apr#</month>
            <abstract>One of our greatest scientists—and the winner of two Pulitzer Prizes for On Human Nature and The Ants—gives us a work of visionary importance that may be the crowning achievement of his career. In Consilience (a word that originally meant "jumping together"), Edward O. Wilson renews the Enlightenment's search for a unified theory of knowledge in disciplines that range from physics to biology, the social sciences and the humanities.

Using the natural sciences as his model, Wilson forges dramatic links between fields. He explores the chemistry of the mind and the genetic bases of culture. He postulates the biological principles underlying works of art from cave-drawings to Lolita. Presenting the latest findings in prose of wonderful clarity and oratorical eloquence, and synthesizing it into a dazzling whole, Consilience is science in the path-clearing traditions of Newton, Einstein, and Richard Feynman.</abstract>
            <isbn>0-679-76867-X</isbn>
            <url>http://wtf.tw/ref/wilson.pdf</url>
        </book>
    </entry>
    <entry id="Kleidon_2021">
        <article>
            <author>Axel Kleidon</author>
            <title>What limits photosynthesis? Identifying the thermodynamic constraints of the terrestrial biosphere within the Earth system</title>
            <journal>Biochimica et Biophysica Acta ({BBA}) - Bioenergetics</journal>
            <year>2021</year>
            <volume>1862</volume>
            <number>1</number>
            <pages>148303</pages>
            <month>jan</month>
            <abstract>Photosynthesis converts sunlight into the chemical free energy that feeds the Earth's biosphere, yet at levels much lower than what thermodynamics would allow for. I propose here that photosynthesis is nevertheless thermodynamically limited, but this limit acts indirectly on the material exchange. I substantiate this proposition for the photosynthetic activity of terrestrial ecosystems, which are notably more productive than the marine biosphere. The material exchange for terrestrial photosynthesis involves water and carbon dioxide, which I evaluate using global observation-based datasets of radiation, photosynthesis, precipitation and evaporation. I first calculate the conversion efficiency of photosynthesis in terrestrial ecosystems and its climatological variation, with a median efficiency of 0.77% (n = 13,274). The rates tightly correlate with evaporation on land (r2 = 0.87), which demonstrates the importance of the coupling of photosynthesis to material exchange. I then infer evaporation from the maximum material exchange between the surface and the atmosphere that is thermodynamically possible using datasets of solar radiation and precipitation. This inferred rate closely correlates with the observation-based land evaporation dataset (r2 = 0.84). When this rate is converted back into photosynthetic activity, the resulting patterns correlate highly with the observation-based dataset (r2 = 0.66). This supports the interpretation that it is not energy directly that limits terrestrial photosynthesis, but rather the material exchange that is driven by sunlight. This interpretation can explain the very low, observed conversion efficiency of photosynthesis in terrestrial ecosystems as well as its spatial variations. More generally, this implies that one needs to take the necessary material flows and exchanges associated with life into account to understand the thermodynamics of life. This, ultimately, requires a perspective that links the activity of the biosphere to the thermodynamic constraints of transport processes in the Earth system.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bbabio.2020.148303</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="Adami_2004">
        <article>
            <author>Christoph Adami</author>
            <title>Information theory in molecular biology</title>
            <journal>Physics of Life Reviews</journal>
            <year>2004</year>
            <volume>1</volume>
            <number>1</number>
            <pages>3--22</pages>
            <month>apr</month>
            <abstract>This article introduces the physics of information in the context of molecular biology and genomics. Entropy and information, the two central concepts of Shannon's theory of information and communication, are often confused with each other but play transparent roles when applied to statistical ensembles (i.e., identically prepared sets) of symbolic sequences. Such an approach can distinguish between entropy and information in genes, predict the secondary structure of ribozymes, and detect the covariation between residues in folded proteins. We also review applications to molecular sequence and structure analysis, and introduce new tools in the characterization of resistance mutations, and in drug design.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.plrev.2004.01.002</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="vernadskyProblemsII">
        <incollection>
            <author>Vernadsky, Vladimir</author>
            <title>Problems of biogeochemistry II</title>
            <booktitle>150 Years of Vernadsky: The Biosphere</booktitle>
            <publisher>CreateSpace</publisher>
            <year>2014</year>
            <editor>Rss, Jason and Freeman, Marsha</editor>
            <volume>1</volume>
            <pages>46--65</pages>
            <isbn>9781500605148</isbn>
        </incollection>
    </entry>
    <entry id="tesisAnarquista">
        <incollection>
            <author>Paul K. Feyerabend</author>
            <title>Tesis a favor del anarquismo</title>
            <booktitle>¿Por qué no Platón?</booktitle>
            <publisher>Tecnos</publisher>
            <year>2009</year>
            <pages>9-16</pages>
            <edition>3</edition>
            <isbn>9788430948499</isbn>
        </incollection>
    </entry>
    <entry id="Park_2023">
        <article>
            <author>Michael Park and Erin Leahey and Russell J. Funk</author>
            <title>Papers and patents are becoming less disruptive over time</title>
            <journal>Nature</journal>
            <year>2023</year>
            <volume>613</volume>
            <number>7942</number>
            <pages>138--144</pages>
            <month>jan</month>
            <abstract>Theories of scientific and technological change view discovery and invention as endogenous processes1,2, wherein previous accumulated knowledge enables future progress by allowing researchers to, in Newton’s words, ‘stand on the shoulders of giants’3,4,5,6,7. Recent decades have witnessed exponential growth in the volume of new scientific and technological knowledge, thereby creating conditions that should be ripe for major advances8,9. Yet contrary to this view, studies suggest that progress is slowing in several major fields10,11. Here, we analyse these claims at scale across six decades, using data on 45 million papers and 3.9 million patents from six large-scale datasets, together with a new quantitative metric—the CD index12—that characterizes how papers and patents change networks of citations in science and technology. We find that papers and patents are increasingly less likely to break with the past in ways that push science and technology in new directions. This pattern holds universally across fields and is robust across multiple different citation- and text-based metrics1,13,14,15,16,17. Subsequently, we link this decline in disruptiveness to a narrowing in the use of previous knowledge, allowing us to reconcile the patterns we observe with the ‘shoulders of giants’ view. We find that the observed declines are unlikely to be driven by changes in the quality of published science, citation practices or field-specific factors. Overall, our results suggest that slowing rates of disruption may reflect a fundamental shift in the nature of science and technology.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-022-05543-x</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="Jessop_2017">
        <article>
            <author>Bob Jessop</author>
            <title>On academic capitalism</title>
            <journal>Critical Policy Studies</journal>
            <year>2017</year>
            <volume>12</volume>
            <number>1</number>
            <pages>104--109</pages>
            <month>nov</month>
            <abstract>This forum contribution discusses the increasing trend toward academic capitalism and profit-oriented entrepreneurial practices in the fields of education and research. This occurs as universities, in different ways and subject to greater or lesser financial, administrative, and ideological pressures, act less like centers of disinterested education and research and more like economic enterprises that aim to maximize their revenues and/or advance the economic competitiveness of the spaces in which they operate. This development has become more global thanks to intensifying competition among relevant institutions (reflected, inter alia, in international accreditation for teaching and international rankings for research), intensified competition between the wider economic and political spaces in which they are embedded, and the ‘me-too-ism’ that leads social actors to jump on the latest bandwagon. I also consider the expansion of predatory academic capitalism and, because this is the least familiar type, I use my limited space to illustrate this rather than the more widely discussed examples of academic capitalism and entrepreneurialism (further examples of all case are presented in Jessop 2017).</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1080/19460171.2017.1403342</doi>
            <keywords>Academic capitalism; entrepreneurship; political capitalism; financiation; kowledge-based economy</keywords>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="Trainer_2019">
        <article>
            <author>Melissa G. Trainer and Michael H. Wong and Timothy H. McConnochie and Heather B. Franz and Sushil K. Atreya and Pamela G. Conrad and Franck Lefèvre and Paul R. Mahaffy and Charles A. Malespin and Heidi L.K. Manning and Javier Martín-Torres and Germán M. Martínez and Christopher P. McKay and Rafael Navarro-González and Álvaro Vicente-Retortillo and Christopher R. Webster and María-Paz Zorzano</author>
            <title>Seasonal Variations in Atmospheric Composition as Measured in Gale Crater, Mars</title>
            <journal>Journal of Geophysical Research: Planets</journal>
            <year>2019</year>
            <volume>124</volume>
            <number>11</number>
            <pages>3000--3024</pages>
            <month>nov</month>
            <abstract>The Sample Analysis at Mars (SAM) instrument onboard the Mars Science Laboratory Curiosity rover measures the chemical composition of major atmospheric species (CO2, N2, 40Ar, O2, and CO) through a dedicated atmospheric inlet. We report here measurements of volume mixing ratios in Gale Crater using the SAM quadrupole mass spectrometer, obtained over a period of nearly 5 years (3 Mars years) from landing. The observation period spans the northern summer of MY 31 and solar longitude (LS) of 175° through spring of MY 34, LS = 12°. This work expands upon prior reports of the mixing ratios measured by SAM QMS in the first 105 sols of the mission. The SAM QMS atmospheric measurements were taken periodically, with a cumulative coverage of four or five experiments per season on Mars. Major observations include the seasonal cycle of CO2, N2, and Ar, which lags approximately 20–40° of LS behind the pressure cycle driven by CO2 condensation and sublimation from the winter poles. This seasonal cycle indicates that transport occurs on faster timescales than mixing. The mixing ratio of O2 shows significant seasonal and interannual variability, suggesting an unknown atmospheric or surface process at work. The O2 measurements are compared to several parameters, including dust optical depth and trace CH4 measurements by Curiosity. We derive annual mean volume mixing ratios for the atmosphere in Gale Crater: CO2 = 0.951 (±0.003), N2 = 0.0259 (±0.0006), 40Ar = 0.0194 (±0.0004), O2 = 1.61 (±0.09) x 10-3, and CO = 5.8 (±0.8) x 10-4.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1029/2019JE006175</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="Johnson_2019">
        <article>
            <author>Natasha M. Johnson and Marta R. R. Oliveira</author>
            <title>Venus Atmospheric Composition In Situ Data: A Compilation</title>
            <journal>Earth and Space Science</journal>
            <year>2019</year>
            <volume>6</volume>
            <number>7</number>
            <pages>1299--1318</pages>
            <month>jul</month>
            <abstract>The Venus atmosphere is of significant interest yet only rudimentary solid data have been gathered about its composition and chemistry. These measurements are scattered through time and place and are limited by parameters such as resolution and error margins as well as reinterpretations. This paper presents an extensive compilation of published in situ data for the atmospheric composition of Venus. It also includes remotely gathered measurements and some extrapolated and modeled data for the lower atmosphere. The composition tables are divided in four categories: noble gases, reactive gases, noble, and nonnoble isotopes. These tables were first presented in 2016 within the scientific heritage appendix of the Deep Atmosphere Venus Investigation of Noble gases, Chemistry, and Imaging (DAVINCI) mission proposal. These tables provide respective measurements, error margins, techniques, altitudes, instruments, mission, and references. The objective of this paper is to provide a simple, comprehensive list of available measurements to date, in particular the in situ data, to serve as a quick overall Venus atmosphere data reference.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1029/2018EA000536</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="Leovy_2001">
        <article>
            <author>Conway Leovy</author>
            <title>Weather and climate on Mars</title>
            <journal>Nature</journal>
            <year>2001</year>
            <volume>412</volume>
            <number>6843</number>
            <pages>245--249</pages>
            <month>jul</month>
            <abstract>Imagine a planet very much like the Earth, with similar size, rotation rate and inclination of rotation axis, possessing an atmosphere and a solid surface, but lacking oceans and dense clouds of liquid water. We might expect such a desert planet to be dominated by large variations in day–night and winter–summer weather. Dust storms would be common. Observations and simulations of martian climate confirm these expectations and provide a wealth of detail that can help resolve problems of climate evolution.</abstract>
            <doi>10.1038/35084192</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="Khalil_1988">
        <article>
            <author>M. A. K. Khalil and R. A. Rasmussen</author>
            <title>Carbon monoxide in the Earth{\textquotesingle}s atmosphere: indications of a global increase</title>
            <journal>Nature</journal>
            <year>1988</year>
            <volume>332</volume>
            <number>6161</number>
            <pages>242--245</pages>
            <month>mar</month>
            <abstract>Over half of the carbon monoxide in the atmosphere comes from human activities including motor traffic, other combustion of fossil fuels, and slash and burn agriculture1–4. Additional anthropogenic sources include the burning of wood, savannah lands, and the oxidation of hydrocarbons including methane. Over the years these sources have increased gradually and may have already caused the concentrations of CO to double since pre-industrial times when human activities did not significantly affect the global cycles of CO and other trace gases. Increasing levels of CO can lead to an increase of tropospheric O3 (refs 5,6) and a build-up of many other trace gases in the Earth's atmosphere, which may in turn cause widespread perturbations of tropospheric chemistry, global warming, and other climatic changes7. In a recent report8 to senior US Government officials the National Academies stated the urgent need to know the global distribution and trends of CO. During the past 6–8 years we have taken systematic measurements of CO at sites ranging from within the Arctic Circle to the South Pole. The rates of increase of the globally averaged concentration are between 0.8% and 1.4% per year depending on the statistical method used for estimating the trends. These increases may have gone on for much longer because more than half of the atmospheric CO now comes from anthropogenic sources. We find that the rates of increase are largest at mid-northern and tropical latitudes, where most of the sources are located.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1038/332242a0</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="2014Atm">
        <article>
            <title>Observations: Atmosphere and Surface</title>
            <year>2014</year>
            <pages>159--254</pages>
            <month>mar</month>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1017/CBO9781107415324.008</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="ClimateChangeIPCC2014">
        <inbook>
            <pages>159–254</pages>
            <year>2014</year>
            <author>Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC)</author>
            <bibtexkey>ClimateChangeIPCC2014</bibtexkey>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
            <abstract>Executive Summary. The evidence of climate change from observations of the atmosphere and surface has grown significantly during recent years. At the same time new improved ways of characterizing and quantifying uncertainty have highlighted the challenges that remain for developing long-term global and regional climate quality data records. Currently, the observations of the atmosphere and surface indicate the following changes:. Atmospheric Composition. It is certain that atmospheric burdens of the well-mixed greenhouse gases (GHGs) targeted by the Kyoto Protocol increased from 2005 to 2011. The atmospheric abundance of carbon dioxide (CO2) was 390.5 ppm (390.3 to 390.7) in 2011; this is 40% greater than in 1750. Atmospheric nitrous oxide (N2O) was 324.2 ppb (324.0 to 324.4) in 2011 and has increased by 20% since 1750. Average annual increases in CO2 and N2O from 2005 to 2011 are comparable to those observed from 1996 to 2005. Atmospheric methane (CH4) was 1803.2 ppb (1801.2 to 1805.2) in 2011; this is 150% greater than before 1750. CH4 began increasing in 2007 after remaining nearly constant from 1999 to 2006. Hydrofluorocarbons (HFCs), perfluorocarbons (PFCs), and sulphur hexafluoride (SF6) all continue to increase relatively rapidly, but their contributions to radiative forcing are less than 1% of the total by well-mixed GHGs.</abstract>
            <place>Cambridge</place>
            <title>Observations: Atmosphere and Surface</title>
            <booktitle>Climate Change 2013 – The Physical Science Basis: Working Group I Contribution to the Fifth Assessment Report of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change</booktitle>
            <doi>10.1017/CBO9781107415324.008</doi>
        </inbook>
    </entry>
    <entry id="Cox1999-rk">
        <book>
            <editor>Cox, Arthur N</editor>
            <title>Allen's Astrophysical Quantities</title>
            <publisher>Springer</publisher>
            <year>1999</year>
            <address>New York, NY</address>
            <edition>4</edition>
            <month>#dec#</month>
            <language>en</language>
        </book>
    </entry>
    <entry id="bazerman2005measuring">
        <article>
            <author>Bazerman, Charles and De los Santos, René Agustín</author>
            <title>Measuring incommensurability: Are toxicology and ecotoxicology blind to what the other sees</title>
            <journal>Rhetoric and incommensurability</journal>
            <year>2005</year>
            <pages>424--463</pages>
            <abstract>Incommensurability of phenomena over periods of radical theory change is a key mechanism of Kuhn’s theory of paradigms in The Structure of Scientific Revolutions. In Kuhn’s account, those who inhabit one theory-based perspective are unable to recognize, understand, or accept entities revealed through observations made from an alternative theoretical perspective. The difference of ontologies stands as fundamental roadblock to communication. One can move from one perspective to the other only through a gestalt  switch, which makes the accounts of nature from the previous theory incoherent and lacking reference to the world.2 In the switch the old gestalt has evaporated. Later when he reformulated the cognitive divide as a matter of a communal switch of a taxonomic lexicon rather than an individual psychological switch of gestalt, incommensurability remained. The terms in the old taxonomy do not exist in the same world of relations of similitudes, contrasts, subordinations as the terms in the new. The new and old terms are incoherent in each other’s presence, and are only intelligible when each is viewed within its own taxonomic world. In his later formulations, Kuhn does think understanding across boundaries is possible, but only by a process akin to learning a new language. Translation is inevitably misleading (Kuhn 2000, pp. 33-57).</abstract>
            <url>https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Charles-Bazerman/publication/315086794_Measuring_Incommensurability_Are_toxicology_and_ecotoxicology_blind_to_what_the_other_sees/links/59f15efe0f7e9beabfca4f60/Measuring-Incommensurability-Are-toxicology-and-ecotoxicology-blind-to-what-the-other-sees.pdf</url>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="Vicente_Saez_2018">
        <article>
            <author>Ruben Vicente-Saez and Clara Martinez-Fuentes</author>
            <title>Open Science now: A systematic literature review for an integrated definition</title>
            <journal>Journal of Business Research</journal>
            <year>2018</year>
            <volume>88</volume>
            <pages>428--436</pages>
            <month>jul</month>
            <abstract>Open Science is a disruptive phenomenon that is emerging around the world and especially in Europe. Open Science brings about socio-cultural and technological change, based on openness and connectivity, on how research is designed, performed, captured, and assessed. Several studies show that there is a lack of awareness about what Open Science is, mainly due to the fact that there is no formal definition of Open Science. The purpose of this paper is to build a rigorous, integrated, and up-to-date definition of the Open Science phenomenon through a systematic literature review. The resulting definition “Open Science is transparent and accessible knowledge that is shared and developed through collaborative networks” helps the scientific community, the business world, political actors, and citizens to have a common and clear understanding about what Open Science is, and stimulates an open debate about the social, economic, and human added value of this phenomenon.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jbusres.2017.12.043</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="Fraile">
        <inbook>
            <chapter>La filosofñia en Mileto</chapter>
            <pages>143-149</pages>
            <year>1997</year>
            <author>Guillermo Fraile</author>
            <isbn>84-7914-291-X</isbn>
            <bibtexkey>Fraile</bibtexkey>
            <publisher>Biblioteca de autores cristianos</publisher>
            <edition>7</edition>
            <language>es</language>
            <title>Historia de la Filosofía: I. Grecia Y Roma</title>
            <url>https://filosofia260.files.wordpress.com/2016/05/historia-de-la-filosofia-fraile.pdf</url>
        </inbook>
    </entry>
    <entry id="Huang_2021">
        <article>
            <author>Daofen Huang and Yibo Xu and Fadan Lei and Xiaoqin Yu and Zhuozhi Ouyang and Yanhua Chen and Hanzhong Jia and Xuetao Guo</author>
            <title>Degradation of polyethylene plastic in soil and effects on microbial community composition</title>
            <journal>Journal of Hazardous Materials</journal>
            <year>2021</year>
            <volume>416</volume>
            <pages>126173</pages>
            <month>aug</month>
            <abstract>Plastics pollution in global soil systems is becoming a severely global issue and potential threat to terrestrial ecosystem serves and human health. Herein, in order to determine the degradability and ecological effects of polyethylene (PE) films, we measured the weight loss and characterization of PE films and analyzed variation in microbial community. The results of weight loss, SEM and FTIR spectra exhibited that PE films had unique degradation performance under different conditions. Simultaneously, we investigated the effects of PE films on the microbial community, and the microbiota colonizing on plastics. PE films may change the soil microbial community composition in soil, and hold the post of unique matrix for microbial colonization. These results indicate that the degradation of PE films and microbial community composition in soil can be affected by different conditions (soil layer, time and plants). By assessing the alteration of microbial community composition and PE films in soil, this work will contribute to enhance our understanding on the potential risks of plastics on soil ecosystems and provide a scientific basis for understanding the ecological effect of plastics on soil functions.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jhazmat.2021.126173</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="Vinnichenko_2020">
        <article>
            <author>Galina Vinnichenko and Amber J. M. Jarrett and Janet M. Hope and Jochen J. Brocks</author>
            <title>Discovery of the oldest known biomarkers provides evidence for phototrophic bacteria in the 1.73~Ga Wollogorang Formation, Australia</title>
            <journal>Geobiology</journal>
            <year>2020</year>
            <volume>18</volume>
            <number>5</number>
            <pages>544--559</pages>
            <month>mar</month>
            <abstract>The discovery of mid-Proterozoic (1.8–0.8 billion years ago, Ga) indigenous biomarkers is a challenge, since biologically informative molecules of such antiquity are commonly destroyed by metamorphism or overprinted by drilling fluids and other anthropogenic petroleum products. Previously, the oldest clearly indigenous biomarkers were reported from the 1.64 Ga Barney Creek Formation in the northern Australian McArthur Basin. In this study, we present the discovery of biomarker molecules from carbonaceous shales of the 1.73 Ga Wollogorang Formation in the southern McArthur Basin, extending the biomarker record back in time by ~90 million years. The extracted hydrocarbons illustrate typical mid-Proterozoic signatures with a large unresolved complex mixture, high methyl alkane/n-alkane ratios and the absence of eukaryotic steranes. Acyclic isoprenoids, saturated carotenoid derivatives, bacterial hopanes and aromatic hopanoids and steroids also were below detection limits. However, continuous homologous series of low molecular weight C14–C19 2,3,4- and 2,3,6-trimethyl aryl isoprenoids (AI) were identified, and C20–C22 AI homologues were tentatively identified. Based on elevated abundances relative to abiogenic isomers, we interpret the 2,3,6-AI isomer series as biogenic molecules and the 2,3,4-AI series as possibly biogenic. The biological sources for the 2,3,6-AI series include carotenoids of cyanobacteria and/or green sulphur bacteria (Chlorobiaceae). The lower concentrated 2,3,4-AI series may be derived from purple sulphur bacteria (Chromatiaceae). These degradation products of carotenoids are the oldest known clearly indigenous molecules of likely biogenic origin.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1111/gbi.12390</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="Ciani_2005">
        <article>
            <author>A. Ciani and K.-U. Goss and R. P. Schwarzenbach</author>
            <title>Light penetration in soil and particulate minerals</title>
            <journal>European Journal of Soil Science</journal>
            <year>2005</year>
            <volume>56</volume>
            <number>5</number>
            <pages>561--574</pages>
            <month>oct</month>
            <abstract>Knowledge of light penetration in soils is of particular interest for photolytic degradation of pesticides, for laser-induced fluorescence spectroscopy and remote sensing, and for understanding better the germination of seeds. To date little information has been available in the literature on this topic. In this paper light penetration in soils is determined successfully using diffuse reflectance and transmittance spectroscopy and the relatively simple Kubelka–Munk model. Using the latter model of light propagation in turbid media, the optical properties of kaolinite, montmorillonite, barium sulphate, goethite and 19 different soils were determined in the wavelength range 275–700 nm. In particular, the light absorption coefficient, k, and light scattering coefficient, s, were determined. The depth at which the light intensity at the surface is reduced by 99% (light penetration depth) and the depth of the sample contributing to the measured reflected radiation (information depth) could also be calculated from k and s. For kaolinite, the light penetration depth ranged between 10 and 200 µm for wavelengths between 275 and 700 nm, respectively; the information depth was between 5 and 80 µm. For soils, the penetration depth was in the range 17–110 µm at 275 nm and 120–300 µm at 700 nm, and the information depth was in the range 8–60 µm at 275 nm and 60–175 µm at 700 nm. Hence, the information depth is about half the penetration depth for media with reflectance smaller than 0.7 (e.g. soils). For dry soils, an empirical relationship was established between the light absorption coefficient and the amount of particle-size fractions. The effect of water content was also investigated: addition of water to kaolinite reduced its scattering coefficients, whereas the absorption coefficient was hardly affected. For the soils, addition of water had a more complex mode of action affecting both absorption and scattering coefficients. With the measured optical properties of dry minerals and soils it is possible to calculate light intensity profiles with depth and to quantify photochemical processes occurring in these media.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2389.2005.00688.x</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="Duchaufour1984Cap1">
        <inbook>
            <editor>Masson S.A</editor>
            <chapter>1</chapter>
            <address>Barcelona</address>
            <year>1984</year>
            <author>Duchaufour, Philippe and Souchier, Bernard</author>
            <isbn>8431103442</isbn>
            <bibtexkey>Duchaufour1984Cap1</bibtexkey>
            <publisher>Masson</publisher>
            <title>Evolución de la fracción mineral, alteración y génesis de las arcillas</title>
            <booktitle>Edafología: 1. Edafogenesis y clasificación/por Philippe Duchaufour y Bernard Souchier.</booktitle>
        </inbook>
    </entry>
    <entry id="Duchaufour1984Cap3">
        <inbook>
            <editor>Masson S.A</editor>
            <chapter>3</chapter>
            <address>Barcelona</address>
            <year>1984</year>
            <author>Duchaufour, Philippe and Souchier, Bernard</author>
            <isbn>8431103442</isbn>
            <bibtexkey>Duchaufour1984Cap3</bibtexkey>
            <publisher>Masson</publisher>
            <title>Transporte de materia en el suelo</title>
            <booktitle>Edafología: 1. Edafogenesis y clasificación/por Philippe Duchaufour y Bernard Souchier</booktitle>
        </inbook>
    </entry>
    <entry id="jennyArt">
        <article>
            <author>Hans Jenny</author>
            <title>The image of soil in the landscape art, old and new</title>
            <journal>Organic matter and soil fertility</journal>
            <year>1968</year>
            <url>https://www.secs.com.es/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/The-Image-of-soil-in-landscape-art-old-and-new.pdf</url>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="rozanov1982methodological">
        <article>
            <author>Rozanov, Boris G</author>
            <title>Methodological bases of modern soviet soil science and its future development</title>
            <journal>Cah. ORSTOM, sér. Pédol</journal>
            <year>1982</year>
            <volume>19</volume>
            <number>1</number>
            <pages>79--90</pages>
            <abstract>Methodological bases of modern Soviet soil science have been treated in the present article in light of its historical
developmenl from DOKUTCHAEV’S times till present. Two main stages or trends were distinguished within this century
of science development: the stage of soil inventary and the stage of soil management. Basic methodological concepts
are being considered, starting from the soil definition in its present form, through the concept of soil evolution; the
concepf of soil as a component of ecosystems of the Biosphere; the concept of elementary soil processes and current
regimes of soil formation; the principles of mathematical modelling of soil processes. An attempt was made fo correlate
fhe development of soil science with changing historical tasks of socioeconomic developmenf of fhe country.</abstract>
            <url>https://horizon.documentation.ird.fr/exl-doc/pleins_textes/cahiers/PTP/1436.PDF</url>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="West_2009">
        <article>
            <author>Jordan M. West and Susan H. Julius and Peter Kareiva and Carolyn Enquist and Joshua J. Lawler and Brian Petersen and Ayana E. Johnson and M. Rebecca Shaw</author>
            <title>U.S. Natural Resources and Climate Change: Concepts and Approaches for Management Adaptation</title>
            <journal>Environmental Management</journal>
            <year>2009</year>
            <volume>44</volume>
            <number>6</number>
            <pages>1001--1021</pages>
            <month>jul</month>
            <abstract>Public lands and waters in the United States traditionally have been managed using frameworks and objectives that were established under an implicit assumption of stable climatic conditions. However, projected climatic changes render this assumption invalid. Here, we summarize general principles for management adaptations that have emerged from a major literature review. These general principles cover many topics including: (1) how to assess climate impacts to ecosystem processes that are key to management goals; (2) using management practices to support ecosystem resilience; (3) converting barriers that may inhibit management responses into opportunities for successful implementation; and (4) promoting flexible decision making that takes into account challenges of scale and thresholds. To date, the literature on management adaptations to climate change has mostly focused on strategies for bolstering the resilience of ecosystems to persist in their current states. Yet in the longer term, it is anticipated that climate change will push certain ecosystems and species beyond their capacity to recover. When managing to support resilience becomes infeasible, adaptation may require more than simply changing management practices—it may require changing management goals and managing transitions to new ecosystem states. After transitions have occurred, management will again support resilience—this time for a new ecosystem state. Thus, successful management of natural resources in the context of climate change will require recognition on the part of managers and decisions makers of the need to cycle between “managing for resilience” and “managing for change.”</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1007/s00267-009-9345-1</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="Dungan_1959">
        <article>
            <author>G.H. Dungan and A.L. Lang and J.W. Pendleton</author>
            <title>Corn Plant Population In Relation To Soil Productivity</title>
            <year>1959</year>
            <pages>435--473</pages>
            <abstract>The corn plant is less capable of adjustment to a poor stand than other members of the grass family. Therefore, it is important that a proper planting rate be chosen. When a corn plant is grown in association with other plants, the available food constituents must be shared and growth processes are correspondingly impaired. With adequate moisture and plant food, and with no competition with other plants, the growth of every organ is enhanced. The amount of plant food available to a plant may be increased in one or both of two ways—the population may be reduced and the fertilizing materials, including water may be applied to the soil.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1016/S0065-2113(08)60072-3</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="rauta1988soil">
        <article>
            <author>Rauta, C and Carstea, S and Davidovici, I</author>
            <title>Soil-Cybernetic System</title>
            <journal>Analele Institutului de Cercetari pentru Pedologie si Agrochimie (Romania)</journal>
            <year>1988</year>
            <abstract>The authors emphasize the cybernetic character of soil system and advocate the systemic approach of soil as the only rational way to provide short and longterm planned yields as well as the reproduction at an enlarged scale of soil fertility and the improvement of the environmental quality. Under this conception, the approach of the system has to be focused not towards the improvement of only some discrete soil characteristics but to the complex treatment of specific area units, considering all the features of the socio-economic ecosystem that are involved in. This way also enables to prevent more easily the soil pollution and to better understand the soil function as any means of production that requires maintenance and slight and even heavy repairs.</abstract>
            <url>https://agris.fao.org/agris-search/search.do?recordID=RO8800796</url>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="gil2018objetivos">
        <article>
            <author>Gómez-Gil, Carlos</author>
            <title>Objetivos de Desarrollo Sostenible (ODS): una revisión crítica</title>
            <journal>Papeles de relaciones ecosociales y cambio global</journal>
            <year>2018</year>
            <volume>140</volume>
            <number>1</number>
            <pages>107--118</pages>
            <abstract>Los Objetivos de Desarrollo Sostenible (ODS) adoptados por las Naciones Unidas en 2015 contienen la agenda global más ambiciosa aprobada por la comunidad internacional para movilizar la acción colectiva en torno a objetivos comunes. Si bien se proponen luchar contra la pobreza extrema, integran y equilibran tres dimensiones esenciales del desarrollo sostenible como son la económica, la social y la ambiental, proporcionando una valiosa hoja de ruta para articular la formulación de políticas mundiales. Sin embargo, la arquitectura compleja bajo la que se han diseñado, sus limitaciones técnicas y las fundadas críticas de la comunidad internacional proyectan importantes limitaciones para que esta novedosa agenda pueda alcanzar los objetivos previstos de construir un planeta mejor para las generaciones venideras.</abstract>
            <url>https://www.fuhem.es/media/cdv/file/biblioteca/revista_papeles/140/ODS-revision-critica-C.Gomez.pdf</url>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="sampedroVideo">
        <article>
            <author>Sampedro,José Luis</author>
            <title>José Luis Sampedro en TVE</title>
            <journal>attactv</journal>
            <year>2011</year>
            <abstract>"Este sistema se acaba, el sistema de vida occidental se acaba... el capitalismo se ha reformado ya muchas veces". Fragmento de entrevista realizada por TVE.</abstract>
            <url>https://youtu.be/736TFZAevnc?t=346</url>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="ortega1969barbarie">
        <inbook>
            <editor>Diario EL PAÍS</editor>
            <chapter>12</chapter>
            <address>Madrid</address>
            <year>2002</year>
            <author>Ortega y Gasset, José</author>
            <isbn>84-89669-31-7</isbn>
            <bibtexkey>ortega1969barbarie</bibtexkey>
            <publisher>Diario EL PAÍS S.L</publisher>
            <title>La barbarie del “especialismo”</title>
            <booktitle>La rebelión de las masas</booktitle>
        </inbook>
    </entry>
    <entry id="fisher2016realismo">
        <book>
            <author>Fisher, Mark</author>
            <title>«Realismo capitalista» ¿No hay alternativa?</title>
            <publisher>Caja negra</publisher>
            <year>2016</year>
            <address>Buenos Aires</address>
            <abstract>En su libro Realismo capitalista. ¿No hay alternativa?, Mark Fisher se enfoca en la famosa frase de Margaret Thatcher («There is no alternative») e indaga las nuevas subjetividades del capitalismo tardío. A continuación, reproducimos el capítulo «Impotencia reflexiva, ‘inmovilización’ y comunismo liberal», escrito a partir de su experiencia como educador en el Reino Unido.</abstract>
            <isbn> 978-987-1622-45-0</isbn>
            <url>https://monoskop.org/images/4/47/Fisher_Mark_Realismo_Capitalista_No_hay_alternativa_2016.pdf</url>
        </book>
    </entry>
    <entry id="abad2020sustainable">
        <article>
            <author>Abad-Segura, Emilio and González-Zamar, Mariana-Daniela and Infante-Moro, Juan C and Ruipérez García, Germán</author>
            <title>Sustainable management of digital transformation in higher education: Global research trends</title>
            <journal>Sustainability</journal>
            <year>2020</year>
            <volume>12</volume>
            <number>5</number>
            <pages>2107</pages>
            <abstract>Digital transformation in the education sector has implied the involvement of sustainable management, in order to adapt to the changes imposed by new technologies. Trends in global research on this topic have been analyzed and studied, during the 1986–2019 period. To achieve this purpose, a bibliometric study of 1590 articles from the Scopus database has been applied.
The results provided data on the scientific productivity of authors, journals, institutions, and countries that contribute to the development of this research area. The evidence reveals an exponential trend, with special interest in the last five years. The main categories are Social Sciences and Environmental Science. The most productive journal is Sustainability. The author with more articles is Mulder, from The Hague University of Applied Sciences. The most productive institution is Delft University of Technology. The USA is the country with the most academic publications and international collaborations in its studies. The main keywords used in the articles
are “sustainability”, “sustainable development”, “higher education”, “innovation”, “technology”, “environmental technology”, “technological development”, and “environmental management”. Global research has followed a growing trend, with optimal publication levels in recent years.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.3390/su12052107</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="latour2007crisis">
        <book>
            <author>Latour, Bruno</author>
            <editor>Victor Goldstein</editor>
            <title>Nunca fuimos modernos</title>
            <publisher>Siglo Veintiuno</publisher>
            <year>2007</year>
            <address>Avellaneda, Argentina</address>
            <isbn>978-987-1220-85-4</isbn>
            <url>https://monoskop.org/images/f/fb/Latour_Bruno_Nunca_fuimos_modernos_Ensayo_de_antropologia_simetrica.pdf</url>
        </book>
    </entry>
    <entry id="pierri2005historia">
        <article>
            <author>Pierri, Naína</author>
            <title>Historia del concepto de desarrollo sustentable</title>
            <journal>Sustentabilidad</journal>
            <year>2005</year>
            <pages>27--81</pages>
            <abstract>EL PRIMER objetivo de este capítulo es reconstruir el camino intelectual y político recorrido hasta la propuesta de desarrollo sustentable. Nos motiva la percepción de que muchas presentaciones de estos antecedentes suelen simplificarlo como una evolución más o menos lineal, que no explica cómo es que, partiendo de posiciones muy diferentes sobre la cuestión ambiental a principios de los setenta, todos confluyen, años después, en la idea de desarrollo sustentable. Buscamos explicar ese proceso a partir de identificar el escenario inicial de la discusión ambiental, y cómo se conforman en él formas de interpretación diferentes que constituyen, de ahí en delante, las principales corrientes de pensamiento del ambientalismo contemporáneo.1 Luego, le damos seguimiento a la discusión, contextualizada en la situación socioambiental mundial, y vamos viendo cómo evolucionan las posiciones en el proceso político que las enfrenta, intentando captar la dinámica que altera la correlación de fuerzas entre ellas y agrega o resta elementos, o cambia el énfasis de
sus argumentos. Es explicada la confluencia en la propuesta de desarrollo sustentable no como una disolución de las diferencias, sino como un momento de homogenización de una de las corrientes (la del ambientalismo moderado) que, en el mismo momento que sus ideas resultan un acuerdo general, da margen a la persistencia de las mismas. Luego, y como corolario de lo anterior, presentamos estas diferencias, mostrando que las distintas interpretaciones so-
bre el desarrollo sustentable son la forma en que aparecen esas grandes concepciones en el debate actual.</abstract>
            <url>http://soda.ustadistancia.edu.co/enlinea/eduvirtual/Seminario_ecoturismo/documentos/Unidad%201%20-Sustentabilidad/Desarrollo%20Sustentable_capitulo_2.pdf</url>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="sokal1996transgressing">
        <article>
            <author>Sokal, Alan D</author>
            <title>Transgressing the boundaries: Toward a transformative hermeneutics of quantum gravity</title>
            <journal>Social text</journal>
            <year>1996</year>
            <pages>217--252</pages>
            <url>https://www.webpages.uidaho.edu/~brian/sokal_transgress_1996.pdf</url>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="Finocchiaro_2021">
        <incollection>
            <author>Maurice A. Finocchiaro</author>
            <title>Feyerabend's Against Method: Rationalism vs. Pseudo-irrationalism</title>
            <booktitle>Science, Method, and Argument in Galileo</booktitle>
            <publisher>Springer International Publishing</publisher>
            <year>2021</year>
            <pages>389--405</pages>
            <abstract>This is a critical examination of Paul Feyerabend’s Against Method (originally published in 1975). I argue that, although Feyerabend’s book may superficially appear as primarily destructive, he is really practicing a relatively novel and essentially sound approach to the analysis of scientific rationality; Feyerabend’s approach is a concrete, empirical, historical, and rhetorical one, and his account of Galileo’s methodology is meant to be a case study. I also argue that Feyerabend’s account of Galileo’s methodology is not really irrationalistic, but pseudo-irrationalistic; in reality, Galileo proceeds rationally for Feyerabend, as long as the concept of scientific rationality is expanded to allow for rhetorical factors that are a-logical rather than anti-logical, and for epistemological practices neglected by orthodox scholars but ultimately reducible to reasoning and argumentation. Finally, I elaborate, along such lines, a critical appreciation of Feyerabend’s discussion of Galileo’s critique of the vertical-fall argument against the earth’s motion.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-030-77147-8_20</doi>
        </incollection>
    </entry>
    <entry id="Hotez_2020">
        <article>
            <author>Peter J. Hotez</author>
            <title>Anti-science extremism in America: escalating and globalizing</title>
            <journal>Microbes and Infection</journal>
            <year>2020</year>
            <volume>22</volume>
            <number>10</number>
            <pages>505--507</pages>
            <month>nov</month>
            <abstract>The last five years has seen a sharp rise in anti-science rhetoric in the United States, especially from the political far right, mostly focused on vaccines and, of late, anti-COVID-19 prevention approaches. Vaccine coverage has declined in more than 100 US counties leading to measles outbreaks in 2019, while in 2020 the US became the epicenter of the COVID-19 pandemic. Now the anti-science movement in America has begun to globalize, with new and unexpected associations with extremist groups and the potential for tragic consequences in terms of global public health. A new anti-science triumvirate has emerged, comprised of far right groups in the US and Germany, and amplified by Russian media.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.micinf.2020.09.005</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="Donthu_2021">
        <article>
            <author>Naveen Donthu and Satish Kumar and Debmalya Mukherjee and Nitesh Pandey and Weng Marc Lim</author>
            <title>How to conduct a bibliometric analysis: An overview and guidelines</title>
            <journal>Journal of Business Research</journal>
            <year>2021</year>
            <volume>133</volume>
            <pages>285--296</pages>
            <month>sep</month>
            <abstract>Bibliometric analysis is a popular and rigorous method for exploring and analyzing large volumes of scientific data. It enables us to unpack the evolutionary nuances of a specific field, while shedding light on the emerging areas in that field. Yet, its application in business research is relatively new, and in many instances, underdeveloped. Accordingly, we endeavor to present an overview of the bibliometric methodology, with a particular focus on its different techniques, while offering step-by-step guidelines that can be relied upon to rigorously perform bibliometric analysis with confidence. To this end, we also shed light on when and how bibliometric analysis should be used vis-à-vis other similar techniques such as meta-analysis and systematic literature reviews. As a whole, this paper should be a useful resource for gaining insights on the available techniques and procedures for carrying out studies using bibliometric analysis.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jbusres.2021.04.070</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="pascon1997developing">
        <inproceedings>
            <author>Pascon, Jean-Louis</author>
            <title>Developing a national strategy for multimedia cultural heritage</title>
            <booktitle>Museums and the Web</booktitle>
            <year>1997</year>
            <volume>97</volume>
            <pages>57--66</pages>
        </inproceedings>
    </entry>
    <entry id="Jenny_1961">
        <article>
            <author>Hans Jenny</author>
            <title>Derivation of State Factor Equations of Soils and Ecosystems</title>
            <journal>Soil Science Society of America Journal</journal>
            <year>1961</year>
            <volume>25</volume>
            <number>5</number>
            <pages>385--388</pages>
            <month>sep</month>
            <abstract>The ecosystem is a piece of landscape having artificial boundaries. Changes in ecosystem properties are viewed as gains minus losses or influxes minus outfluxes of matter and energy. The fluxes are expressed as products of gradients and permeation. The outside potentials of the flux gradients are identified with the environmental soil-forming factors, particularly climate and biotic factor. Pedogenic functions as now rewritten offer psychological and typographical advantages.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.2136/sssaj1961.03615995002500050023x</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="Lovelock_1989">
        <article>
            <author>James E. Lovelock</author>
            <title>Geophysiology, the science of Gaia</title>
            <journal>Reviews of Geophysics</journal>
            <year>1989</year>
            <volume>27</volume>
            <number>2</number>
            <pages>215</pages>
            <abstract>The Gaia hypothesis postulates that the climate and chemical composition of the Earth's surface environment is, and has been, regulated at a state tolerable for the biota. This notion was introduced in 1972 and 1973 (Lovelock, 1972; Margulis and Lovelock, 1974; Lovelock and Margulis, 1973). The wording of these early papers was sometimes poetic, rather than scientific, but Gaia has matured and might be better stated as a theory that views the evolution of the biota and of their material environment as a single, tightly coupled process, with the self-regulation of climate and chemistry as an emergent property. It is a theory that makes “risky” predictions, for example, that oxygen is and has been regulated during the existence of land plants, within ±5% of its present level; it is therefore falsifiable. Numerical models are used to illustrate the potential for stable self-regulation of tightly coupled systems of organisms and their environments.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1029/RG027i002p00215</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="Batty_2014">
        <article>
            <author>Michael Batty and Robin Morphet and Paolo Masucci and Kiril Stanilov</author>
            <title>Entropy, complexity, and spatial information</title>
            <journal>Journal of Geographical Systems</journal>
            <year>2014</year>
            <volume>16</volume>
            <number>4</number>
            <pages>363--385</pages>
            <month>sep</month>
            <abstract>We pose the central problem of defining a measure of complexity, specifically for spatial systems in general, city systems in particular. The measures we adopt are based on Shannon’s (in Bell Syst Tech J 27:379–423, 623–656, 1948) definition of information. We introduce this measure and argue that increasing information is equivalent to increasing complexity, and we show that for spatial distributions, this involves a trade-off between the density of the distribution and the number of events that characterize it; as cities get bigger and are characterized by more events—more places or locations, information increases, all other things being equal. But sometimes the distribution changes at a faster rate than the number of events and thus information can decrease even if a city grows. We develop these ideas using various information measures. We first demonstrate their applicability to various distributions of population in London over the last 100 years, then to a wider region of London which is divided into bands of zones at increasing distances from the core, and finally to the evolution of the street system that characterizes the built-up area of London from 1786 to the present day. We conclude by arguing that we need to relate these measures to other measures of complexity, to choose a wider array of examples, and to extend the analysis to two-dimensional spatial systems.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1007/s10109-014-0202-2</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="Castillo_2011">
        <article>
            <author>Luis Felipe del Castillo and Paula Vera-Cruz</author>
            <title>Thermodynamic Formulation of Living Systems and Their Evolution</title>
            <journal>Journal of Modern Physics</journal>
            <year>2011</year>
            <volume>02</volume>
            <number>5</number>
            <pages>379--391</pages>
            <abstract>The purpose of this review article is to present some of the recent contributions that show the use of thermo-
dynamics to describe biological systems and their evolution, illustrating the agreement that this theory pre-
sents with the field of evolution. Organic systems are described as thermodynamic systems where entropy is 
produced by the irreversible processes, considering as an established fact that this entropy is eliminated 
through their frontiers to preserve life. The necessary and sufficient conditions to describe the evolution of 
life in the negentropy principle are established. Underlining the fact that the necessary condition requires 
formulation, which is founded on the principle of minimum entropy production for open systems operating 
near or far from equilibrium, other formulations are mentioned, particularly the information theory, the en-
ergy intensiveness hypothesis and the theory of open systems far from equilibrium. Finally suggesting the 
possibility of considering the lineal formulation as a viable alternative; that is, given the internal constric-
tions under which a biological system operates, it is possible that the validity of its application is broader 
than it has been suggested.</abstract>
            <doi>doi:10.4236/jmp.2011.25047</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="Shannon_1948">
        <article>
            <author>C. E. Shannon</author>
            <title>A Mathematical Theory of Communication</title>
            <journal>Bell System Technical Journal</journal>
            <year>1948</year>
            <volume>27</volume>
            <number>3</number>
            <pages>379--423</pages>
            <month>jul</month>
            <abstract>The recent development of various methods of modulation such as PCM and PPM which exchange bandwidth for signal-to-noise ratio has intensified the interest in a general theory of communication. A basis for such a theory is contained in the important papers of Nyquist 1 and Hartley 2 on this subject. In the present paper we will extend the theory to include a number of new factors, in particular the effect of noise in the channel, and the savings possible due to the statistical structure of the original message and due to the nature of the final destination of the information.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1002/j.1538-7305.1948.tb01338.x</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="Ghosh_2009">
        <article>
            <author>Wriddhiman Ghosh and Bomba Dam</author>
            <title>Biochemistry and molecular biology of lithotrophic sulfur oxidation by taxonomically and ecologically diverse bacteria and archaea</title>
            <journal>{FEMS} Microbiology Reviews</journal>
            <year>2009</year>
            <volume>33</volume>
            <number>6</number>
            <pages>999--1043</pages>
            <month>nov</month>
            <abstract>Lithotrophic sulfur oxidation is an ancient metabolic process. Ecologically and taxonomically diverged prokaryotes have differential abilities to utilize different reduced sulfur compounds as lithotrophic substrates. Different phototrophic or chemotrophic species use different enzymes, pathways and mechanisms of electron transport and energy conservation for the oxidation of any given substrate. While the mechanisms of sulfur oxidation in obligately chemolithotrophic bacteria, predominantly belonging to Beta- (e.g. Thiobacillus) and Gammaproteobacteria (e.g. Thiomicrospira), are not well established, the Sox system is the central pathway in the facultative bacteria from Alphaproteobacteria (e.g. Paracoccus). Interestingly, photolithotrophs such as Rhodovulum belonging to Alphaproteobacteria also use the Sox system, whereas those from Chromatiaceae and Chlorobi use a truncated Sox complex alongside reverse-acting sulfate-reducing systems. Certain chemotrophic magnetotactic Alphaproteobacteria allegedly utilize such a combined mechanism. Sulfur-chemolithotrophic metabolism in Archaea, largely restricted to Sulfolobales, is distinct from those in Bacteria. Phylogenetic and biomolecular fossil data suggest that the ubiquity of sox genes could be due to horizontal transfer, and coupled sulfate reduction/sulfide oxidation pathways, originating in planktonic ancestors of Chromatiaceae or Chlorobi, could be ancestral to all sulfur-lithotrophic processes. However, the possibility that chemolithotrophy, originating in deep sea, is the actual ancestral form of sulfur oxidation cannot be ruled out.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1574-6976.2009.00187.x</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="Mayorga_2012">
        <article>
            <author>Luis S. Mayorga and María José López and Wayne M. Becker</author>
            <title>Molecular Thermodynamics for Cell Biology as Taught with Boxes</title>
            <journal>{CBE}{\textemdash}Life Sciences Education</journal>
            <year>2012</year>
            <volume>11</volume>
            <number>1</number>
            <pages>31--38</pages>
            <month>mar</month>
            <abstract>Thermodynamic principles are basic to an understanding of the complex fluxes of energy and information required to keep cells alive. These microscopic machines are nonequilibrium systems at the micron scale that are maintained in pseudo-steady-state conditions by very sophisticated processes. Therefore, several nonstandard concepts need to be taught to rationalize why these very ordered systems proliferate actively all over our planet in seeming contradiction to the second law of thermodynamics. We propose a model consisting of boxes with different shapes that contain small balls that are in constant motion due to a stream of air blowing from below. This is a simple macroscopic system that can be easily visualized by students and that can be understood as mimicking the behavior of a set of molecules exchanging energy. With such boxes, the basic concepts of entropy, enthalpy, and free energy can be taught while reinforcing a molecular understanding of the concepts and stressing the stochastic nature of the thermodynamic laws. In addition, time-related concepts, such as reaction rates and activation energy, can be readily visualized. Moreover, the boxes provide an intuitive way to introduce the role in cellular organization of “information” and Maxwell's demons operating under nonequilibrium conditions.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1187/cbe.11-07-0053</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="Kerr_2011">
        <article>
            <author>Richard A. Kerr</author>
            <title>Peak Oil Production May Already Be Here</title>
            <journal>Science</journal>
            <year>2011</year>
            <volume>331</volume>
            <number>6024</number>
            <pages>1510--1511</pages>
            <month>mar</month>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1126/science.331.6024.1510</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="Deming_2023">
        <article>
            <author>David Deming</author>
            <title>M. King Hubbert and the rise and fall of peak oil theory</title>
            <journal>{AAPG} Bulletin</journal>
            <year>2023</year>
            <volume>107</volume>
            <number>6</number>
            <pages>851--861</pages>
            <month>jun</month>
            <abstract>In 1956, American geologist M. King Hubbert predicted that United States oil production would follow a bell-shaped curve and peak between 1965 and 1970. When petroleum production peaked in 1970 and subsequently declined for 38 yr, Hubbert’s model was corroborated, and he was heralded as a prophet and an oracle. However, Hubbert’s peak oil theory was effectively falsified when United States oil production began to increase in 2009 and surpassed the 1970 peak in 2018. A close reading of Hubbert’s analysis reveals that the model was flawed from the beginning, because Hubbert had conceded that the life cycle of a resource would not necessarily follow a single curve. Thus, any prediction of a production history made from a single curve had little to no predictive validity. Whereas Hubbert was celebrated for decades, the Cornucopian critics, who were correct in their assessments of resource abundance, were relegated to obscurity. Hubbert was a brilliant scientist who made significant contributions in several areas, but his views on resource exhaustion were influenced by his ideological beliefs. A false belief in the future scarcity of oil driven by peak oil theory resulted in the misallocation of resources. Bad science produces bad public policy.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1306/03202322131</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="Thelin_2019">
        <article>
            <author>John R. Thelin</author>
            <title>An Embarrassment of Riches: Admission and Ambition in American Higher Education</title>
            <journal>Society</journal>
            <year>2019</year>
            <volume>56</volume>
            <number>4</number>
            <pages>329--334</pages>
            <month>jul</month>
            <abstract>Allegations of bribery and corruption in admission to prestigious American colleges brought academics and athletics into the
public forum in March 2019. This paper distinguishes illegalities from inequities in the decisions that elite college admissions
offices make about student applications. Typically special admission allowances tend to favor outstanding athletes whose
academic record may be marginal. The incidents in Varsity Blues indicated a different imbalance: namely, that athletic admission
slots, especially in so-called “country club” sports tended to give an admissions edge to applicants who did not show great athletic
achievement or potential. These episodes put into bold relief new examples of advantage and privilege in going to college as part
of American society.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1007/s12115-019-00376-3</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="TOLA_2016">
        <article>
            <author>MIRIAM TOLA</author>
            <title>Composing with Gaia: Isabelle Stengers and the Feminist Politics of the Earth</title>
            <journal>{PhaenEx}</journal>
            <year>2016</year>
            <volume>11</volume>
            <number>1</number>
            <pages>1--21</pages>
            <month>jun</month>
            <abstract>This essay brings the work of Isabelle Stengers into the fold of feminism to propose a feminist politics of the earth that disrupts the fantasy of human exceptionalism underpinning much Anthropocene discourse. I begin by situating Stengers’s political use of Gaia theory in current debates on the Anthropocene. Next, I show how Stengers’s reworking of Gaia helps in reconsidering the relations between two bodies of feminist theory—Deleuzian feminism and Marxist ecofeminism—that are rarely brought into conversation. On this basis, I explore what a feminist politics of composition with the earth might look like.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.22329/p.v11i1.4390</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="Schultz_2013">
        <article>
            <author>Colin Schultz</author>
            <title>Marcellus Shale fracking waste caused earthquakes in Ohio</title>
            <journal>Eos, Transactions American Geophysical Union</journal>
            <year>2013</year>
            <volume>94</volume>
            <number>33</number>
            <pages>296--296</pages>
            <month>aug</month>
            <abstract>Before January 2011, Youngstown, Ohio, had never had an earthquake since observations began in 1776. In December 2010 the Northstar 1 injection well came online; this well was built to pump wastewater produced by hydraulic fracturing projects in Pennsylvania into storage deep underground. In the year that followed, seismometers in and around Youngstown recorded 109 earthquakes—the strongest of the set being a magnitude 3.9 earthquake on 31 December 2011.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1002/2013EO330008</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="Hill_2021">
        <article>
            <author>Elaine Hill and Lala Ma</author>
            <title>The fracking concern with water quality</title>
            <journal>Science</journal>
            <year>2021</year>
            <volume>373</volume>
            <number>6557</number>
            <pages>853--854</pages>
            <month>aug</month>
            <abstract>Unconventional oil and gas development (UOGD) has revolutionized resource extraction over the past two and a half decades. Although these methods to recover oil and gas began in the 1980s, only recently have technological innovations in horizontal drilling and hydraulic fracturing (HF) made it financially feasible to extract resources from difficult-to-access rock formations with low permeability (1). These innovations have massively increased the availability of oil and gas resources for consumption, yielding energy cost savings, employment, and income (2). One estimate finds per household benefits to be about 4.9% of income annually (3). Many have cautioned that human and ecological health may be damaged by the negative environmental impacts that come with these benefits. On page 896 of this issue, Bonetti et al. (4) report that UOGD has increased salt concentrations in surface waters across the United States. The findings have broad implications for research and policy going forward.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1126/science.abk3433</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="Smith_Nonini_2016">
        <article>
            <author>Sandy Smith-Nonini</author>
            <title>The role of corporate oil and energy debt in creating the neoliberal era</title>
            <journal>Economic Anthropology</journal>
            <year>2016</year>
            <volume>3</volume>
            <number>1</number>
            <pages>57--67</pages>
            <month>jan</month>
            <abstract>This article examines the relationship between the United States’s rapid loss of energy sovereignty in the 1970s and the rise of speculative finance and
neoliberal ideology that reshaped global trade relationships. Prevailing academic analysis of the neoliberal economy understates the tight relationship
between the U.S. corporate state’s influence over oil markets and persistent U.S. global hegemony since the 1973 energy crisis. During the Keynesian
era, U.S. power was backed by actual geopolitical control over oil production, but after the 1970s, the influence of the so-called Washington Consensus
enforcing neoliberal policies derived in large part from leverage over international “energy debt” that propped up the U.S. dollar, allowing continued
capital accumulation by banks and corporations via financial speculation, while disguising global energy risk. The article thus examines the roles of
major U.S. oil companies in shaping neoliberal policies from which they benefited, the relationship of militarism to oil company profit, and the essential
role of speculative debt financing in permitting otherwise uneconomic production of fossil fuels with low “energy return on investment” in the new
era of climate change and resource limits.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1002/sea2.12044</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="Xie_2022">
        <article>
            <author>Yuanyu Xie and Meiyun Lin and Bertrand Decharme and Christine Delire and Larry W. Horowitz and David M. Lawrence and Fang Li and Roland S{\'{e}}f{\'{e}}rian</author>
            <title>Tripling of western {US} particulate pollution from wildfires in a warming climate</title>
            <journal>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</journal>
            <year>2022</year>
            <volume>119</volume>
            <number>14</number>
            <month>mar</month>
            <abstract>Record-setting fires in the western United States over the last decade caused severe air pollution, loss of human life, and property damage. Enhanced drought and increased biomass in a warmer climate may fuel larger and more frequent wildfires in the coming decades. Applying an empirical statistical model to fires projected by Earth System Models including climate–ecosystem–socioeconomic interactions, we show that fine particulate pollution over the US Pacific Northwest could double to triple during late summer to fall by the late 21st century under intermediate- and low-mitigation scenarios. The historic fires and resulting pollution extremes of 2017–2020 could occur every 3 to 5 y under 21st-century climate change, posing challenges for air quality management and threatening public health.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.2111372119</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="H_k_2010">
        <article>
            <author>Mikael Höök and Ugo Bardi and Lianyong Feng and Xiongqi Pang</author>
            <title>Development of oil formation theories and their importance for peak oil</title>
            <journal>Marine and Petroleum Geology</journal>
            <year>2010</year>
            <volume>27</volume>
            <number>9</number>
            <pages>1995--2004</pages>
            <month>oct</month>
            <abstract>This paper reviews the historical development of both biogenic and non-biogenic petroleum formation. It also examines the recent claim that the so-called “abiotic” oil formation theory undermines the concept of “peak oil,” i.e. the notion that world oil production is destined to reach a maximum that will be followed by an irreversible decline. We show that peak oil is first and foremost a matter of production flows. Consequently, the mechanism of oil formation does not strongly affect depletion. We would need to revise the theory beyond peak oil only for the extreme — and unlikely — hypothesis of abiotic petroleum formation.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.marpetgeo.2010.06.005</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="Thomas_2021">
        <article>
            <author>Cassidy Thomas and Elhom Gosink</author>
            <title>At the Intersection of Eco-Crises, Eco-Anxiety, and Political Turbulence: A Primer on Twenty-First Century Ecofascism</title>
            <journal>Perspectives on Global Development and Technology</journal>
            <year>2021</year>
            <volume>20</volume>
            <pages>30--54</pages>
            <month>mar</month>
            <abstract>This article explores the concept of ecofascism during the twenty-first century. In the midst of worsening ecological crises, a revival of ecofascist rhetoric and action has been observed. Despite this resurfacing, there is a lack of theorizing around the topic. This discussion will explore how the ecofascist label has been applied in different contexts historically, and the ways it may manifest in the twenty-first century. We hope that this stimulates conversation and awareness around ecofascism and serves as a guide to identify various ecofascist rhetorical tools, policies, and proposals.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1163/15691497-12341581</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="Schmidt_2022">
        <article>
            <author>Suzanne Schmidt and Sara Kildgaard and Huijuan Guo and Christine Beemelmanns and Michael Poulsen</author>
            <title>The chemical ecology of the fungus-farming termite symbiosis</title>
            <journal>Natural Product Reports</journal>
            <year>2022</year>
            <volume>39</volume>
            <number>2</number>
            <pages>231--248</pages>
            <abstract>Explorations of complex symbioses have often elucidated a plethora of previously undescribed chemical compounds that may serve ecological functions in signalling, communication or defence. A case in point is the subfamily of termites that cultivate a fungus as their primary food source and maintain complex bacterial communities, from which a series of novel compound discoveries have been made. Here, we summarise the origins and types of 375 compounds that have been discovered from the symbiosis over the past four decades and discuss the potential for synergistic actions between compounds within the complex chemical mixtures in which they exist. We go on to highlight how vastly underexplored the diversity and geographic distribution of the symbiosis is, which leaves ample potential for natural product discovery of compounds of both ecological and medical importance.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1039/D1NP00022E</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="Fronk_2022">
        <article>
            <author>David C. Fronk and Joel L. Sachs</author>
            <title>Symbiotic organs: the nexus of host{\textendash}microbe evolution</title>
            <journal>Trends in Ecology {\&amp;}amp$\mathsemicolon$ Evolution</journal>
            <year>2022</year>
            <volume>37</volume>
            <number>7</number>
            <pages>599--610</pages>
            <month>jul</month>
            <abstract>Symbiotic organs are host structures that house populations of beneficial microbes.
    Microbes within symbiotic organs provide a core set of mutualism services to hosts, including nitrogen fixation, bioluminescence, antimicrobial protection, nutrition, and vertical transmission to new hosts.
    Microbial communities are filtered by symbiotic organs, mediating which genotypes interact with hosts, gain host resources, and are subsequently passed on to new hosts.
    Growth and development of symbiotic organs imposes selection on microbial populations, altering their population structure, effective population size, opportunity for gene exchange, and genome architecture.
    Cooperation and conflict between microbes and host shape the development, morphology, and functions of symbiotic organs, and have emergent effects on individuality, heritability, and the stability of microbial mutualisms.

Diverse plants and animals have evolved specialized structures to filter and house beneficial microbes. These symbiotic organs form crucial points of exchange between host and symbiont, are often shaped by both partners, and exhibit features that facilitate a suite of microbial services. While symbiotic organs exhibit varied function, morphology, and developmental plasticity, they share core features linked to the evolutionary maintenance of beneficial symbiosis. Moreover, these organs can have a significant role in altering the demographic forces that shape microbial genomes, driving population bottlenecks and horizontal gene transfer (HGT). To advance our understanding of these ‘joint phenotypes’ across varied systems, future research must consider the emergent forces that can shape symbiotic organs, including fitness feedbacks and conflicts between interacting genomes.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tree.2022.02.014</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="Burke_2021">
        <article>
            <author>Ariane Burke and Matthew C. Peros and Colin D. Wren and Francesco S. R. Pausata and Julien Riel-Salvatore and Olivier Moine and Anne de Vernal and Masa Kageyama and Sol{\`{e}}ne Boisard</author>
            <title>The archaeology of climate change: The case for cultural diversity</title>
            <journal>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</journal>
            <year>2021</year>
            <volume>118</volume>
            <number>30</number>
            <month>jul</month>
            <abstract>Anthropogenic climate change is currently driving environmental transformation on a scale and at a pace that exceeds historical records. This represents an undeniably serious challenge to existing social, political, and economic systems. Humans have successfully faced similar challenges in the past, however. The archaeological record and Earth archives offer rare opportunities to observe the complex interaction between environmental and human systems under different climate regimes and at different spatial and temporal scales. The archaeology of climate change offers opportunities to identify the factors that promoted human resilience in the past and apply the knowledge gained to the present, contributing a much-needed, long-term perspective to climate research. One of the strengths of the archaeological record is the cultural diversity it encompasses, which offers alternatives to the solutions proposed from within the Western agro-industrial complex, which might not be viable cross-culturally. While contemporary climate discourse focuses on the importance of biodiversity, we highlight the importance of cultural diversity as a source of resilience.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.2108537118</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="Yao_2022">
        <article>
            <author>Song Yao and Kui Liu</author>
            <title>Actor-Network Theory: Insights into the Study of Social-Ecological Resilience</title>
            <journal>International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health</journal>
            <year>2022</year>
            <volume>19</volume>
            <number>24</number>
            <pages>16704</pages>
            <month>dec</month>
            <abstract>Actor-network theory, which emerged from science and technology studies in the 1980s, regards everything in the social and ecological systems as a continuous result of the network of relations where they are located. Social-ecological resilience, with its origins in systems ecology, focuses on the non-linear changing dynamics of social-ecological systems and their governance. Among them, social-ecological resilience study integrates different disciplines, backgrounds, and themes, which inevitably leads to the vagueness of its concept. Both actor-network theory and social-ecological resilience emphasize human-nature relationships and view social-ecological systems as dynamic and unpredictable “networks”. Therefore, this paper explored the potential conceptual or theoretical underpinnings that actor-network theory can provide in social-ecological resilience through interdisciplinary research. Specifically, a semi-structured interview was conducted with 30 fishing households from Chang-shan Archipelago in Northeastern China. The obtained interview data were analyzed through thematic analysis, and three main themes were generated, including “heterogeneous networks”, “agency”, and “translation”, which facilitated a reconceptualization of the three components of social-ecological resilience, namely, “linked social-ecological systems”, “changing dynamics” and “the ability to maintain resilience”, and also provided a new theoretical perspective on the adaptive governance of social-ecological systems.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.3390/ijerph192416704</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="wasson2013camino">
        <book>
            <author>Wasson, Robert Gordon and Hofmann, Albert and Ruck, Carl</author>
            <title>El camino a Eleusis</title>
            <publisher>FCE-Fondo de Cultura Económica</publisher>
            <year>2013</year>
            <isbn>968-16-0655-8</isbn>
            <url>https://d1wqtxts1xzle7.cloudfront.net/81546543/El_Camino_a_Eleusis_Una_solucion_al_enigma_de_los_misterios_Wasson_Hofmann_Ruck-libre.pdf?1646196192=&amp;response-content-disposition=inline%3B+filename%3DEl_Camino_a_Eleusis_R_Gordon_Wasson_Albe.pdf&amp;Expires=1692205340&amp;Signature=NBA1h4ifzIhJzSi0CVrGw0v0SfFCw72Cug35K6NHn8~YDA5b-QaJfMz~HbAHxodgvkROdYWNWRTePSJJULytfAyqiVqgNCDN~1qQL9~~X-KlZkzLdSQMPjyUz3q~p9IGQC-97kabGoQEeUg8gS6WR4EV7XZGlsVaUvdrzjAXrDP9mWebDysHDiP5ysJo3lhUM5uLKLe2fuUIWqbtm4BBINilEeWBndC6EUGXIrvaXC5JsfLkxKArPluFoHvCb7a327EnBDZ05JaUGonMBrMD0SVd-xcyuONBLDLbDhRMovOSFlUqblVq0PKaYFyjewzcXRzCRZ2vw7cgzVO-YHjSug__&amp;Key-Pair-Id=APKAJLOHF5GGSLRBV4ZA</url>
        </book>
    </entry>
    <entry id="hirsch2005index">
        <article>
            <author>Hirsch, Jorge E.</author>
            <title>An index to quantify an individual's scientific research output</title>
            <journal>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</journal>
            <year>2005</year>
            <volume>102</volume>
            <number>46</number>
            <pages>16569--16572</pages>
            <abstract>I propose the index h, defined as the number of papers with citation number ≥h, as a useful index to characterize the scientific output of a researcher.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.0507655102</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="Ma_2021">
        <article>
            <author>Bin Ma and Erinne Stirling and Yuanhui Liu and Kankan Zhao and Jizhong Zhou and Brajesh K. Singh and Caixian Tang and Randy A. Dahlgren and Jianming Xu</author>
            <title>Soil Biogeochemical Cycle Couplings Inferred from a Function-Taxon Network</title>
            <journal>Research</journal>
            <year>2021</year>
            <volume>2021</volume>
            <month>jan</month>
            <abstract>Soil biogeochemical cycles and their interconnections play a critical role in regulating functions and services of environmental systems. However, the coupling of soil biogeochemical processes with their mediating microbes remains poorly understood. Here, we identified key microbial taxa regulating soil biogeochemical processes by exploring biomarker genes and taxa of contigs assembled from metagenomes of forest soils collected along a latitudinal transect (18° N to 48° N) in eastern China. Among environmental and soil factors, soil pH was a sensitive indicator for functional gene composition and diversity. A function-taxon bipartite network inferred from metagenomic contigs identified the microbial taxa regulating coupled biogeochemical cycles between carbon and phosphorus, nitrogen and sulfur, and nitrogen and iron. Our results provide novel evidence for the coupling of soil biogeochemical cycles, identify key regulating microbes, and demonstrate the efficacy of a new approach to investigate the processes and microbial taxa regulating soil ecosystem functions.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.34133/2021/7102769</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="Yu_2021">
        <article>
            <author>Changxun Yu and Shurong Xie and Zhaoliang Song and Shaopan Xia and Mats E. {\AA}ström</author>
            <title>Biogeochemical cycling of iron (hydr-)oxides and its impact on organic carbon turnover in coastal wetlands: A global synthesis and perspective</title>
            <journal>Earth-Science Reviews</journal>
            <year>2021</year>
            <volume>218</volume>
            <pages>103658</pages>
            <month>jul</month>
            <abstract>Coastal wetlands host large and dynamic reservoirs of organic carbon (C) and are also biogeochemical hotspots for a wide range of Fe (hydr-)oxides with different chemical reactivities, properties, and functions. The cycling of these iron (hydr-)oxides is closely coupled to that of organic C, which in turn strongly influences the magnitude and dynamics of organic C turnover in these ecosystems. This review synthesizes and summarizes current knowledge of distribution, turnover, and controls of Fe (hydr-)oxides, as well as their ecological roles and impacts on organic C turnover in coastal wetland ecosystems globally. Regional hydro-geochemical processes and anthropogenic activities in the uplands as well as soil texture exert a first-order control on the abundance and distribution of Fe (hydr-)oxides in coastal wetland soils, while the activities of plant roots and macro-organisms act as important biological drivers for the formation, transformation, and turnover of Fe (hydr-)oxides as well as associated organic C in both rhizosphere/burrows and bulk soils. The reported rates of dissimilatory Fe reduction (DFeR) are correlated with incubation temperature and the sizes of reactive Fe(III) phases. However, the contributions of DFeR to total anaerobic carbon oxidation were found to be correlated only with the size of reactive Fe(III) pools, meaning that all the identified processes contributing to the accumulation and formation of Fe hydroxides could increase the importance of the DFeR-dominated respiratory pathway and suppress sulfate reduction and methanogenesis. Additionally, Fe plaques dominated by amorphous Fe hydroxides are formed and cycled in close interaction with the activities of wetland plant roots, and likely provide several important ecological functions and contribute to maintaining high levels of plant productivity in coastal wetlands under different environmental stresses. The features and findings presented in this review not only contribute to an improved understanding of the biogeochemical cycle and ecological roles of Fe (hydr-)oxides in coastal wetlands, but also provide a basis for future studies on some highlighted key research areas. Such future studies will further increase our ability to understand and predict how the size, stability, and turnover of Fe (hydr-)oxides and organic C in coastal wetlands will respond to and affect global climate change.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.earscirev.2021.103658</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="Schlesinger_2021">
        <article>
            <author>William H. Schlesinger and Emily M. Klein and Zhen Wang and Avner Vengosh</author>
            <title>Global Biogeochemical Cycle of Lithium</title>
            <journal>Global Biogeochemical Cycles</journal>
            <year>2021</year>
            <volume>35</volume>
            <number>8</number>
            <month>aug</month>
            <abstract>The total human mobilization of Li from the Earth's crust, &gt;1,000 × 109 g/year, is much larger than Li mobilized by the natural processes of chemical and mechanical weathering (94 and 132 × 109 g/year, respectively), representing a ∼500% perturbation of the global cycle of Li by human activities. The anthropogenic perturbation of the global Li cycle shows enhanced releases to freshwaters from oil-produced water (46 × 109 g/year), leaching of coal ash (7–20 × 109 g/year), and extraction of groundwaters (29 × 109 g/year). The sum of these anthropogenic sources more than doubles the natural transport of dissolved Li to the sea in rivers (69 × 109 g/year). Currently, releases from the excretion of therapeutic drugs and disposal of lithium-ion batteries are a small component of the transport of Li in rivers, although the latter may increase markedly as lithium-ion batteries dominant global energy storage. Human emissions of Li particles to the atmosphere—55 × 109 g/year from coal combustion—comprise about 38% of the emission of Li to the atmosphere from various sources. The inputs to the atmosphere are more than the estimated deposition of Li from the atmosphere, which is poorly constrained by available data.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1029/2021GB006999</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="Peng_2011">
        <article>
            <author>Junhua H. Peng and Dongfa Sun and Eviatar Nevo</author>
            <title>Domestication evolution, genetics and genomics in wheat</title>
            <journal>Molecular Breeding</journal>
            <year>2011</year>
            <volume>28</volume>
            <number>3</number>
            <pages>281--301</pages>
            <month>jul</month>
            <abstract>Domestication of plants and animals is the major factor underlying human civilization and is a gigantic evolutionary experiment of adaptation and speciation, generating incipient species. Wheat is one of the most important grain crops in the world, and consists mainly of two types: the hexaploid bread wheat (Triticum aestivum) accounting for about 95% of world wheat production, and the tetraploid durum wheat (T. durum) accounting for the other 5%. In this review, we summarize and discuss research on wheat domestication, mainly focusing on recent findings in genetics and genomics studies. T. aestivum originated from a cross between domesticated emmer wheat T. dicoccum and the goat grass Aegilops tauschii, most probably in the south and west of the Caspian Sea about 9,000 years ago. Wild emmer wheat has the same genome formula as durum wheat and has contributed two genomes to bread wheat, and is central to wheat domestication. Domestication has genetically not only transformed the brittle rachis, tenacious glume and non-free threshability, but also modified yield and yield components in wheat. Wheat domestication involves a limited number of chromosome regions, or domestication syndrome factors, though many relevant quantitative trait loci have been detected. On completion of the genome sequencing of diploid wild wheat (T. urartu or Ae. tauschii), domestication syndrome factors and other relevant genes could be isolated, and effects of wheat domestication could be determined. The achievements of domestication genetics and robust research programs in Triticeae genomics are of greatly help in conservation and exploitation of wheat germplasm and genetic improvement of wheat cultivars.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1007/s11032-011-9608-4</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="Lu_2020">
        <article>
            <author>Jianhong Lu and Xianqiang Mao and Mudan Wang and Zhengyan Liu and Peng Song</author>
            <title>Global and National Environmental Impacts of the {US}{\textendash}China Trade War</title>
            <journal>Environmental Science {\&amp;}amp$\mathsemicolon$ Technology</journal>
            <year>2020</year>
            <volume>54</volume>
            <number>24</number>
            <pages>16108--16118</pages>
            <month>nov</month>
            <abstract>The recent “US–China trade war” has aroused concern over trade-related environmental impacts. This study built a multiregional computable general equilibrium model to simulate environmental impacts of the “US–China trade war” under different scenarios of tariff and nontariff barriers and the battlefield spreading ranges. The present study found that although the trade war will cause a global economic downturn, which will seemingly reduce environmental pressure globally, global carbon emissions are expected to increase rather than decline. On the one hand, the CO2 emission increase caused by land-use changes in Brazil and Argentina will far exceed the emission reduction because of decreased global production. On the other hand, some countries/economies especially those developing countries such as Vietnam, Russia, and India will face emission increases driven by scale effects. Countries such as Korea, the UK, and France will enjoy a reduction in emissions driven by structural effects. China and the US will face a reduction in production and CO2 emissions, but their CO2 emission intensities will rise. The results remind us that as global production and supply chains are formed, it is important to closely monitor trade-related environmental impacts. Efforts should be made to balance the interests of trade and the environment.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.est.0c03863</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="Han_2021">
        <article>
            <author>Jingwei Han and Jianjun Miao and Gang Du and Dan Yan and Zhuang Miao</author>
            <title>Can market-oriented reform inhibit carbon dioxide emissions in China? A new perspective from factor market distortion</title>
            <journal>Sustainable Production and Consumption</journal>
            <year>2021</year>
            <volume>27</volume>
            <pages>1498--1513</pages>
            <month>jul</month>
            <abstract>To explore whether market-oriented reform can help reduce CO2 emissions, by adopting the spatial panel data model based on the provincial panel data of China during 2001-2017, this article empirically tests the impact of labor market distortion and capital market distortion on CO2 emissions. The main findings are yielded as follows. (1) The labor market distortion and capital market distortion are widespread in China. The high wages caused by the insufficient supply of labor and the low marginal output of labor due to the shortage of human capital stock are the main reason for the positive labor market distortion. The capital market distortion can be put down to the excessive interventions of the government on the allocation of capital. (2) The labor market distortion can enhance CO2 emissions, that is, promoting market-oriented reform in the labor market can curb CO2 emissions. (3) The connection between capital market distortion and CO2 emissions can be described as a U-shaped curve. The complete marketization of the capital market and excessive government intervention in the allocation of capital can both cause an increase in CO2 emissions. (4) Improving the marketization of the labor market is effective for reducing CO2 emissions in almost all provinces. In the central region, the capital market distortion can exacerbate CO2 emissions. However, in the western region, the governmental intervention on the allocation of capital can enable limited funds to more effectively move to environmentally friendly enterprises, and avoid these provinces becoming a pollution refuge. Based on these findings, this article goes into more detail on the policy implications.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.spc.2021.03.020</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="G_R_AM_2022">
        <article>
            <author>Selçuk Gürçam</author>
            <title>The Neoliberal Initiative of the Aviation Industry to Fight the Climate Crisis: Greenwashing</title>
            <journal>International Journal of Environment and Geoinformatics</journal>
            <year>2022</year>
            <volume>9</volume>
            <number>3</number>
            <pages>178--186</pages>
            <month>sep</month>
            <abstract>The global climate crisis deepening rapidly and turning into a severe security problem requires a global struggle. In this regard, the United Nations has initiated comprehensive negotiations for a long time, but the process has not achieved the desired level of success. Behind this failure lies neoliberalism and its institutions that dominate the global economic system. The aviation sector with rapid growth potential grows and develops around the aggressive strategies of neoliberalism. The developments in the aviation sector naturally affect the climate negatively at the same rate. In this context, the aviation industry adopting the policy of pretending to be environmentalist has ignored or covered up the environmental impacts to escape the pressure of the climate crisis and continued to grow around the deregulation principle of neoliberalism. This situation, called greenwashing, has been well adopted by the aviation industry. The current study deals with the greenwashing application, a strategical approach that the aviation industry has implemented against other environmental problems, especially the climate crisis. The study has revealed that the innovative projects of the aviation industry, such as electric airplanes, hydrogen-powered airplanes, biofuel studies, high-efficiency, etc., are highly nonfunctional. In conclusion, the study has emphasized that the aviation industry is not as innocent as pretended; their attempts to hide the sector-based pollution effects are unrealistic, and the sector-related climate crisis continues to increase.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.30897/ijegeo.1083921</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="Chen_2023">
        <article>
            <author>Liming Chen and Minda Ma and Xiwang Xiang</author>
            <title>Decarbonizing or illusion? How carbon emissions of commercial building operations change worldwide</title>
            <journal>Sustainable Cities and Society</journal>
            <year>2023</year>
            <volume>96</volume>
            <pages>104654</pages>
            <month>sep</month>
            <abstract>To lead the low-carbon transition in global buildings, this study is the first to use the generalized Divisia index method (GDIM) to identify the factors driving carbon emissions and assess the decarbonization performance in commercial building operations (CBOs) of sixteen countries during 2000–2019. Results show that (1) while the global carbon emissions from CBOs have increased at a modest rate of 0.9%/yr, this trend runs counter to the declining emissions in the U.S. (-1.1%/yr) and the significant growth in China (14.4%/yr), which can be attributed to the impact of economy-related factors. (2) The U.S. and China, as the largest emitters, contributed 66.8% of the samples’ decarbonization of CBOs (919.1 million tons of carbon dioxide). (3) Most countries’ CBOs had a decarbonization efficiency level of less than 10%, except for Spain (27.8%). Spain excelled in both areas of per capita and per floor area with an average efficiency of nearly 30%. Moreover, ridge regression successfully confirms the stability of GDIM results and it should be noted GDIM has limitations in characterizing the end-use activity. Overall, this study tracks the historical decarbonization of global CBOs and offers benchmarks for different emitters to forecast the dynamic of building emissions along with economic booms.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scs.2023.104654</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="mittelbach2019community">
        <inbook>
            <chapter>El crecimiento de la población y la dependencia de la densidad</chapter>
            <pages>63-80</pages>
            <year>2019</year>
            <author>Mittelbach, Gary G and McGill, Brian J</author>
            <bibtexkey>mittelbach2019community</bibtexkey>
            <publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
            <title>Community ecology</title>
        </inbook>
    </entry>
    <entry id="kropotkin2005apoyo">
        <inbook>
            <chapter>La ayuda mutua entre los animales</chapter>
            <pages>35-55</pages>
            <journal>Santiago de Chile: Instituto de Estudios Anarquistas</journal>
            <year>2005</year>
            <author>Kröpotkin, Pedro</author>
            <bibtexkey>kropotkin2005apoyo</bibtexkey>
            <publisher>Instituto de Estudios Anarquistas</publisher>
            <title>El apoyo mutuo: un factor de la evolución</title>
            <doi>https://users.resist.ca/~crisxyz/iea/biblioteca/pdf/Kropotkin.El%20apoyo%20mutuo.pdf</doi>
        </inbook>
    </entry>
    <entry id="LiFungico_2021">
        <article>
            <author>Huili Li and Yang Tian and Nelson Menolli and Lei Ye and Samantha C. Karunarathna and Jesus Perez-Moreno and Mohammad Mahmudur Rahman and Md Harunur Rashid and Pheng Phengsintham and Leela Rizal and Taiga Kasuya and Young Woon Lim and Arun Kumar Dutta and Abdul Nasir Khalid and Le Thanh Huyen and Marilen Parungao Balolong and Gautam Baruah and Sumedha Madawala and Naritsada Thongklang and Kevin D. Hyde and Paul M. Kirk and Jianchu Xu and Jun Sheng and Eric Boa and Peter E. Mortimer</author>
            <title>Reviewing the world's edible mushroom species: A new evidence-based classification system</title>
            <journal>Comprehensive Reviews in Food Science and Food Safety</journal>
            <year>2021</year>
            <volume>20</volume>
            <number>2</number>
            <pages>1982--2014</pages>
            <month>feb</month>
            <abstract>Wild mushrooms are a vital source of income and nutrition for many poor communities and of value to recreational foragers. Literature relating to the edibility of mushroom species continues to expand, driven by an increasing demand for wild mushrooms, a wider interest in foraging, and the study of traditional foods. Although numerous case reports have been published on edible mushrooms, doubt and confusion persist regarding which species are safe and suitable to consume. Case reports often differ, and the evidence supporting the stated properties of mushrooms can be incomplete or ambiguous. The need for greater clarity on edible species is further underlined by increases in mushroom-related poisonings. We propose a system for categorizing mushroom species and assigning a final edibility status. Using this system, we reviewed 2,786 mushroom species from 99 countries, accessing 9,783 case reports, from over 1,100 sources. We identified 2,189 edible species, of which 2,006 can be consumed safely, and a further 183 species which required some form of pretreatment prior to safe consumption or were associated with allergic reactions by some. We identified 471 species of uncertain edibility because of missing or incomplete evidence of consumption, and 76 unconfirmed species because of unresolved, differing opinions on edibility and toxicity. This is the most comprehensive list of edible mushrooms available to date, demonstrating the huge number of mushrooms species consumed. Our review highlights the need for further information on uncertain and clash species, and the need to present evidence in a clear, unambiguous, and consistent manner.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1111/1541-4337.12708</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="Nieminen_2020">
        <article>
            <author>Petteri Nieminen and Anne-Mari Mustonen</author>
            <title>Toxic Potential of Traditionally Consumed Mushroom Species{\textemdash}A Controversial Continuum with Many Unanswered Questions</title>
            <journal>Toxins</journal>
            <year>2020</year>
            <volume>12</volume>
            <number>10</number>
            <pages>639</pages>
            <month>oct</month>
            <abstract>Mushroom poisonings remain a significant cause of emergency medicine. While there are well-known species, such as Amanita phalloides, causing life-threatening poisonings, there is also accumulating evidence of poisonings related to species that have been considered edible and are traditionally consumed. In particular, the Tricholoma equestre group was reported to cause myotoxicity. In addition, particular wild mushrooms that are traditionally consumed especially in Asia and Eastern Europe have been subject to suspicion due to possible mutagenicity. Hitherto, the causative agents of these effects often remain to be determined, and toxicity studies have yielded contradictory results. Due to this, there is no consensus about the safety of these species. The issue is further complicated by difficulties in species identification and other possible sources of toxicity, such as microbiological contamination during storage, leading to sometimes opposite conclusions about the edibility of a species. This review focuses on existing data about these types of mushroom poisonings, including the still sparse knowledge about the causative chemical agents. In addition, the aim is to initiate a meta-discussion about the issue and to give some suggestions about how to approach the situation from the viewpoint of the collector, the researcher, and the practicing physician.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.3390/toxins12100639</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="Boyce_2015">
        <article>
            <author>Kylie J. Boyce and Alex Andrianopoulos</author>
            <title>Fungal dimorphism: the switch from hyphae to yeast is a specialized morphogenetic adaptation allowing colonization of a host</title>
            <journal>{FEMS} Microbiology Reviews</journal>
            <year>2015</year>
            <volume>39</volume>
            <number>6</number>
            <pages>797--811</pages>
            <month>aug</month>
            <abstract>The ability of pathogenic fungi to switch between a multicellular hyphal and unicellular yeast growth form is a tightly regulated process known as dimorphic switching. Dimorphic switching requires the fungus to sense and respond to the host environment and is essential for pathogenicity. This review will focus on the role of dimorphism in fungi commonly called thermally dimorphic fungi, which switch to a yeast growth form during infection. This group of phylogenetically diverse ascomycetes includes Talaromyces marneffei (recently renamed from Penicillium marneffei), Blastomyces dermatitidis (teleomorph Ajellomyces dermatitidis), Coccidioides species (C. immitis and C. posadasii), Histoplasma capsulatum (teleomorph Ajellomyces capsulatum), Paracoccidioides species (P. brasiliensis and P. lutzii) and Sporothrix schenckii (teleomorph Ophiostoma schenckii). This review will explore both the signalling pathways regulating the morphological transition and the transcriptional responses necessary for intracellular growth. The physiological requirements of yeast cells during infection will also be discussed, highlighting recent advances in the understanding of the role of iron and calcium acquisition during infection.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1093/femsre/fuv035</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="Wilson_2021">
        <article>
            <author>Andi M. Wilson and Raphael Gabriel and Steven W. Singer and Timo Schuerg and P. Markus Wilken and Magriet A. van der Nest and Michael J. Wingfield and Brenda D. Wingfield</author>
            <title>Doing it alone: Unisexual reproduction in filamentous ascomycete fungi</title>
            <journal>Fungal Biology Reviews</journal>
            <year>2021</year>
            <volume>35</volume>
            <pages>1--13</pages>
            <month>mar</month>
            <abstract>Unisexuality in fungi is the result of sexual reproduction in a single isolate that harbors genes associated with only a single mating type. To date, unisexual reproduction has been described in only three genera of filamentous fungi. Consequently, our understanding of this unusual pathway is limited. In this critical review, we compare genetic, genomic and transcriptomic data from a variety of unisexual species to similar data from their primary homothallic and heterothallic relatives. These analyses show that unisexual reproduction is likely derived from heterothallism via the mutation of genes involved in the initiation of sexual reproduction. We show that significant changes in mating-type genes, pheromone precursor genes and pheromone receptor genes are common in unisexual species, but that similar changes are not evident in their primary homothallic or heterothallic relatives. These findings are particularly notable because the unisexual species are accommodated in unrelated genera, illustrating that a similar transition to unisexuality has likely occurred independently in their lineages.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fbr.2020.12.003</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="Lin_2014">
        <article>
            <author>Xiaorong Lin and Joseph Heitman</author>
            <title>Mechanisms of Homothallism in Fungi and Transitions between Heterothallism and Homothallism</title>
            <year>2014</year>
            <pages>35--57</pages>
            <month>apr</month>
            <abstract>Sexual systems are classified into heterothallism or homothallism in fungi. This chapter focuses on examples of homothallic fungi and how their sexuality is governed. Conversions between heterothallic and homothallic sexual cycles are common evolutionary transitions in fungi, and whether homothallism evolved from heterothallism or vice versa is a controversial topic, and there is evidence supporting both hypotheses. The structural analyses of MAT sequences from homothallic and heterothallic Cochliobolus species support the hypothesis that heterothallism is the ancestral state in this genus. This unique arrangement of the Aspergillus nidulans MAT locus led to the proposal that homothallism is the ancestral state and that a transition from homothallism to heterothallism could have occurred in A. oryzae and A. fumigatus by gene loss, although neither species has a defined sexual cycle. Homothallic species may originate from heterothallic predecessors, and the homothallic lifestyle may have a selective advantage under certain ecological pressures. This hypothesis is consistent with the repeated occurrence of homothallism within numerous genera and the fact that many heterothallic fungi achieve homothallism in the form of pseudohomothallism by mating-type switching or packaging two compatible nuclei into one spore. Homothallic individuals contain all of the necessary genetic information for full sexual expression.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1128/9781555815837.ch3</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="Grognet_2015">
        <article>
            <author>Pierre Grognet and Philippe Silar</author>
            <title>Maintaining heterokaryosis in pseudo-homothallic fungi</title>
            <journal>Communicative {\&amp;}amp$\mathsemicolon$ Integrative Biology</journal>
            <year>2015</year>
            <volume>8</volume>
            <number>4</number>
            <pages>e994382</pages>
            <month>jul</month>
            <abstract>Among all the strategies displayed by fungi to reproduce and propagate, some species have adopted a peculiar behavior called pseudo-homothallism. Pseudo-homothallic fungi are true heterothallics, i.e., they need 2 genetically-compatible partners to mate, but they produce self-fertile mycelium in which the 2 different nuclei carrying the compatible mating types are present. This lifestyle not only enables the fungus to reproduce without finding a compatible partner, but also to cross with any mate it may encounter. However, to be fully functional, pseudo-homothallism requires maintaining heterokaryosis at every stage of the life cycle. We recently showed that neither the structure of the mating-type locus nor hybrid-enhancing effect due to the presence of the 2 mating types accounts for the maintenance of heterokaryosis in the pseudo-homothallic fungus P. anserina. In this addendum, we summarize the mechanisms creating heterokaryosis in P. anserina and 2 other well-known pseudo-homothallic fungi, Neurospora tetrasperma and Agaricus bisporus. We also discuss mechanisms potentially involved in maintaining heterokaryosis in these 3 species.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.4161/19420889.2014.994382</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="Reinhardt_2021">
        <article>
            <author>Didier Reinhardt and Christophe Roux and Nicolas Corradi and Antonio Di Pietro</author>
            <title>Lineage-Specific Genes and Cryptic Sex: Parallels and Differences between Arbuscular Mycorrhizal Fungi and Fungal Pathogens</title>
            <journal>Trends in Plant Science</journal>
            <year>2021</year>
            <volume>26</volume>
            <number>2</number>
            <pages>111--123</pages>
            <month>feb</month>
            <abstract>Genome analysis in arbuscular mycorrhizal fungi (AMF) reveals intraindividual nuclear homogeneity combined with high interstrain diversity.
 The high number of lineage-specific (LS) genes in AMF genomes is reminiscent of the rapidly evolving LS regions found in plant pathogens. These regions encode secreted effectors and other virulence factors, as well as an expanded set of signaling components such as protein kinases, suggesting a similar role in perception and interaction with the abiotic and biotic environment in AMF. Genomes of AMF and fungal pathogens exhibit parallels in the amplification of gene families related to signaling; by contrast, predicted secreted effector genes of AM tend to be more conserved (encoded by core genes), while effectors of pathogens are often encoded by LS genes.
AMF retain most of the genetic machinery required for sex, show evidence of ongoing recombination, and can form pseudo-dikaryons. However, the existence of meiotic cells or other (para)sexual stages has yet to be experimentally confirmed.
Arbuscular mycorrhizal fungi (AMF) live as obligate root symbionts on almost all land plants. They have long been regarded as ancient asexuals that have propagated clonally for millions of years. However, genomic studies in Rhizophagus irregularis and other AMF revealed many features indicative of sex. Surprisingly, comparative genomics of conspecific isolates of R. irregularis revealed an unexpected interstrain diversity, suggesting that AMF carry a high number of lineage-specific (LS) genes. Intriguingly, cryptic sex and LS genomic regions have previously been reported in a number of fungal pathogens of plants and humans. Here, we discuss these genomic similarities and highlight their potential relevance for AMF adaptation to the environment and for symbiotic functioning.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tplants.2020.09.006</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="nikkola2022experiences">
        <article>
            <author>Tiina Nikkola and Tuomas Tervasmäki</author>
            <title>Experiences of arbitrary management among Finnish academics in an era of academic capitalism</title>
            <journal>Journal of Education Policy</journal>
            <year>2020</year>
            <volume>37</volume>
            <number>4</number>
            <pages>548--568</pages>
            <month>dec</month>
            <abstract>For the last two decades, Finnish universities have faced the implementation of new systems of control and undergone dramatic changes that have worsened academic working conditions – such as corporatisation and budget cuts. This article explores Finnish academics’ experiences of university reforms with a special focus on the consequences it has had in terms of organisational socio-dynamics. We adapt Glynos and Howarth’s logics of critical explanation and apply this theoretical framework to analyse the interviews of academics who, against their own will, did not have their contracts renewed. This approach describes, explains, and criticises the logics – which are social, political and fantasmatic – behind the existence, continuation, and transformation of practices that are very real. Our research findings suggest that there are situations in which experiences of opaque management may occur at university. Academics often found the decision-making processes to be unpredictable and ambiguous, leading to a precarious working atmosphere. Combining the logics approach with micro-level data analysis, we developed the concept of arbitrary management, offering new perspectives for understanding the mediation between social practices and structural reforms. This micro-political analysis provides a new take on how ideologies operate at university in an era of academic capitalism.</abstract>
            <doi>https://doi.org/10.1080/02680939.2020.1854350</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="FactoMineR">
        <article>
            <author>Sébastien Lê and Julie Josse and François Husson</author>
            <title>FactoMineR: An R Package for Multivariate Analysis</title>
            <journal>Journal of Statistical Software</journal>
            <year>2008</year>
            <volume>25</volume>
            <number>1</number>
            <abstract>In this article, we present FactoMineR an R package dedicated to multivariate data analysis. The main features of this package is the possibility to take into account different types of variables (quantitative or categorical), different types of structure on the data (a partition on the variables, a hierarchy on the variables, a partition on the individuals) and finally supplementary information (supplementary individuals and variables). Moreover, the dimensions issued from the different exploratory data analyses can be automatically described by quantitative and/or categorical variables. Numerous graphics are also available with various options. Finally, a graphical user interface is implemented within the Rcmdr environment in order to propose an user friendly package.</abstract>
            <doi>10.18637/jss.v025.i01</doi>
        </article>
    </entry>
    <entry id="factoextra">
        <manual>
            <author>Alboukadel Kassambara and Fabian Mundt</author>
            <title>factoextra: Extract and Visualize the Results of Multivariate Data Analyses</title>
            <year>2020</year>
            <note>R package version 1.0.7</note>
            <url>https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=factoextra</url>
        </manual>
    </entry>
</file>
